<div class="Course"><a name="100"/><a name="AAS100"/><h4 class="crsname">AAS 100. Introduction to African American Studies.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines African American history and culture through four themes: fragmentation, exclusion, resistance, and community. Particular attention is given to the diversity of cultures in the African diaspora in the Americas. Not open to students who have received credit for African American Studies 140A. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="119"/><a name="AA/AC119"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/AC 119. Cultural Politics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the relationship of culture to politics. It introduces the study of struggles to acquire, maintain, or resist power and gives particular attention to the role culture plays in reproducing and contesting social divisions of class, race, gender, and sexuality. Lectures and discussion incorporate film, music, and fiction in order to evaluate the connection between cultural practices and politics.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121J"/><a name="AA/EN121J"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/EN 121J. African American Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This introductory course traces the development of a distinct African American literary tradition by focusing on the call-and-response pattern of slavery through the civil rights, feminist, and Black Power liberation movements. Students examine the music, oratory, letters, poems, essays, slave narratives, autobiographies, fiction, and plays by Americans of African descent. Two essential questions shape this course: What is the role of African American literature in the cultural identity and collective struggle of black people, and what should that role be? What themes, tropes, and forms connect these texts, authors, and movements into a coherent living tradition? Enrollment limited to 25. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C085">Language and Literacy (C085)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121X"/><a name="AA/EN121X"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/EN 121X. Music and Metaphor: The Sounds in African American Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">While African American musical traditions command attention on stages across the world, they have a unique home in African American literature. This course explores folk, sacred, blues, jazz, and hip-hop music as aesthetic and sociopolitical resources for African American authors. Course texts may include poetry, drama, fiction, criticism, and theory. Authors include Sterling Plumpp, Toni Morrison, Jayne Cortez, Albert Murray, W. E. B. Du Bois, Zora Neale Hurston, Larry Neal, and Ralph Ellison. Not open to students who have received credit for First-Year Seminars 287. Enrollment limited to 25. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="162"/><a name="AA/RH162"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/RH 162. White Redemption: Cinema and the Co-optation of African American History.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Since its origins in the early twentieth century, film has debated how to represent black suffering. This course examines one aspect of that debate: the persistent themes of white goodness, innocence, and blamelessness in films that are allegedly about black history and culture. Historical and cultural topics examined in film include the enslavement of Africans, Reconstruction, and the civil rights movement. Particular attention is given to films in the interracial male-buddy genre.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Normally offered every year. C. Nero.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C036">Color: Sight and Perception (C036)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C019">Film and Media Studies (C019)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C040">Popular Culture (C040)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="201"/><a name="AA/WS201"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/WS 201. Black Feminist Thought.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">While focusing primarily on African American women, this interdisciplinary course surveys historical, intellectual, political, and cultural contributions as well as literary, filmic, and artistic representations of women throughout the Black Atlantic.  Using perspectives from the social sciences (especially history, anthropology, and sociology), the humanities (particularly literature), and critical race, womanist/black feminist, and queer theories, students examine experiences and depictions of women of African descent.  The class pays particular attention to developing knowledge and understanding of black women's 1) experiences of enslavement and colonization; 2) involvement in liberation movements; 3) efforts at self-definition and self-sufficiency; 4) social and political activism; and 5) production of modes of analysis at the junctures or articulations of race, gender, sexuality, and class. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every year. S. Houchins.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="212"/><a name="AA/EN212"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/EN 212. Black Lesbian and Gay Literatures.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines black lesbian and gay literatures in English from Africa, the Caribbean, the United Kingdom, the United States, and Canada. Students are introduced to critical and historical approaches for analyzing literature about black queer sensibilities. Open to first-year students.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> C. Nero.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C085">Language and Literacy (C085)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="223"/><a name="AA/EN223"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/EN 223. Survey of Literature of the Caribbean.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the literatures of the African diaspora in the Caribbean and the Caribbean diaspora in Canada, the United States, the United Kingdom, and France. Some texts are drawn from Anglophone authors such as Lamming, Anthony, Walcott, Brodber, Danticat, Lovelace, Brathwaite, and Denis Williams; others, from Francophone and Hispanophone writers, including Guillen, Carpentier, Cond&#233;, Chamoiseau, Depestre, Ferr&#233;, and Morej&#243;n. The course places each work in its historical, political, and anthropological contexts. Students are introduced to a number of critical theories and methodologies with which to analyze the works, including poststructuralist, Marxist, Pan-African, postcolonial, and feminist. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. S. Houchins.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="235"/><a name="INDS235"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 235. The Politics of Pleasure and Desire: Women's Independent and Third Cinema and Video from the African Diaspora.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines independent and Third Cinema, and some written texts by women of African descent using contemporary theories of female pleasure and desire. By viewing and reading these cultural productions drawn from "high" and "low" culture in the light of a variety of film theories (e.g., feminist, womanist/black feminist, postcolonial, diasporic) as well as race-critical, feminist, and cultural theories, students explore the "textual" strategies that construct black female representations, and Afra-diasporic authors/directors and audiences as subjects and as agents of political change. Cross-listed in African American studies, rhetoric, and women and gender studies. Open to first-year students. S. Houchins.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C022">Considering Africa (C022)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C019">Film and Media Studies (C019)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="243"/><a name="AA/HI243"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/HI 243. African American History.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">People of African heritage in this country have been described as both "omni-Americans" and a distinctive cultural "nation within a nation." The course explores this apparent paradox using primary and interpretive sources, including oral and written biography, music, fiction, and social history. It examines key issues, recurrent themes, conflicting strategies, and influential personalities in African Americans' quest for freedom and security. It surveys black American history from seventeenth-century African roots to current problems that remain in building an egalitarian, multiracial society for the future. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. (United States.) H. Jensen.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C037">Identity, Race, and Ethnicity (C037)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="249"/><a name="AA/MU249"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/MU 249. African American Popular Music.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The history of the twentieth century can be understood in terms of the increasing African-Americanization of music in the West. The rapid emergence and dissemination of African American music made possible through recording technologies has helped to bring about radical cultural change: it has subverted received wisdoms about race, gender, and sexuality, and has fundamentally altered our relationship to time, to our bodies, to our most basic cultural priorities. This course explores some crucial moments in the history of this African-Americanization of popular music and helps  students develop an understanding of the relationship between musical sound and cultural practice. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. D. Chapman.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C080">Music and Culture (C080)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C040">Popular Culture (C040)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="250"/><a name="INDS250"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 250. Interdisciplinary Studies: Methods and Modes of Inquiry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Interdisciplinarity involves more than a meeting of disciplines. Practitioners stretch methodological norms and reach across disciplinary boundaries. Through examination of a single topic, this course introduces students to interdisciplinary methods of analysis. Students examine what practitioners actually do and work to become practitioners themselves. Prerequisite(s): African American Studies 100 or 140A or Women and Gender Studies 100, and one other course in African American studies, American cultural studies, or women and gender studies. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and women and gender studies. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="251"/><a name="AA/AN251"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/AN 251. Imagining the Caribbean.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">One anthropologist writing about the Caribbean asserts: "Nowhere else in the universe can one look with such certainty into the past and discern the outlines of an undisclosed future." Caribbean social systems bore the full impact of Western imperial expansion yet have adjusted to it in resilient and creative ways. The course surveys and interprets aspects of Caribbean life, and the ways in which they have been represented, drawing on a variety of sources&#8212;historical, ethnographic, literary, and visual. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 20. Normally offered every year. C. Carnegie.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C026">Culture and Meaning (C026)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C072">Latin American Studies (C072)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="252"/><a name="AA/DN252"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/DN 252. Contemporary Issues in Dance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on current dance works and some of the issues that inform contemporary dance practices. Discussions include the ways in which choreographers, performers, and societies confront matters of political climate, cultural diversity, entertainment, globalization, and the politicized human body in dance. Open to first-year students.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="253"/><a name="AA/EN253"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/EN 253. The African American Novel.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An examination of the African American novel from its beginnings in the mid-1800s to the present. Issues addressed include a consideration of folk influences on the genre, its roots in the slave narrative tradition, its relation to Euro-American texts and culture, and the "difference" that gender as well as race makes in determining narrative form. Readings include narratives selected from among the works of such writers as Douglass, Jacobs, Wilson, Delany, Hopkins, Harper, Chesnutt, Johnson, Toomer, Larsen, Hurston, Wright, Petry, Ellison, Baldwin, Walker, Morrison, Marshall, and Reed. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C037">Identity, Race, and Ethnicity (C037)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="257"/><a name="INDS257"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 257. African American Women's History and Social Transformation.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the political, social, and cultural traditions African American women have created from slavery to the current moment, notably the influence of African American women on the major social movements of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries including abolition, woman's suffrage, the club movement, women's liberation, the black arts movement, the civil rights movement, and Black Power. Through novels, plays, autobiography, music, and nonfiction produced by and about African American women, students explore a range of intellectual and cultural traditions. Recommended background: one course in women and gender studies and/or one course in African American studies.  Cross-listed in African American studies, politics, and women and gender studies. Not open to students who have received credit for African American Studies/Women and Gender Studies 257. Not open to students who have received credit for AA/WS 257. Enrollment limited to 30. (Identities and Interests.) (Institutional Politics.) M. Plastas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="268"/><a name="AA/EN268"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/EN 268. Survey of Literatures of Africa.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores folklore, myths, and literary texts of the African continent. These include works written by Anglophone authors such as Achebe, Soyinka, Ngugi, Vera, Njau, Nwapa, and Head; those drawn from oral traditions of indigenous languages transcribed into English, such as <span class="cite">The Mwindo Epic</span> and <span class="cite">The Sundiata</span>; and those written by Lusophone and Francophone authors including B&#226;, Senghor, Liking, Neto, Mahfouz, and Kafunkeno. The course contextualizes each work historically, politically, and anthropologically. Students are introduced to a number of critical theories and methodologies with which to analyze the works, such as poststructural, Marxist, Pan-African, postcolonial, and feminist. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. S. Houchins.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C022">Considering Africa (C022)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="292"/><a name="AA/AV292"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/AV 292. Introduction to African Art.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the royal and religious arts of sub-Saharan Africa. The arts commissioned by African kingdoms and royal individuals to define royal identity are explored, as well as the ways in which these arts have been interpreted by the populace. In addition, the course addresses the arts related to religion, many of which interface with arts in the royal context. This includes discussions of divination and religious belief systems, arts related to spirit possession, the role of art in communicating with another realm, and the ways that religious arts have been affected by missionaries, colonialism, and postcolonialism. Not open to students who have received credit for Art and Visual Culture 292. Open to first-year students. A. Bessire.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C022">Considering Africa (C022)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="294"/><a name="AA/AV294"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/AV 294. Religious Arts of the African Diaspora.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the religious arts of the African diaspora. The arts related to the religious traditions of Candombl&#233;, Lucum&#237; (Santer&#237;a), Rastafarianism, Vodun, and Kongo-derived religions are explored through a multidisciplinary lens. Contemporary visual culture is discussed in addition to arts created for the purpose of worship or memory, such as sculptural figures, altars, garments, and yard shows. In exploring these arts of the diaspora, the course considers and challenges constructions of race, ethnicity, and Africanicity from insiders' and outsiders' perspectives. Not open to students who have received credit for African American Studies/Art and Visual Culture s20. Enrollment limited to 20. A. Bessire.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C022">Considering Africa (C022)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C083">Material Culture (C083)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="315"/><a name="INDS315"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 315. African American Philosophers.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on how African American philosophers confront and address philosophical problems. Students consider the relationship between the black experience and traditional themes in Western philosophy. Attention is also given to the motivations and context sustaining African American philosophers. Recommended background: African American Studies 100 or 140A or African American Studies/American Cultural Studies 119. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and philosophy. Not open to students who have received credit for Interdisciplinary Studies 165. Enrollment limited to 15. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="325"/><a name="INDS325"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 325. Black Feminist Literary Theory and Practice.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar examines literary theories that address the representation and construction of race, gender, and sexuality, particularly, but not exclusively, theories formulated and articulated by Afra-diasporic women such as Spillers, Ogunyemi, Henderson, Valerie Smith, McDowell, Busia, Lubiano, and Davies. Students not only analyze theoretical essays but also use the theories as lenses through which to explore literary productions of women writers of Africa and the African diaspora in Europe and in the Americas, including Philip, Dangarembga, Morrison, Herron, Gayle Jones, Head, Cond&#233;, Brodber, Brand, Merle Collins, and Harriet Wilson. Cross-listed in African American studies, English, and women and gender studies. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Enrollment limited to 15. (Critical thinking.) S. Houchins.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C060">Women and Writing (C060)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="342"/><a name="INDS342"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 342. Performance, Narrative, and the Body.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the politics of the body through the  inter/transdisciplinary frames of the narrative and performance, including the specific ways performance and narrative theories of the body and cultural practices operate in everyday life and social formations. Students examine how the "body" is performed and how narrative is constructed in a variety of different contexts such as race, gender, disease, sexuality, and culture. The course places narrative and performance at the center (rather than the margins) of inquiry, asking how far and how deeply performativity reaches into our lives and how performances construct our identities, differences, and our bodies: who we are and who we can become. Recommended background: course work in African American studies, American cultural studies, anthropology, politics, sociology, or women and gender studies. Cross-listed in African American studies, anthropology, and women and gender studies. Enrollment limited to 15. M. Beasley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C037">Identity, Race, and Ethnicity (C037)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C085">Language and Literacy (C085)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="AAS360"/><h4 class="crsname">AAS 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="390E"/><a name="AA/HI390E"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/HI 390E. African Slavery in the Americas.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Of the millions of immigrants who arrived in North and South America during the colonial period, the majority came not from Europe but from Africa. They came not for freedom but as human property, facing a lifetime of bondage for themselves and their offspring. Far from being the "peculiar institution" that whites in the U.S. South called it, slavery existed throughout the Americas before its abolition in the nineteenth century. By reading contemporary scholarship and examining such primary sources as music, letters, autobiographies, and material artifacts, students gain a sense of the ways Africans and African Americans survived and influenced an institution that sought to deny their humanity.  Enrollment limited to 15. (United States.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> J. Hall.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C066">Early Modern World (C066)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="390F"/><a name="AAS390F"/><h4 class="crsname">AAS 390F. The Afro-Hispanic Diaspora.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The 500-year presence of Afrodescendants in the Spanish-speaking world has produced a significant body of literature by blacks and about blacks. Spanish America was the main destination of the African diaspora. Afro-Hispanic writers attest to the struggle for freedom and the abolition of slavery. Their literature shows how the participation of blacks in the wars of Latin American independence was a struggle for their emancipation. Afro-Hispanic writers in Spain, the Americas, and Africa use their art and ideas to address the postnational migrations of the twenty-first century, a diaspora that has not ceased. This course meets jointly, once a week, with Spanish 490F. Recommended background: African American Studies 100 or 140A. B. Fra-Molinero.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C016">Bridging <span class="em">El Atl&#225;ntico</span> (C016)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C059">Colonialism (C059)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="391C"/><a name="AA/RH391C"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/RH 391C. The Harlem Renaissance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the New Negro Movement and the extraordinary creativity in the arts and in other aspects of intellectual life by African Americans in the 1920s and 1930s.  Although this cultural phenomenon was national in scope, most scholars agree that New York City, and Harlem in particular, was its epicenter. Topics include racial, gender, and cultural identities in literature, theater, the performing and visual arts; the formation of black queer culture; and the role in promoting the arts by political organizations such as the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) and Marcus Garvey's Universal Negro Improvement Association (UNIA). Prerequisite(s): one of the following: African American Studies 100 or 140 or African American Studies/Rhetoric 162. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> C. Nero.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395Z"/><a name="AA/EN395Z"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/EN 395Z. African American Literature and the Bible.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Bible is unmatched in its influence on African American literary and cultural traditions. No other book has inspired such a broad scope of oral and written work. From explorations of the Exodus narrative to the Gospel writers' parables of Jesus, this course examines the way Hebrew and Christian biblical texts have inspired African American artists. Beginning with oral traditions such as spirituals and sermons, students then consider the Bible's role in scribal literacy and political discourse, and conclude with its impact on contemporary writers. Students combine interpretation of biblical texts and course readings with literary/cultural theory and criticism. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English or African American studies course. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Critical thinking.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="AAS457"/><h4 class="crsname">AAS 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The research and writing of an extended essay or report, or the completion of a creative project, under the supervision of a faculty member. Students register for African American Studies 457 in the fall semester and for African American Studies 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both African American Studies 457 and 458.   <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457, 458"/><a name="AAS457, 458"/><h4 class="crsname">AAS 457, 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The research and writing of an extended essay or report, or the completion of a creative project, under the supervision of a faculty member. Students register for African American Studies 457 in the fall semester and for African American Studies 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both African American Studies 457 and 458.   <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="AAS458"/><h4 class="crsname">AAS 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The research and writing of an extended essay or report, or the completion of a creative project, under the supervision of a faculty member. Students register for African American Studies 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both African American Studies 457 and 458.   <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s16"/><a name="AA/ACs16"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/AC s16. <span class="em">The Wire</span>: The City and Race in Popular Culture.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on the HBO series <span class="cite">The Wire</span>. Students discuss the episodes in terms of their narrative structure and content as well as cinematic techniques including shot sequence, lighting, camera angle, editing, and transitional devices. They also explore some of the sociopolitical issues this series examines: poverty, unemployment, the drug trade, public education, the decline of newspapers, and public housing. The intersection of race, gender, sexuality, and class serves as the lens through which they scrutinize these topics. Enrollment limited to 20. S. Houchins.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C019">Film and Media Studies (C019)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s19"/><a name="INDSs19"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS s19. Food, Culture, and Performance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This interdisciplinary seminar examines the idea of cultural engagement through food. Students explore the meanings of food and eating across cultures, with particular attention to how people define themselves socially, symbolically, and politically through food consumption practices. Drawing from cultural, critical, and performance theories, students engage in the dialectics of cultural exchange and the fluidity of identity; they interrogate conceptions of desire and consumption. The course develops research and writing skills, introduces visual and performance theories of culture, and fosters an understanding of the importance of food and its relationship to identity construction, histories, and cultural literacy. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, anthropology, and women and gender studies. Enrollment limited to 20. M. Beasley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s20"/><a name="AA/AVs20"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/AV s20. Religious Arts of the African Diaspora.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the religious arts of the African diaspora. The arts related to the religious traditions of Candombl&#233;, Lucum&#237; (Santer&#237;a), Rastafarianism, Vodun, and Kongo-derived religions are explored through a multidisciplinary lens. Contemporary visual culture is discussed in addition to arts created for the purpose of worship or memory, such as sculptural figures, altars, garments, and yard shows. A short trip to New York City to visit sites of these arts is an integral part of the course. In exploring these arts of the diaspora, the course considers and challenges constructions of race, ethnicity, and Africanicity from insiders' and outsiders' perspectives. Not open to students who have received credit for African American Studies/Art and Visual Culture 294. Enrollment limited to 15. A. Bessire.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C022">Considering Africa (C022)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s28"/><a name="AA/ANs28"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/AN s28. Cultural Production and Social Context, Jamaica.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Although Jamaica's artistic and popular culture enjoys international acclaim, it is at the same time often misunderstood. This course affords students an opportunity to investigate a range of Jamaican cultural practices within the context of the specific social, historical, and political matrices in which they are generated and received. This course begins with a preliminary introduction/orientation in Lewiston. In Jamaica, regular seminar meetings are supplemented by guest speakers and visits with writers and artists. In addition, each student carries out an individual research project using both textual and ethnographic methods of inquiry. Recommended background: coursework on the Caribbean or in African American studies. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. C. Carnegie.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C026">Culture and Meaning (C026)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s33"/><a name="AA/WSs33"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/WS s33. Reading Toni Morrison.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course surveys the writing of Nobel laureate Toni Morrison. Texts are selected from her novels, essays, drama, children's literature, and drama and also include criticism written about her work by other scholars. Prerequisite(s): one of the following: African American Studies 100 or 140A, African American Studies/English 225, English 294 or 295,  English/Women and Gender Studies 297 or 395. Not open to students who have received credit for African American Studies/Women and Gender Studies s32. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 15. S. Houchins.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="AASs50"/><h4 class="crsname">AAS s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
