<div class="Course"><a name="100"/><a name="ACS100"/><h4 class="crsname">ACS 100. Introduction to American Cultural Studies.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to the different methods and perspectives of cultural studies within an American context. The course considers the separate evolution of American studies and cultural studies in the academy, and considers how cultural studies provides a lens through which to investigate dynamic American identities, institutions, and communities. Of particular concern is how differences such as race, gender, class, ethnicity, and sexuality are constructed and expressed in diverse settings, and how they connect to the deployment of power. Enrollment limited to 35. Normally offered every other year. M. Bruce.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="119"/><a name="AA/AC119"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/AC 119. Cultural Politics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the relationship of culture to politics. It introduces the study of struggles to acquire, maintain, or resist power and gives particular attention to the role culture plays in reproducing and contesting social divisions of class, race, gender, and sexuality. Lectures and discussion incorporate film, music, and fiction in order to evaluate the connection between cultural practices and politics.  Not open to students who have received credit for Political Science 119. Normally offered every year. J. McClendon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="215"/><a name="INDS215"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 215. African American Culture through Sports.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Sports in African American life have served in a variety of ways to offer a means for social, economic, cultural, and even political advancement. This unit examines how sports have historically formed and contemporaneously shape the contours of African  American culture. Particular attention is given to such questions as the ethical dimension of segregation, the locus of gender equity, cultural images, and their political effects for African American athletes and the African American community. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and philosophy. Not open to students who have received credit for Interdisciplinary Studies s18. Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. J. McClendon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="220"/><a name="ACS220"/><h4 class="crsname">ACS 220. Fieldwork in American Cultural Studies.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Central to the Program in American Cultural Studies is the examination of and engagement with diverse American communities. Students in this course first consider their own positions, identities, and privileges within America, and then, using gender, class, and race analysis, they investigate the historical cultures of the College and the Lewiston community. In cooperation with the Harward Center for Community Partnerships, students also work in service-oriented agencies. Besides extensive fieldwork, students participate in weekly seminar discussions, and prepare a research paper relevant to their experience. Enrollment limited to 12. Normally offered every year. M. Creighton.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="240"/><a name="INDS240"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 240. Theory and Method in African American Studies.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course addresses the relationship between political culture and cultural politics within African American studies. Particular attention is paid to the contending theories of cultural criticism. Cornel West, Molefi Asante, Patricia Hill Collins, Angela Davis, bell hooks, Maramba Ani, and Henry Louis Gates Jr. are some of the theorists under review. Recommended background: African American Studies/American Cultural Studies 119 or significant work in politics, American cultural studies, or African American studies. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and philosophy. Not open to students who have received credit for American Cultural Studies 240 or Political Science 240. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 50. Offered with varying frequency. J. McClendon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="250"/><a name="INDS250"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 250. Interdisciplinary Studies: Methods and Modes of Inquiry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Interdisciplinarity involves more than a meeting of disciplines. Practitioners stretch methodological norms and reach across disciplinary boundaries. Through examination of a single topic, this course introduces students to interdisciplinary methods of analysis. Students examine what practitioners actually do and work to become practitioners themselves. Prerequisite(s): African American Studies 140A or Women and Gender Studies 100, and one other course in African American studies, American cultural studies, or women and gender studies. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and women and gender studies. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="260"/><a name="INDS260"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 260. United States Latina/Chicana Writings.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course rests on two conceptual underpinnings: Gloria Anzald&#250;a's <span class="cite">Neueva Mestiza</span> and the more recent "<span class="cite">U.S. Pan-latinidad</span>" postulated by the Latina Feminist Group. The literary and theoretical production of Chicanas and Latinas is examined through these lenses. Particular attention is given to developing a working knowledge of the key historical and cultural discourses engaged by these writings and the various contemporary United States Latina and Chicana positionalities vis-&#224;-vis popular ethnic representations. The course also examines the function given to marketable cultural productions depending on the different agents involved. Cross-listed in American cultural studies, Spanish, and women and gender studies. Open to first-year students. Offered with varying frequency. C. Aburto Guzm&#225;n.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="291"/><a name="INDS291"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 291. Exhibiting Cultures.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the politics of exhibiting cultures. Each week students analyze specific exhibitions of cultural artifacts, visual culture, and the cultural body as a means to evaluate the larger issues surrounding such displays. These include issues of race, colonialism, postcolonialism, and curatorial authority in relation to the politics of exhibiting cultures. A field trip to analyze an exhibition is a critical part of the students' experience in the course. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and art and visual culture. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="339"/><a name="INDS339"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 339. Africana Thought and Practice.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar examines in depth a broad range of black thought. Students consider the various philosophical problems and the theoretical issues and practical solutions offered by such scholar/activists as W. E. B. Du Bois, Marcus Garvey, Kwame Nkrumah, Claudia Jones, C. L. R. James, Leopold Senghor, Amilcar Cabrah, Charlotta Bass, Lucy Parsons, Walter Rodney, and Frantz Fanon. Recommended background: a course on the Africana world, or a course in philosophy or political theory. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and philosophy. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. J. McClendon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="ACS360"/><h4 class="crsname">ACS 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="363"/><a name="AC/SP363"/><h4 class="crsname">AC/SP 363. Poetry, Exile, and the U.S.A.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Two books of poetry, <span class="cite">Versos libres</span> and <span class="cite">Ismaelillo</span>, by Jos&#233; Mart&#237;, considered milestones in the foundation of the Hispanic <span class="cite">Modernismo</span>, were written by the Cuban poet in the United States in 1882. This could be a disturbing coincidence considering Mart&#237;'s <span class="cite">"americanismo"</span> and his sharp image of the United States as a historical symbol. This course explores the varied and problematic ways Spanish and Latin American poets living in the United States in the twentieth century created an image of the United States through poetry. The course focuses on works by the Spanish poets Juan Ram&#243;n Jim&#233;nez, Garc&#237;a Lorca, Luis Cernuda, Pedro Salinas, and Jorge Guill&#233;n, and Latin American poets Xavier Villaurrutia, Ernesto Cardenal, Enrique Lihn, and Heberto Padilla. Prerequisite(s): any 200-level literature course in Spanish. O. Torres Duque.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="390B"/><a name="AC/HI390B"/><h4 class="crsname">AC/HI 390B. History in the Public Sphere.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course combines a cultural history seminar with a community history practicum. On the one hand, students explore together the role of social memory and historical consciousness in American culture&#8212;the history of Americans' views on and use of their past. On the other hand, students' research and writing focuses on the history of Lewiston's mills and millworker families, as they work with a local museum to help create a traveling exhibit for the Lewiston-Auburn community. The goal is both to understand the importance of the past in community life and to contribute to our own community's historical consciousness. Prerequisite(s): History s40 or American Cultural Studies 220. Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every year. D. Scobey.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="ACS457"/><h4 class="crsname">ACS 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Under the supervision of a faculty advisor, all majors write an extended essay that utilizes the methods of at least two disciplines. Students register for American Cultural Studies 457 in the fall semester and for American Cultural Studies 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both American Cultural Studies 457 and 458.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457, 458"/><a name="ACS457, 458"/><h4 class="crsname">ACS 457, 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Under the supervision of a faculty advisor, all majors write an extended essay that utilizes the methods of at least two disciplines. Students register for American Cultural Studies 457 in the fall semester and for American Cultural Studies 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both American Cultural Studies 457 and 458.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="ACS458"/><h4 class="crsname">ACS 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Under the supervision of a faculty advisor, all majors write an extended essay that utilizes the methods of at least two disciplines. Students register for American Cultural Studies 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both American Cultural Studies 457 and 458.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s18"/><a name="INDSs18"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS s18. African American Culture through Sports.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Sports in African American life have served in a variety of ways to offer a means for social, economic, cultural, and even political advancement. This unit examines how sports have historically formed and contemporaneously shape the contours of African American culture. Particular attention is given to such questions as segregation, gender equity, cultural images, and their political effects for African American athletes and the black community. In addition to the required and recommended readings, lectures, and discussions, videos and films are central to the teaching and learning process. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and philosophy.  Not open to students who have received credit for Interdisciplinary Studies 215. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. J. McClendon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s22"/><a name="AC/HIs22"/><h4 class="crsname">AC/HI s22. Red Sox Nation.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This unit examines the place of major league baseball in American history  and contemporary culture, considering particularly the franchise and fan base known as Red Sox Nation, and the legendary rivalry between Boston and the New York Yankees. Students consider how race, class, ethnicity, and gender dynamics have determined the business and practice of the game, and how  baseball itself is a culturally defining event. They also examine how baseball rivalries have shaped and reflected regional cultures and identities. This interdisciplinary unit uses a variety of materials for its texts: historical studies, documentary and feature films, Web sites, and visits to baseball games and parks. Students are responsible not only for readings, viewings, and in-class discussion, but also for presentations and a short research paper. This unit has an additional fee. Enrollment limited to 20. Offered with varying frequency. M. Creighton.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="ACSs50"/><h4 class="crsname">ACS s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>

               