<div class="Course"><a name="101"/><a name="CHI101"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 101. Beginning Chinese I.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to spoken and written modern Chinese. Conversation and comprehension exercises in the classroom and laboratory provide practice in pronunciation and the use of basic patterns of speech.   Normally offered every year. S. Yang, Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="102"/><a name="CHI102"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 102. Beginning Chinese II.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A continuation of Chinese 101 with increasing emphasis on the recognition of Chinese characters. By the conclusion of this course, students know more than one quarter of the characters expected of an educated Chinese person. Classes, conducted increasingly in Chinese, stress sentence patterns that facilitate both speaking and reading. Prerequisite(s): Chinese 101. Normally offered every year. S. Yang, Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="201"/><a name="CHI201"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 201. Intermediate Chinese.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Designed to enable students to converse in everyday Chinese and to read simple texts in Chinese (both traditional and simplified characters). Classes conducted primarily in Chinese aim at further development of overall language proficiency. Prerequisite(s): Chinese 102.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. L. Miao.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="201-202"/><a name="CHI201-202"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 201-202. Intermediate Chinese.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Designed to enable students to converse in everyday Chinese and to read simple texts in Chinese (both traditional and simplified characters). Classes conducted primarily in Chinese aim at further development of overall language proficiency. Prerequisite(s): Chinese 102.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. L. Miao.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="202"/><a name="CHI202"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 202. Intermediate Chinese.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Designed to enable students to converse in everyday Chinese and to read simple texts in Chinese (both traditional and simplified characters). Classes conducted primarily in Chinese aim at further development of overall language proficiency. Prerequisite(s): Chinese 102  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. L. Miao.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="207"/><a name="CHI207"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 207. Traditional Chinese Literature in Translation.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An exploration of Chinese literature through reading and discussion of some of its masterworks of poetry, drama, fiction, and belles-lettres prose pieces from ancient times through the premodern era. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every year. S. Yang.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="209"/><a name="CHI209"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 209. Modern China through Film and Fiction.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores modern China through a number of short stories and feature films produced in the twentieth century, from Lu Hsun's fiction of the 1920s to recent films directed by such directors as Zhang Yimou and Ang Lee. The course focuses on ways of interpreting different cultural products of modern China, but students also gain a general knowledge of the history of modern Chinese fiction and film. All readings, lectures, and discussions are in English. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 35. Normally offered every year. S. Yang.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="211"/><a name="CHI211"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 211. Film and Chinese Modernity.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the role film has played in China's ongoing construction of modernity since the end of the nineteenth century. Discussion focuses not only on the social and historical context of Chinese films, but also on various kinds of cinematic languages through which Chinese filmmakers articulate their ideas, especially those involving debates concerning tradition, modernity, revolution, gender, sexuality, and national identity, as well as Chinese filmmakers' responses to constructions of the cultural "other" in Western films. Conducted in English. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="212"/><a name="INDS212"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 212. Writing/Righting Chinese Women.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is a survey of major writings by Chinese women, from Ban Zhao (40&#8211;120 <span class="smcaps">C.E.</span>), whose <span class="cite">nujie</span> is considered the early canon of female moral virtues, to the most recent novels by women writers who pride themselves in their audacity to write about their bodies. The course emphasizes ways women writers across time have countered various masculine constructions of silenced femininity and developed their own literary sensibility, especially in the context of China's modern development. Literary works explore topics that resonate with women's experience such as family, marriage, gender identity, sexuality, revolution, nation, and modernity. Conducted in English. Cross-listed in Asian studies, Chinese, and women and gender studies. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. H. Su.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="261"/><a name="CHI261"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 261. Self and Society in Chinese Culture: Classics and Folk Tales.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to Chinese culture and civilization through reading and discussion of a number of classical texts of Confucian, Taoist, and Buddhist thought, as well as traditional tales, popular stories, and legends in which these basic philosophies are reflected.  Readings and lectures are all in English.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every other year. S. Yang.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="301"/><a name="CHI301"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 301. Upper-Level Modern Chinese.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Designed for students who already have a strong background in spoken Chinese, the course gives an intensive review of the essentials of grammar and phonology, introduces a larger vocabulary and a variety of sentence patterns, improves conversational and auditory skills, and develops some proficiency in reading and writing. The course makes extensive use of short texts (both literary and nonfictional) and some films. Classes are conducted primarily in Chinese. Prerequisite(s): Chinese 202.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. L. Miao.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="301-302"/><a name="CHI301-302"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 301-302. Upper-Level Modern Chinese.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Designed for students who already have a strong background in spoken Chinese, the course gives an intensive review of the essentials of grammar and phonology, introduces a larger vocabulary and a variety of sentence patterns, improves conversational and auditory skills, and develops some proficiency in reading and writing. The course makes extensive use of short texts (both literary and nonfictional) and some films. Classes are conducted primarily in Chinese. Prerequisite(s): Chinese 202.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. L. Miao.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="302"/><a name="CHI302"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 302. Upper-Level Modern Chinese.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Designed for students who already have a strong background in spoken Chinese, the course gives an intensive review of the essentials of grammar and phonology, introduces a larger vocabulary and a variety of sentence patterns, improves conversational and auditory skills, and develops some proficiency in reading and writing. The course makes extensive use of short texts (both literary and nonfictional) and some films. Classes are conducted primarily in Chinese. Prerequisite(s): Chinese 202.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. L. Miao.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="CHI360"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365"/><a name="CHI365"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 365. Special Topics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Designed for the small seminar group of students who may have particular interests in areas of study that go beyond the regular course offerings. Periodic conferences and papers are required.   Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="401"/><a name="CHI401"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 401. Advanced Chinese I.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is designed to further enhance students' ability to understand and speak idiomatic Mandarin Chinese. Included are readings of modern and contemporary literary works, journalistic writings, and other nonliterary texts. Classical texts may also be studied upon students' request.  Prerequisite(s): Chinese 302. Recommended background: three years or more of Chinese. Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. S. Yang, Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="402"/><a name="CHI402"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 402. Advanced Chinese II.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A continuation of Chinese 401. Prerequisite(s): Chinese 302 or 401. Recommended background: three years of Chinese or more.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="415"/><a name="CHI415"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 415. Readings in Classical Chinese.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An intensive study of classical Chinese through reading selections of ancient literary, historical, and philosophical texts in the original, including excerpts from the <span class="em">Analects</span>, the <span class="em">Mencius, Laozi, Zhuangzi, Shiji,</span> Tang-Song prose, and poetry. Conducted in Chinese. Prerequisite(s): Chinese 302 or 401. Open to first-year students. Normally offered every other year. S. Yang.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="CHI457"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An extended research or translation project on a topic in Chinese literature, culture, or language utilizing some source materials in Chinese. Qualified students may choose to write the thesis in Chinese. Before registering for either 457 or 458, the student should consult with his or her advisor and submit a concise description and a tentative bibliography. Students register for 457 in the fall semester or for 458 in the winter semester unless the program gives approval for a two-semester project. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both Chinese 457 and 458. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457, 458"/><a name="CHI457, 458"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 457, 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An extended research or translation project on a topic in Chinese literature, culture, or language utilizing some source materials in Chinese. Qualified students may choose to write the thesis in Chinese. Before registering for either 457 or 458, the student should consult with his or her advisor and submit a concise description and a tentative bibliography. Students register for 457 in the fall semester or for 458 in the winter semester unless the program gives approval for a two-semester project. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both Chinese 457 and 458. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="CHI458"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An extended research or translation project on a topic in Chinese literature, culture, or language utilizing some source materials in Chinese. Qualified students may choose to write the thesis in Chinese. Before registering for either 457 or 458, the student should consult with his or her advisor and submit a concise description and a tentative bibliography. Students register for 457 in the fall semester or for 458 in the winter semester unless the program gives approval for a two-semester project. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both Chinese 457 and 458. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s30"/><a name="CHIs30"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI s30. Chinese Calligraphy and Etymology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of Chinese calligraphy through practice in the use of the brush-pen and through analysis of the aesthetics as well as the historical development of this graphic art. Calligraphy or brushwriting (<span class="em">shufa</span> in Chinese and <span class="em">shodo</span> in Japanese) is considered in East Asia as a spontaneous yet premeditated act of self-expression, which embraces philosophy, religion, culture, and an artistic tradition thousands of years old. Conducted in English.  Prerequisite(s): Chinese 101 or Japanese 101. Recommended background: some knowledge of Chinese characters or <span class="em">kanji</span>. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 20. Offered with varying frequency. S. Yang.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="CHIs50"/><h4 class="crsname">CHI s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="101"/><a name="JPN101"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 101. Beginning Japanese I.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to the basics of spoken and written Japanese as a foundation for advanced study and proficiency in the language. Fundamental patterns of grammar and syntax are introduced together with a practical, functional vocabulary. Mastery of the <span class="em">katakana</span> and <span class="em">hiragana</span> syllabaries, as well as approximately 140 written characters, introduce students to the beauty of written Japanese. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="101-102"/><a name="JPN101-102"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 101-102. Beginning Japanese I and II.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to the basics of spoken and written Japanese as a foundation for advanced study and proficiency in the language. Fundamental patterns of grammar and syntax are introduced together with a practical, functional vocabulary. Mastery of the <span class="em">katakana</span> and <span class="em">hiragana</span> syllabaries, as well as approximately 140 written characters, introduce students to the beauty of written Japanese. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="102"/><a name="JPN102"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 102. Beginning Japanese II.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Introduction to the basics of spoken and written Japanese as a foundation for advanced study and proficiency in the language. Fundamental patterns of grammar and syntax are introduced together with a practical, functional vocabulary. Mastery of the <span class="em">katakana</span> and <span class="em">hiragana</span> syllabaries, as well as approximately 140 written characters, introduce students to the beauty of written Japanese. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="125"/><a name="AS/JA125"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/JA 125. Japanese Literature and Society.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines major trends in Japanese literature and society from its beginnings to the present. Are there features of Japanese culture that continue unchanging through time? How have ideas of what is artistically valuable been linked with ideas of what is Japanese? How valid are the claims that Japanese culture is intimately involved with the appreciation of nature and the seasons? Students examine visual, literary, and historical texts, including classical narratives and painting scrolls of aristocratic culture, early modern plays and prints of samurai and geisha, and recent stories and films exploring questions of individual and national identity. All readings are in English.  Normally offered every year. S. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="130"/><a name="AS/JA130"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/JA 130. Japanese Film.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to Japanese cinema and criticism. They consider the aesthetic style and narrative themes of films from the silent era to the present day, focusing on directors such as Ozu Yasujiro, Kurosawa Akira, and Oshima Nagisa. They explore such questions as: Is there a distinctive Japanese film style? How do filmic qualities such as camera movement relate to story? How do films relate to their particular historical and cultural moment? In addition to viewing films, students read Japanese film history and criticism. No prior familiarity with Japan is required. Conducted in English. Normally offered every other year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="201"/><a name="JPN201"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 201. Intermediate Japanese I.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A continuation of Japanese 102, the course stresses the acquisition of new and more complex spoken patterns, vocabulary building, and increasing knowledge of cultural context through use of calligraphy, role play, video, and varied reading materials. One hundred fifty Chinese characters are introduced. A range of oral as well as written projects and exercises provide a realistic context for language use. Prerequisite(s): Japanese 102.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. K. Ofuji.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="201-202"/><a name="JPN201-202"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 201-202. Intermediate Japanese I and II.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A continuation of Japanese 102, the course stresses the acquisition of new and more complex spoken patterns, vocabulary building, and increasing knowledge of cultural context through use of calligraphy, role play, video, and varied reading materials. One hundred fifty Chinese characters are introduced. A range of oral as well as written projects and exercises provide a realistic context for language use. Prerequisite(s): Japanese 102.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. K. Ofuji.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="202"/><a name="JPN202"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 202. Intermediate Japanese II.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A continuation of Japanese 102, the course stresses the acquisition of new and more complex spoken patterns, vocabulary building, and increasing knowledge of cultural context through use of calligraphy, role play, video, and varied reading materials. One hundred fifty Chinese characters are introduced. A range of oral as well as written projects and exercises provide a realistic context for language use. Prerequisite(s): Japanese 102.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. K. Ofuji.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="210"/><a name="AS/JA210"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/JA 210. Heterogeneous Japan.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Scholars of Japan have long portrayed Japan as culturally homogenous. In recent years, however, people in and outside the academy have begun to challenge this assumption. In this course, students examine autobiography, fiction, and films that emphasize Japan's ethnic, regional, and socioeconomic diversity. Readings also may include historical and analytical essays and theoretical works on the relationship of modernity, national identity, and narrative. Conducted in English.  Not open to students who have received credit for Japanese 210 or Asian Studies 210. Open to first-year students. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="255"/><a name="JA/WS255"/><h4 class="crsname">JA/WS 255. Modern Japanese Women Writers.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In its beginnings, Japanese literature was considered a female art: the greatest writers of the classical period were women, while men at times assumed a female persona in order to write. How do Japanese women writers of the late twentieth and early twenty-first centuries portray the complexities of today's world? How do they negotiate the gendered institutions of the society in which they live? What values do they assign to being a woman, to being Japanese? What significance does the female canon hold for them as modern and postmodern writers? Students consider issues such as family, power, gender roles, selfhood, and the female body in reading a range of novels, short stories, and poems. Authors may include Enchi and Fumiko, Ohba Minako, Kurahashi Yumiko, Tsushima Yuko, Tawara Machi, Yamada Eimi, and Yoshimoto Banana. Readings and discussion are in English.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every other year. S. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="290"/><a name="ES/JA290"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/JA 290. Nature in East Asian Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">How have poets and other writers in Japan and China portrayed, valued, and responded to the myriad phenomena that Western tradition calls "nature"? What ideas have they used to construct the relationship between human beings and the environment? Do their views offer the modern world a possible antidote to its environmental ills? This course looks closely at several works from Japanese and Chinese traditions whose authors pay particular attention to the relationship between the self and the physical world the self observes. Specific writers may include Hitomaro, Saigy&#244;, Kamo no Chomei, Bash&#244;, Li Po, and Wang Wei. Conducted in English. Open to first-year students. Offered with varying frequency. S. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="301"/><a name="JPN301"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 301. Intermediate Japanese III.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course completes the introduction of essential Japanese syntactic forms and sentence patterns. Students continue development of oral skills and emphasis is placed on increased competence in the written language. Two hundred new characters are introduced. Prerequisite(s): Japanese 202. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="301-302"/><a name="JPN301-302"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 301-302. Intermediate Japanese III and IV.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course completes the introduction of essential Japanese syntactic forms and sentence patterns. Students continue development of oral skills and emphasis is placed on increased competence in the written language. Two hundred new characters are introduced. Prerequisite(s): Japanese 202. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="302"/><a name="JPN302"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 302. Intermediate Japanese IV.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course completes the introduction of essential Japanese syntactic forms and sentence patterns. Students continue development of oral skills and emphasis is placed on increased competence in the written language. Two hundred new characters are introduced. Prerequisite(s): Japanese 202. Normally offered every year. S. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="310"/><a name="JPN310"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 310. The Myth of the Samurai.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The samurai, the sword-wielding warrior with his strict <span class="em">bushido</span> code of  honor, is one of the most enduring images of Japan, both in the West and among the Japanese themselves. This course first acquaints  students with the decidedly less glamorous reality of the samurai. Students then explore the myths surrounding the warrior through medieval war tales, kabuki play scripts, and modern novels. Discussions focus on the shifting meanings invested in the image of the samurai by different writers and audiences over the centuries. Recommended background: one course in Japanese culture, history, or language. Conducted in English. Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every other year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="320"/><a name="ES/JA320"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/JA 320. Haiku and Nature in Japan.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The concise, seventeen-syllable verse form known today as haiku rose to prominence in the popular culture of seventeenth-century Japan. With its emphasis on the experience of the present moment and its use of clear natural imagery, haiku is seen by many as defining the way generations of Japanese have perceived and related to the natural world. This seminar examines the poetics of haiku and linked verse <span class="em">(renku)</span> and looks at the expression of their aesthetics in recent Japanese literature and culture from architecture to the novel to Zen. Prerequisite(s): at least one course in Japanese or one course in environmental studies. Conducted in English. Normally offered every other year. S. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="JPN360"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="401"/><a name="JPN401"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 401. Advanced Japanese I.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Through the discussion and study of contemporary literary texts and other journalistic modes, the course seeks to utilize, develop, and integrate skills acquired in the earlier stages of language learning. Particular emphasis is placed on reading and writing, and translation. Through class presentations and discussion students further develop oral skills and expand their understanding of Japanese culture. Prerequisite(s): Japanese 302.  Normally offered every year. K. Ofuji.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="402"/><a name="JPN402"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 402. Advanced Japanese II.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course covers materials in Japanese such as newspaper articles, other media material, and short stories. Through presentations and discussions students utilize, develop, and integrate spoken skills acquired in the earlier stages of language learning. Written skills are also emphasized; normally students complete a final research project on a topic of their choice. Students taking this course in conjunction with the thesis should also register for Japanese 458. Prerequisite(s): Japanese 401.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="JPN457"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An extended research or translation project on a topic in Japanese literature, culture, or language utilizing some source materials in Japanese. Qualified students may choose to write the thesis in Japanese. Before registering for either 457 or 458, the student should consult with his or her advisor and submit a concise description of the proposed project as well as a tentative bibliography. Students register for Japanese 457 in the fall semester or for Japanese 458 in the winter semester unless the program gives approval for a two-semester project. Majors writing an honors thesis register for Japanese 457 and 458. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457, 458"/><a name="JPN457, 458"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 457, 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An extended research or translation project on a topic in Japanese literature, culture, or language utilizing some source materials in Japanese. Qualified students may choose to write the thesis in Japanese. Before registering for either 457 or 458, the student should consult with his or her advisor and submit a concise description of the proposed project as well as a tentative bibliography. Students register for Japanese 457 in the fall semester or for Japanese 458 in the winter semester unless the program gives approval for a two-semester project. Majors writing an honors thesis register for Japanese 457 and 458. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="JPN458"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An extended research or translation project on a topic in Japanese literature, culture, or language utilizing some source materials in Japanese. Qualified students may choose to write the thesis in Japanese. Before registering for either 457 or 458, the student should consult with his or her advisor and submit a concise description of the proposed project as well as a tentative bibliography. Students register for Japanese 457 in the fall semester or for Japanese 458 in the winter semester unless the program gives approval for a two-semester project. Majors writing an honors thesis register for Japanese 457 and 458. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="JA/WSs21"/><h4 class="crsname">JA/WS s21. Geisha Fantasy: Representations of an Icon.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the stereotypes of the cultural category of geisha in film, literature, visual culture, and the performing arts. Students locate the discourse surrounding the geisha in both Japan and the United States, which leads to themes of "orientalism" (differentiating self and other in a way that hierarchizes the self), "self-orientalism," and <span class="em">nihonjinron</span> (doctrine of a Japanese essence). Students focus on historical contexts in which the category of geisha was formed and developed largely as a projection of male desire and male fantasy, and explore the homogenizing and dichotomizing of racial and sexual identities in the construction of the geisha. Conducted in English. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s25"/><a name="JPNs25"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN s25. Haiku Poetry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Matsuo Bash&#244; (1644&#8211;1694) is one of Japan's most celebrated poets. As a <span class="em">haikai</span> master he led group compositions in linked verse (<span class="em">renga</span>), in addition to writing the seventeen-syllable <span class="em">hokku</span> for which he is best known. His travel diaries represent a landmark in the history of Japanese literature. This unit explores the background and nature of the <span class="em">haikai</span> genre, with particular attention to Bash&#244;'s outstanding achievement. Students of Japanese language are encouraged to do some guided reading in the original. Recommended background: Japanese 240 and History 172. Conducted in English. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every other year. S. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s27"/><a name="JPNs27"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN s27. Hiroshima and Nagasaki.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The technologies of the industrial and postindustrial age have made possible a scale of destruction that seems impossible for human beings either to grasp or perhaps even to survive. Japan is the only nation to have experienced attack by atomic weapons. What is the role of art, literature, film, and journalism in expressing the "inexpressible" and possibly preventing its reoccurrence? This unit examines Japanese and Korean responses to the bombing of Hiroshima and Nagasaki. Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. S. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="JPNs50"/><h4 class="crsname">JPN s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="125"/><a name="AS/JA125"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/JA 125. Japanese Literature and Society.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines major trends in Japanese literature and society from its beginnings to the present. Are there features of Japanese culture that continue unchanging through time? How have ideas of what is artistically valuable been linked with ideas of what is Japanese? How valid are the claims that Japanese culture is intimately involved with the appreciation of nature and the seasons? Students examine visual, literary, and historical texts, including classical narratives and painting scrolls of aristocratic culture, early modern plays and prints of samurai and geisha, and recent stories and films exploring questions of individual and national identity. All readings are in English.  Normally offered every year. S. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="130"/><a name="AS/JA130"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/JA 130. Japanese Film.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to Japanese cinema and criticism. They consider the aesthetic style and narrative themes of films from the silent era to the present day, focusing on directors such as Ozu Yasujiro, Kurosawa Akira, and Oshima Nagisa. They explore such questions as: Is there a distinctive Japanese film style? How do filmic qualities such as camera movement relate to story? How do films relate to their particular historical and cultural moment? In addition to viewing films, students read Japanese film history and criticism. No prior familiarity with Japan is required. Conducted in English. Normally offered every other year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="208"/><a name="AS/RE208"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/RE 208. Religions in China.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the various religious traditions of China in their independence and interaction. The course focuses on the history, doctrines, and practices of Taoism, Confucianism, and various schools of Mahayana Buddhism. Readings include basic texts and secondary sources. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every other year. J. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="209"/><a name="AS/RE209"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/RE 209. Religions in Japan.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the various religious traditions of Japan in their independence and interaction. The course focuses on the doctrines and practices of Shinto, folk religion, and various schools of Buddhism. These are considered in the context of Japanese history and culture and set against their Korean and Chinese backgrounds. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every other year. J. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="210"/><a name="AS/JA210"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/JA 210. Heterogeneous Japan.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Scholars of Japan have long portrayed Japan as culturally homogenous. In recent years, however, people in and outside the academy have begun to challenge this assumption. In this course, students examine autobiography, fiction, and films that emphasize Japan's ethnic, regional, and socioeconomic diversity. Readings also may include historical and analytical essays and theoretical works on the relationship of modernity, national identity, and narrative. Conducted in English.  Not open to students who have received credit for Japanese 210 or Asian Studies 210. Open to first-year students. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="212"/><a name="INDS212"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 212. Writing/Righting Chinese Women.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is a survey of major writings by Chinese women, from Ban Zhao (40&#8211;120 <span class="smcaps">C.E.</span>), whose <span class="cite">nujie</span> is considered the early canon of female moral virtues, to the most recent novels by women writers who pride themselves in their audacity to write about their bodies. The course emphasizes ways women writers across time have countered various masculine constructions of silenced femininity and developed their own literary sensibility, especially in the context of China's modern development. Literary works explore topics that resonate with women's experience such as family, marriage, gender identity, sexuality, revolution, nation, and modernity. Conducted in English. Cross-listed in Asian studies, Chinese, and women and gender studies. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. H. Su.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="229"/><a name="AS/EC229"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/EC 229. Economics of Greater China.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Chinese are among the world's leading experimentalists in economics. The twentieth-century economic history of China, Taiwan, Hong Kong, and the overseas Chinese diaspora spans the entire gamut of economic regimes from virtually unrestricted competition to rigid state management. This course surveys economic development in Greater China with emphasis on understanding how institutions and institutional change affect economic and social development. Prerequisite(s): Economics 101 or 103.  Not open to students who have received credit for Economics 229. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 45. Offered with varying frequency. M. Maurer-Fazio.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="231"/><a name="AS/EC231"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/EC 231. The Economic Development of Japan.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course surveys the development of Japan's economy. A brief historical introduction focuses on the preconditions for economic modernization and the role of the government in Japan's late nineteenth- and early twentieth-century experience. The course then concentrates on an overview of Japan's post&#8211;World War II experience of recovery, explosive growth, slowdown, and attempted reform. Students consider whether the Japanese economy operates according to principles, objectives, and structures that are substantially different from those of the West. Japan's economic impact on other East Asian countries and relatedness with the world economy are also explored. Prerequisite(s): Economics 101 or 103. Not open to students who have received credit for Economics 231. Open to first-year students. Offered with varying frequency. M. Maurer-Fazio.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="234"/><a name="AV/AS234"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/AS 234. Chinese Visual Culture.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces Chinese visual cultures, from the Neolithic period to the present day, focusing on a period of particular cultural significance from the Han to Qing Dynasty. The course reveals interrelationships among Chinese art, literature, religious philosophy, and politics. Topics discussed include artists' places within specific social groups, theories of arts, questions of patronage, and the relation of traditional indigenous art forms to the evolving social and cultural orders from which they draw life. Principal objects include ritual objects, bronze vessels, ceramics, porcelain, lacquer ware, sculptures, rock-cut temples, gardens, painting, calligraphy, and wood-block prints. Recommended background: Asian Studies/Religion 208, Chinese 261, and History 171. Open to first-year students. Normally offered every other year. T. Nguyen.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="243"/><a name="AV/AS243"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/AS 243. Buddhist Visual Worlds.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course examines the history of Buddhist visual cultures. It provides a basic introduction to a broad spectrum of Buddhist art, beginning with the emergence of early Buddhist sculpture in India and ending with modern Buddhist visual works. It examines selected works of architecture, sculpture, and paintings in their religious, social, and cultural contexts. It also briefly surveys regional Buddhism and its arts. Normally offered every year. T. Nguyen.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="245"/><a name="AV/AS245"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/AS 245. Architectural Monuments of Southeast Asia.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the arts of Southeast Asia by focusing on significant monuments of the countries in the region. It examines the architecture, sculpture, and relief carvings on the ancient monuments and their relations to religious, cultural, political, and social contexts. Sites covered include Borobudur, Angkor, Pagan, Sukkhothai, and My-Son. Open to first-year students. Normally offered every other year. T. Nguyen.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="246"/><a name="AV/AS246"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/AS 246. Visual Narratives: Storytelling in East Asian Art.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the important artistic tradition of narrative painting in China and Japan. Through study of visually narrative presentations of religious, historical, and popular stories, the course explores different contexts in which the works&#8212;tomb, wall, and scroll paintings&#8212;were produced. The course introduces various modes of visual analysis and art historical contexts. Topics include narrative theory, text-image relationships, elite patronage, and gender representation. Recommended background: History 171, 172, and Japanese 240. Open to first-year students. Normally offered every other year. T. Nguyen.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="247"/><a name="AV/AS247"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/AS 247. The Art of Zen Buddhism.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The art of Zen (Chan) as the unique and unbounded expression of the liberated mind has attracted Westerners since the mid-twentieth century. But what is Zen, its art, and its culture? This course considers the historical development of Zen art and its use in several genres within monastic and lay settings. It also examines the underlying Buddhist concepts of Zen art. The course aims to help students understand the basic teachings of Zen and their expression in architecture, gardens, sculpture, painting, poetry, and calligraphy. Recommended background: Art and Visual Culture/Asian Studies 243, Asian Studies/Religion 208, 209, 250, or 309. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. T. Nguyen.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="249"/><a name="AS/RE249"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/RE 249. The Hindu Tradition.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An examination, through the use of primary and secondary texts, of the various traditions of Hinduism, with some consideration of their relation to Jainism and Indian Buddhism. Special attention is paid to the Vedas, Upanishads, and Bhagavad-Gita, as well as to the classical myths of Hinduism embodied in the Puranas, and to ritual and devotional practices. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every other year. J. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="250"/><a name="AS/RE250"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/RE 250. The Buddhist Tradition.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course focuses on the Buddha's life and teachings; on early Buddhism in India and the rise of various Buddhist schools of thought; on the development of Mahayana philosophies; on rituals, meditation, and other forms of expression in India and Southeast Asia.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every other year. J. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="251"/><a name="AS/RE251"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/RE 251. Religions of Tibet.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Tibetan religions are a complex mixture of Indian, Chinese, and indigenous elements. This course focuses on the history, doctrines, practices, literatures, major personalities, and communities of the different religious traditions that are expressions of this mixture, including the <span class="em">rNying ma</span>, <span class="em">bKa' brgyud</span>, <span class="em">Sa skya</span>, and <span class="em">dGe lugs</span> sects of Buddhism as well as the B&#246;n and "folk" traditions. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every other year. J. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="252"/><a name="AS/MU252"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/MU 252. Musics of Southeast Asia.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Designed for students interested in performing arts cultures based outside the West, this course introduces selected historical and contemporary musical traditions of mainland and island Southeast Asia. The integration of music, dance, theater, and ritual is a unifying theme of the course. Special attention is given to historical and contemporary gong-chime cultures of the region. Several practical sessions, in which students learn to play instruments of the Bates Javanese gamelan orchestra, enhance the grasp of formal principles common to a variety of Southeast Asian musics. The study of Southeast Asian arts contributes to students' understanding of the region. Prerequisite(s): Any course in music or Asian Studies. Open to first-year students. Offered with varying frequency. G. Fatone.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="260"/><a name="AS/PY260"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/PY 260. Cultural Psychology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course provides an introduction to the theoretical perspectives and research findings of cultural psychology, with an emphasis on comparisons between North American and East Asian cultural groups. Topics include defining culture as a topic of psychological inquiry; the methods of conducting cultural research; the debate between universality versus cultural specificity of psychological processes; acculturation and multiculturalism; and cultural influences on thought, feeling, motivation, personality, abnormality, and social behavior. Prerequisite(s): Psychology 101. Enrollment limited to 50. Normally offered every year. H. Boucher.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="308"/><a name="AS/RE308"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/RE 308. Buddhist Texts in Translation.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar involves the close reading and discussion of a number of texts representing a variety of Buddhist traditions. Emphasis is placed on several different genres including canonical sutras, commentarial exegeses, philosophical treatises, and popular legends. Prerequisite(s): Asian Studies/Religion 250,  Anthropology/Religion 263, or Art and Visual Culture/Asian Studies 243. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. J. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="309"/><a name="AS/RE309"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/RE 309. Buddhism in East Asia.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar focuses on the teachings, traditions, and contemplative practices of a number of East Asian schools of Buddhism, including the Tiantai (Tendai), Huayan (Kegon), Chan (Zen), Zhenyan (Shingon), and Pure Land traditions. Special consideration is given to the question of the continuities and discontinuities in the ways these schools became established in China, Korea, and Japan. Prerequisite(s): one of the following: Asian Studies/Religion 208, 209, or 250. Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every other year. J. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="ASIA360"/><h4 class="crsname">ASIA 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="380"/><a name="AV/AS380"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/AS 380. Stupas: Forms and Meanings.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Stupas are the most pervasive and symbolic form of Buddhist architecture in Asia. Buddhist stupas serve as the symbols of illumination, and repositories for the relics of revered persons. They also serve as universal symbols, embodiments of metaphysical principles and multivalent meanings. This seminar not only examines different architectural forms of stupas, but also studies religious concepts and symbolic meanings expressed in stupas in Buddhist Asia. Recommended background: one of the following: Anthropology 244, Art and Visual Culture/Asian Studies 243, Asian Studies/Religion 250, 251, 308, or 309. <span class="crsaddmod"> </span> Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. T. Nguyen.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="ASIA457"/><h4 class="crsname">ASIA 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students register for Asian Studies 457 in the fall semester and for Asian Studies 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both Asian Studies 457 and 458. Prerequisite(s): one course of appropriate preparatory work to be determined in consultation with the advisor.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457, 458"/><a name="ASIA457, 458"/><h4 class="crsname">ASIA 457, 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students register for Asian Studies 457 in the fall semester and for Asian Studies 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both Asian Studies 457 and 458. Prerequisite(s): one course of appropriate preparatory work to be determined in consultation with the advisor.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="ASIA458"/><h4 class="crsname">ASIA 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students register for Asian Studies 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both Asian Studies 457 and 458. Prerequisite(s): one course of appropriate preparatory work to be determined in consultation with the advisor.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="ASIAs21"/><h4 class="crsname">ASIA s21. Traditional Chinese Color Ink Painting.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of traditional Chinese color ink painting through practice in the use of the brush-pen on rice paper. Students explore the aesthetics as well as brush techniques and brushwork styles of this unique form of art. Techniques include <span class="em">gongbi</span> (meticulous brushwork on details) and <span class="em">xieyi</span> (an impressionistic way of evoking subtle moods) renditions of plant and animal images such as grapes, lotus flowers, chrysanthemums, roses, peonies, plum blossoms, chickens, butterflies, shrimp, and goldfish. There is a studio fee of $150. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 20. Offered with varying frequency. M. Maurer-Fazio.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s22"/><a name="ASIAs22"/><h4 class="crsname">ASIA s22. Indian Lyrical Traditions.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Much of premodern literature from India consists of poignant, sensual love poetry, full of pining heroines whose bodies are "scalded by moonlight" or enamored male heroes whose feet are "pricked by thorns." This unit introduces students to translated poetry from several classical and medieval Indian traditions and languages (Sanskrit, Prakrit, Brajhbhasha, Urdu, Bengali, Tamil), accompanied by interpretive orientations and related material from visual arts, music, and dance. Students engage with the traditions creatively by composing their own poems&#8212;in English&#8212;according to various conventions. At the end of the term, the class presents a public reading of selected student works. Not open to students who have received credit for First-Year Seminar 321. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. S. Sengupta.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s25"/><a name="AS/HIs25"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/HI s25. Americans in Japan.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The unit considers Americans who visited Japan since the first contact between the two nations in 1853. Focusing on the period before World War II, students examine the motivations and goals of these sojourners, and what they accomplished in their travels. Enrollment limited to 16. (East Asian.) Normally offered every year. A. Hirai.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s28"/><a name="AS/PTs28"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/PT s28. Sufi Saints and Muslim Missionaries.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This unit offers an introduction to the study of Islam in South Asia, focusing on Chishti Sufi saints, their shrines, and the work of the Tablighi Jama'at, a distantly related movement devoted to the cause of religious revival and reform (<span class="em">tajdid</span>) around the world. During four weeks in India, students attend lectures by faculty at local universities and travel to mosques, shrines, and other sites of religious and historical significance in Delhi, Rajasthan, and Uttar Pradesh. A tolerance for very high temperatures is essential. Recommended background: previous course work concerning Islam and/or non-Western countries. Enrollment limited to 12. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. M. Nelson.<br/></span></div>
