<div class="Course"><a name="102"/><a name="BIO102"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 102. Sensory Biology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the biology of sensation in humans and other organisms. It focuses on the chemical (taste, smell) and mechanical (touch, hearing) senses, and includes other topics such as electroreception in fish, magnetoreception in migrating animals, and vision in vertebrates and invertebrates. Laboratory exercises examine our own senses (why, for example, do peppers seem hotter to some humans than others?), as well as those of other organisms, such as aversive behaviors to chemical or tactile stimuli in invertebrates, and reaction to touch in carnivorous plants. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 103 or s27. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> N. Kleckner.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C036">Color: Sight and Perception (C036)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C005">Sound (C005)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="103"/><a name="BIO103"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 103. Sensory Biology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This laboratory course examines the biology of sensation in humans and other organisms. It focuses on the chemical (taste, smell) and mechanical (touch, hearing) senses, and includes other topics such as electroreception in fish, magnetoreception in migrating animals, and vision in vertebrates and invertebrates. Laboratory exercises examine our own senses (why, for example, do peppers seem hotter to some humans than others?), as well as those of other organisms, such as aversive behaviors to chemical or tactile stimuli in invertebrates, and reaction to touch in carnivorous plants. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 102 or s27. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> N. Kleckner.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C036">Color: Sight and Perception (C036)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C005">Sound (C005)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="104"/><a name="BIO104"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 104. Forensic Science/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Forensic science encompasses many scientific disciplines from cell and molecular biology to geology, anatomy, and physics. Using knowledge acquired through lectures, readings, and discussions, students perform many field and laboratory techniques used by crime-scene analysts. Critical thinking and analytical skills are used to analyze mock crime scenes. Students produce written analyses of their work, and present their findings and conclusions to their peers and others in various formats. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO s21. Enrollment limited to 10.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> L. Abrahamsen.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="108"/><a name="BIO108"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 108. Cancer.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this course, students examine the biological basis of cancer, including the role of oncogenes and tumor suppressors in regulating how the cell divides, how environmental agents and viruses can induce DNA mutations leading to cancerous growth, and the genetic basis of certain predispositions of inherited cancers. Students also examine how cancer treatments (radiation, chemotherapy drugs) work to kill cancerous cells. Finally, they explore emerging technologies that are developing new targeted cancer therapies, based on understanding the basic biological processes of cell division and blood vessel growth. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> S. Richards.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="112"/><a name="BI/GE112"/><h4 class="crsname">BI/GE 112. Oceanography/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An integrated, interdisciplinary overview of the chemistry, physics, geology, and biology of the world's oceans. Topics include chemical and physical properties of sea water, ocean circulation, evolution of ocean basins, coastal geomorphology, the distribution and abundance of organisms in the major marine communities, the status of the world's most important fisheries, and the role of the ocean in the global carbon cycle. The course may include weekend field trips. Not open to students who have received credit for BI/GE 113. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> W. Ambrose.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="113"/><a name="BI/GE113"/><h4 class="crsname">BI/GE 113. Marine Science.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An integrated, interdisciplinary overview of the chemistry, physics, geology, and biology of the world's oceans. Topics include chemical and physical properties of sea water, ocean circulation, evolution of the ocean basins, coastal geomorphology, the distribution and abundance of organisms in the major marine communities, the status of the world's major fisheries, and the role of the ocean in the global carbon cycle. Lectures are supplemented by demonstrations and occasional laboratory exercises, though the course does not fulfill the General Education laboratory requirement.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Not open to students who have received credit for BI/GE 112. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> W. Ambrose.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="114"/><a name="BIO114"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 114. Extreme Physiology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Physiology, the study of how organisms function, has benefited tremendously from studies of amazing animals doing amazing things. How do bar-headed geese fly over the top of Mount Everest when humans struggle to reach the summit? How do fish withstand body temperatures below the freezing point of water? This course explores how animals work under extreme environmental conditions and what this reveals about human physiology in health and disease. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> R. Bavis.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="117"/><a name="BIO117"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 117. Plants and Human Affairs.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A survey of economically and historically important plants, with emphasis on aspects of agronomy, forestry, plant biochemistry, and ethnobotany. Plant products studied include perfumes, spices, medicinals, fermentation products, oils, rubber, textiles, wood, sugar, cereals, and legumes. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 124 or s20. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> L. Johnson.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C059">Colonialism (C059)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="118"/><a name="BIO118"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 118. Insects and Human Health/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Insects&#8212;numerous, ubiquitous, diverse, and uniquely equipped&#8212;play significant roles in human and ecosystem health, and have influenced human history and culture in ways both obvious and obscure. This course introduces insect biology and diversity, and explores insects' influence on human affairs with a particular emphasis on health. Topics include insect function, evolution, and interspecific relationships; insects' roles in human disease, health, and policy; and human endeavors to flourish in coexistence with beneficial and harmful insects. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO s22. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> S. Kinsman.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="119"/><a name="BIO119"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 119. Human Reproduction: Biology and Evolution.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Reproduction is among the most basic and fascinating of human biological functions. This course explores the physiological mechanisms that underlie this process. Topics include sexual differentiation, testicular and ovarian function, pregnancy, fetal development, childbirth, lactation, contraception, and infertility. Why is giving birth so difficult for humans?  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Not open to students who have received credit for AN/BI 119. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> One-time offering. D. Kimmel.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="122"/><a name="BI/CH122"/><h4 class="crsname">BI/CH 122. Structure and Function of DNA, RNA, and Proteins.</h4><span class="CourseDesc"> How does a virus or a bacterial cell develop drug resistance? How does a colony of fruit flies adapt to living in a new environment? Changes in the sequences and/or shapes of DNA, RNA, and proteins can alter their physical and chemical properties, influencing the survival of an organism in an environment. This course introduces the physical and chemical properties of these important molecules and their roles in the Central Dogma of molecular biology. Examples of molecular evolution and adaptation in a variety of biological systems are studied. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> P. Schlax.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C003">Chemistry (C003)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="122"/><a name="BIO122"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 122. Biology, Poetry, and Inheritance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course integrates science and the humanities by presenting topics in biology through the imagined life stories of two individuals with inherited differences. Students work in teams as physicians, scientists, parents, and poets to understand broadly the causes, consequences, and value of these differences. Topics include cells, energy, entropy and emergence; molecular storage, information, and transmission; human reproduction; race and gender; and inheritance and genetics. Students' final projects may take the form of seminar, poetry, dance, or drama. This approach to scientific questions is informed by classical and modern biology and by language and its structure, rhythm, rhyme and reason; surprise in discovery; and mystery and beauty.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2014.</span> Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> One-time offering. D. Kimmel.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="124"/><a name="BIO124"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 124. Plants and Human Affairs/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A survey of economically and historically important plants, with emphasis on aspects of agronomy, forestry, plant biochemistry, and ethnobotany. Plant products studied include perfumes, spices, medicinals, fermentation products, oils, rubber, textiles, wood, sugar, cereals, and legumes. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 117 or s20. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> R. Thomas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C059">Colonialism (C059)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="127"/><a name="BIO127"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 127. Emerging and Reemerging Infections across the Globe.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Emerging infections are those that are newly described, appear in different geographic regions, or move into new host populations. Reemerging infections are those that were controlled in the past but are again of concern. In this course students examine the biology of bacteria, viruses, fungi, and other organisms that cause these infections as well as the mechanisms by which they produce disease. Consideration is given to transmission patterns, treatments, and prevention. Topics may include infections of global concern such as malaria, tapeworms, dengue fever, HIV-AIDS, polio and other childhood diseases, cholera, and tuberculosis. Not open to students who have received credit for FYS 236 or 262. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> K. Palin.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="158"/><a name="BIO158"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 158. Evolutionary Biology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Evolution is the great unifying theory in biology. It is the context into which all other biological subjects fit. The course examines various aspects of evolution, including the origin of life, the major events in the evolution of life on Earth, the processes that result in evolutionary change, the nature of the fossil record, the history of evolutionary theories, and creationist objections to these theories. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> R. Barry.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="190"/><a name="BIO190"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 190. Organismal Biology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to the biology of plants and animals with an emphasis on the evolution of structure, function, and diversity within these groups. The inquiry-based, collaborative laboratory studies introduce students to fundamental principles of form and function in the organismal world, the quantitative analysis of data, scientific writing, and utilizing the primary literature. This course is intended to serve as the entry point for all life science majors including biology, biological chemistry, neuroscience, and environmental studies (science concentration). Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 101. Enrollment limited to 70.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=NRSC">Neuroscience</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="211"/><a name="BIO211"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 211. Marine Invertebrates/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A survey of the varieties, morphology, development, evolution, and behavior of invertebrates with an emphasis on marine animals. Laboratory work includes the study, through dissection and experiment, of representative organisms. The course includes field trips to local marine habitats. Prerequisite(s): BIO 190. Enrollment limited to 14 per section.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> W. Ambrose.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="221"/><a name="BIO221"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 221. Plant and Fungal Diversity/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A survey of fungi, plant-like protists and monerans, algae, bryophytes, ferns and fern allies, gymnosperms, and angiosperms. Lecture, laboratory, and field studies emphasize diversity in morphology, physiology, evolution, ecology, and human uses. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level biology course. Open to first-year students.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> R. Thomas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="242"/><a name="BIO242"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 242. Cellular and Molecular Biology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A view of life at the cellular and molecular levels. Topics include cellular energetics, membrane phenomena, genetics, and molecular biology. Laboratory studies include enzymology, bacterial transformation, the light reactions of photosynthesis, Mendelian genetics, bioinformatics and DNA analysis using gel electrophoresis and polymerase chain reaction. Quantitative analysis of data and peer-reviewed scientific writing are emphasized.  This course is required for the biology, biological chemistry, and neuroscience majors. Prerequisite(s): BIO 190 and CHEM 108A or CH/ES 108B. Enrollment limited to 60.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span>  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=NRSC">Neuroscience</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="244"/><a name="BIO244"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 244. Biostatistics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A course in the use of both descriptive and inferential statistics in the biological sciences, including such topics as types of data, population structure, probability distributions, common types of statistical inference (t-, F-, and chi-square tests), correlation and regression, analysis of variance, and an introduction to nonparametric statistics.  Prerequisite(s): BIO 190. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 50.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every year. R. Barry.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="252"/><a name="BI/ES252"/><h4 class="crsname">BI/ES 252. Urban Ecology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">More than half of humanity now lives in cities. This course examines the urban environment as a coupled social-ecological system at multiple scales, from individual street trees and community gardens to global biotic homogenization. Topics may include the city as a physical environment for organisms, patterns of urban biodiversity, ecological processes in cities, how cities do (and do not) provide essential ecosystem services to their residents, and applications of ecological science to urban planning and design. Lab activities may combine geospatial and observational approaches, and may include a full-day weekend field trip. Recommended background: BIO 270. 
Prerequisite(s): BIO 190.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter semester 2014.</span> Enrollment limited to 18.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> One-time offering. L. Johnson.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="255A"/><a name="BI/MA255A"/><h4 class="crsname">BI/MA 255A. Mathematical Models in Biology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Mathematical models are increasingly important throughout the life sciences. This course provides an introduction to deterministic and statistical models in biology. Examples are chosen from a variety of biological and medical fields such as ecology, molecular evolution, and infectious disease. Computers are used extensively for modeling and for analyzing data. Prerequisite(s): MATH 105. Not open to students who have received credit for BI/MA 155. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C062">Why Academics Matter (C062)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="260"/><a name="BIO260"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 260. Environmental Toxicology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Environmental toxicology is the study of the impacts of pollutants upon organisms and the structure and function of ecological systems. It draws from a variety of disciplines, including ecology, chemistry, organismal and developmental biology, genetics, epidemiology, and mathematics. This course provides an overview of the field by discussing toxicant introduction, movement, distribution, and fate in the environment; toxicant sites and mechanisms of action in organisms and ecosystems; and toxicant impact upon organisms and ecosystems. Basics of toxicity testing design and analysis are an important part of the laboratory. Prerequisite(s): BIO 190 and CHEM 108A or CH/ES 108B; or ENVR 203. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 24.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> R. Sommer.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C062">Why Academics Matter (C062)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="265"/><a name="BIO265"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 265. Invasive Plant Ecology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Species transported and established beyond their original range may become invasive, changing the distribution and  abundance of local species, and altering the composition, structure, and dynamics of local communities. This course uses knowledge of the ecology of plants&#8212;including individual adaptations and abilities; population dynamics; community patterns and dynamics; life history and reproduction; and interactions with mutualists, competitors, and herbivores&#8212;to recognize and evaluate the patterns and causes of invasive plant species' effects on communities and ecosystems. Discussions of research literature emphasize the mechanisms of effects; field laboratories emphasize identification, assessment in common and rare local community types, and management planning. Some Saturday field trip laboratories are required. Prerequisite(s): BIO 190, 221, or 270. Enrollment limited to 12.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> S. Kinsman.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="268"/><a name="BIO268"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 268. Entomology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of insects, the largest group of animals. Lectures and laboratories emphasize insect morphology and physiology, evolution and classification as well as behavior, ecology, and experimental research. Selected topics may include flight, development and hormones, variations in life cycles and reproductive modes, courtship and parental care, and evolution of mutualisms, defense, and social behavior. Certain laboratories are scheduled as weekend afternoon field trips. In addition, one overnight museum field trip may be scheduled. Prerequisite(s): BIO 190, 114, or 118. Enrollment limited to 14 per section.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> S. Kinsman.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270"/><a name="BIO270"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 270. Ecology and Evolution/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to ecological and evolutionary patterns, principles, and processes. Topics include life history and adaptation, speciation, mechanisms of evolution, population dynamics and interactions, community structure, and ecosystem processes. Laboratories include experimental investigations of several levels of biological organization using cooperative lab groups. Prerequisite(s): BIO 190.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span>  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="308"/><a name="BI/NS308"/><h4 class="crsname">BI/NS 308. Neurobiology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course is an introduction to the molecular and cellular principles of neurobiology and the organization of neurons into networks. Also included are the topics of developmental and synaptic plasticity, and the role invertebrate systems have played in our understanding of these processes. Laboratories include electrical recordings from nerve cells, computer simulation and modeling, and the use of molecular techniques in neurobiology. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 12 per laboratory section.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every year. N. Kleckner.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="311"/><a name="BIO311"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 311. Comparative Anatomy of the Chordates/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to the comparative anatomy of the vertebrates and their kin, with laboratory study of both sharks and mammals. Prerequisite(s): BIO 190. Enrollment limited to 18.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> R. Barry.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="313"/><a name="BIO313"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 313. Marine Ecology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An examination of the complex ecological interactions that structure marine systems. Habitats studied include intertidal, estuary, coral reef, deep sea, salt marsh, and pelagic. Laboratories include work in local marine communities and require occasional weekend trips. Prerequisite(s): BIO 270. Enrollment limited to 12 per laboratory section.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> W. Ambrose.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="314"/><a name="BIO314"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 314. Virology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A lecture and seminar examination of the molecular biology of viruses, including viroids and bacteriophages. Topics include viral infection and replication cycles, morphology, oncogenesis, and virus-host interactions. Viruses of epidemiologic and biotechnologic importance are emphasized. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> L. Abrahamsen.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="315"/><a name="BIO315"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 315. Bacteriology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A survey of the structure and physiology of bacteria, emphasizing adaptations of these organisms to specific environmental niches. Particular attention is given to organisms of medical, ecological, or industrial interest. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 25.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every year. L. Abrahamsen.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="320"/><a name="BIO320"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 320. Pharmacology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Pharmacology is the study of the actions and effects of drugs within a living organism, whether they are illegal, legal, prescription, or over-the-counter. This course places an emphasis on treatment of illness and disease in mammals and presents mechanisms of action, and therapeutic uses and toxicities of important drugs, including medications that affect the peripheral nervous system, cardiovascular system, gastrointestinal tract, endocrine system, reproductive system, and agents used to treat cancer. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Recommended background: BIO 337 and CHEM 218.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> R. Sommer.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=NRSC">Neuroscience</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="321"/><a name="BIO321"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 321. Cellular Biochemistry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the biochemical mechanisms of cellular functions with the goal of extending student knowledge about the structure, synthesis, and metabolism of biological macromolecules and contextualizing the regulation of these molecules in healthy and diseased cells and tissues. The course does not satisfy a requirement for the biological chemistry major.  Not open to students who have received credit for CHEM 321 or 322.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course begining Winter 2014.</span>  <span class="gened">[S]</span> N. Kleckner, S. Richards.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="323"/><a name="BIO323"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 323. Forest Ecology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Study of terrestrial plants' population dynamics, community patterns, and adaptations to physical and biological environments, with an emphasis on northern New England. Topics may include alpine and subalpine vegetation of Mount Washington, rare coastal communities, adaptations to selected wetland conditions, plant-animal interactions, reproduction and demography, forest disturbance dynamics, and plant community patterns. Field trip learning is essential; some Saturday field trips are required. Prerequisite(s): BIO 270. Enrollment limited to 12.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> S. Kinsman.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="326"/><a name="BIO326"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 326. Plant Ecology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This introductory course explores historical and contemporary issues of harvesting and raising aquatic and marine fish and invertebrates. An examination of key commercially important species and methods sets the stage for exploring the biology behind the issue: How can humans meet the challenge of supplying food to a growing human population, with shrinking fish populations in a changing global environment? Examples from fisheries and aquaculture research illustrate topical issues through lectures, field trips, and laboratory experiences. Several all-day field trips are scheduled. Prerequisite(s): Biology 270. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 323. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> One-time offering. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="328"/><a name="BIO328"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 328. Developmental Biology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Developmental biology is a dynamic field that addresses questions related to how organisms come into being and grow. This course introduces students to developmental biology with a particular emphasis on the molecular basis for developmental events. The course focuses on the mechanisms involved in making cells that are different from one another (cell differentiation) and the associated mechanisms by which patterns are created (morphogenesis). In the lab, students explore the phenomenon of development in several of the most prominently utilized model organisms. The lab culminates in an independent project. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 20.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> Normally offered every year. L. Williams.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="330"/><a name="BIO330"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 330. Advanced Genetics/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A lecture and laboratory exploration of the principles of inheritance. Topics include viral, bacterial, and human genetics, population genetics, the genetics of model organisms, and genomics. Readings include primary literature. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Not open to students who have received credit for BI/ES 330. Enrollment limited to 16.  <span class="gened">[L]</span> D. Dearborn.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=NRSC">Neuroscience</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="331"/><a name="BIO331"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 331. Molecular Biology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A laboratory and lecture introduction to the molecular biology of genes and chromosomes. The course emphasizes current research about gene structure and function, experimental techniques, and eukaryotic genetics. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> Normally offered every year. L. Williams.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=NRSC">Neuroscience</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="333"/><a name="BI/ES333"/><h4 class="crsname">BI/ES 333. The Genetics of Conservation Biology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Conserving biodiversity is important at multiple scales, including genetic variation within species. Does a species have enough variation to evolve in a changing world? Are individuals differentially adapted to local environmental variation? In a captive population of a rare animal, which individuals should be bred to minimize the erosion of genetic variation? Lectures and labs cover the fundamentals of classical, molecular, and population genetics, applying them to current issues in biological conservation. Prerequisites: Biology 242 or Biology 270. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 330. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> D. Dearborn.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="337"/><a name="BIO337"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 337. Animal Physiology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The major physiological processes of animals, including digestion, circulation, respiration, excretion, locomotion, and both neural and hormonal regulation. Examples are drawn from several species and include a consideration of the cellular basis of organ-system function.  Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 12 per laboratory section.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every year. R. Bavis.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=NRSC">Neuroscience</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="338"/><a name="BIO338"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 338. Drug Actions on the Nervous System.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on the biochemistry and physiology of neural tissues. An emphasis is placed on neurotransmitter systems, and on drugs thought to act on these systems. The relationships between the actions of drugs at molecular, cellular, and behavioral levels are also discussed. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Recommended background: NS/PY 200, 363, or BI/NS 308.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> N. Kleckner.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=NRSC">Neuroscience</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="340"/><a name="BIO340"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 340. Introduction to Epidemiology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Epidemiology is the study of the distribution and determinants of disease, injuries, and health within populations. This course examines the frequencies and types of illnesses and injuries within various groups and the multiple factors that influence their distribution. Students consider infectious, chronic, emerging, and reemerging diseases of historical and current importance. Models and preventions are discussed. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242 or 270. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> K. Palin.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C059">Colonialism (C059)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C062">Why Academics Matter (C062)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="342"/><a name="BIO342"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 342. Ecological and Evolutionary Physiology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the interaction between the environment and physiological phenotypes in animals while emphasizing the role of evolutionary processes in shaping physiological variation. Topics may include the evolution of endothermy, adaptation to extreme environments (e.g., high altitudes, deserts), and controversial concepts such as symmorphosis. Readings from the primary scientific literature highlight diverse methodological approaches used to understand the evolution of physiological traits, such as comparative and phylogenetic analysis, selection experiments, genetic and phenotypic manipulation, and quantitative genetics. Prerequisite(s): BIO 270.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> R. Bavis.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="350"/><a name="BIO350"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 350. Immunology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course comprises a comprehensive survey of the immune system:  those physiological processes responsible for distinguishing self from non-self, preventing debilitating infection, and clearing tumors.  After building a thorough understanding of the function of the innate and adaptive immune systems in health, students will explore the contribution of immune dysfunction to important diseases such as allergy, autoimmunity, AIDS, and cancer.  Medical approaches to immune modulation such as vaccination, anti-inflammatory therapeutics, and hematopoietic stem cell transplantation will also be discussed.  Evaluation will be based on class participation, group presentations, and take home exams in essay format.  Prerequisite(s): BIO 242.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2014.</span> Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 351. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="351"/><a name="BIO351"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 351. Immunology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The immune system is studied as an example of the body's chemical communication networks and as one mechanism for memory. Topics include production of an immune response, immune surveillance in the maintenance of health, the effects of psychological and environmental factors on the immune system and on health, and the effects of immune dysfunctions (autoimmune diseases and immune deficiencies including AIDS). The course emphasizes the human immune system but briefly covers comparative immunology. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=NRSC">Neuroscience</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="355"/><a name="BIO355"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 355. Advanced Topics in Evolution.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course offers an advanced exploration of how evolution works. The first portion of the course is devoted to an overview of the major topics in evolution, ranging from micro-scale processes, such as mutation, to macro-scale processes, such as mass extinction events. The second portion of the course delves deeply into a small number of topics which vary from year to year but may include, for example, host-parasite arms races, sexual selection, and the evolution of aging. Prerequisite(s): BIO 270. Enrollment limited to 15. D. Dearborn.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="BIO360"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365"/><a name="BIO365"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 365. Special Topics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Offered at irregular intervals by a faculty member in an area of contemporary interest. <br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365F"/><a name="BIO365F"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 365F. Topics in Cell Biology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course considers current topics in cell biology by examining how our knowledge has progressed from a hypothesis to current work. For example, the fluid mosaic model of membranes was hypothesized several decades ago. Students examine the progress of our knowledge, culminating with our current understanding of the importance of lipid rafts for cell signaling. Other topics may include nuclear transport regulation; the cytoskeleton, signaling, and motion; the multiple roles of GTP binding proteins; structure, function and X-ray crystallography; and visualizing cell components. The seminar features reading of the primary literature and student-designed projects and presentations. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> N. Kleckner.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="380"/><a name="BIO380"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 380. Plant Physiology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of organismal and cellular functions important in the life of green plants. Topics include mineral nutrition, water relations, metabolism, and regulatory processes. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 20.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> R. Thomas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="BIO457"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Permission of the department and the thesis advisor are required. Students register for BIO 457 in the fall semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both BIO 457 and 458. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="BIO458"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Permission of the department and the thesis advisor are required. Students register for BIO 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both BIO 457 and 458. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="460"/><a name="BIO460"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 460. Junior Seminar.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Reading original biological literature is an essential skill for biology majors. Focusing on the topics addressed by invited speakers for the semester's biology seminar program, students review articles, write analyses, and contribute oral presentations in a small group format. Students attend afternoon and/or evening seminars and discuss the content, context, and presentation of original investigations. Prerequisite(s): BIO 190, 242, and 270. One of these courses may be taken concurrently, only by permission of the instructor. Enrollment limited to 20.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="471"/><a name="BIO471"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 471. Seminar and Research in Experimental Botany/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Laboratory, field, or library study of a current research topic in experimental botany. A topic is selected with reference to the research interests of the instructor. Enrollment limited to 6. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> R. Thomas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="472"/><a name="BIO472"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 472. Seminar and Research in Physiology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Laboratory or library study of a current research topic in animal physiology. A topic is selected with reference to the research interests of the instructor.  Recommended background: BIO 337. Enrollment limited to 6. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span>  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> R. Bavis.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="473"/><a name="BIO473"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 473. Seminar and Research in Cell Biology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Laboratory and library study of a current research topic in the experimental study of biology at the cellular level. A topic is selected with reference to the research interests of the instructor.  Recommended background: BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 6. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="474"/><a name="BIO474"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 474. Seminar and Research in Marine Ecology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Laboratory, field, and library study of advanced topics in marine ecology. Topics are selected in relation to research interests of the instructor and students.  Prerequisite(s): BIO 244 and 270. Recommended background: BIO 211. Enrollment limited to 6. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span>  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> W. Ambrose.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="475"/><a name="BIO475"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 475. Seminar and Research in Environmental Toxicology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Laboratory and library study of a current research topic in environmental toxicology. Topics are selected in relation to research interests of the instructor and students. Recommended background: BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 6. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> R. Sommer.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="477"/><a name="BIO477"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 477. Seminar and Research in Microbiology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Laboratory and library study of a current research topic in microbiology or immunology. Topics are selected with reference to the research interests of the instructor and students. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 6. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span>  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="478"/><a name="BIO478"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 478. Seminar and Research in Molecular Genetics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Laboratory and library study of a current research topic in molecular biology and genetics. Topics are selected with reference to the research interests of the instructor. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 6. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> S. Richards.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="479"/><a name="BIO479"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO 479. Seminar and Research: Biology in the Community/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Field and library study of biological research topics with applications in the broader community. Topics are selected with reference to the research and community interests of the instructor. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 6.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span>  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> K. Palin.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s15"/><a name="INDSs15"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS s15. Health, Culture, and Community.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines dimensions of health through classroom and community-based experiences, with a special emphasis on current public health issues. The course covers the history and organization of public health; methods associated with health-related research; disparities in health, including those related to race, class, and gender; public policy and health; population-based approaches to public health; and cultural constructions of health and illness. The course is designed to be integrative: expertise from different disciplines is used to address current challenges in public health. Cross-listed in anthropology, biology, and psychology.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. (Diversity.) K. Low.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="BIOs21"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s21. Forensic Science/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Forensics is the utilization and application of scientific information to criminal and civil law. The field of forensics utilizes a number of scientific disciplines including cell biology, molecular biology, genetics, entomology, chemistry, physics, anatomy, biochemistry, geology, and botany. Through lectures, readings, field trips, and discussions, students acquire the knowledge necessary to perform many field and laboratory techniques used by crime-scene analysts. Students then use critical thinking and analytical skills to process mock crime scenes, perform the appropriate laboratory tests, and present their findings and conclusions to their peers. Can they solve the case? Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 104. Enrollment limited to 20.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> S. Richards.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s23"/><a name="BIOs23"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s23. Understanding Cancer/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">As a cause of mortality in the Western world, cancer is second only to cardiovascular disease. What causes cancer? How is cancer diagnosed and classified? How do flaws in fundamental biological processes drive cancerous growth? What are current therapeutic options and potential new treatments in the fight against cancer? These questions are explored in the classroom and the laboratory. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 108. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> S. Richards.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s25"/><a name="BIOs25"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s25. Microbes and Everyday Life/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Microorganisms, most so small that we cannot see them without microscopes, run the world in which we live. They recycle elements and nutrients, play a role in wastewater treatment, cause disease and keep us healthy, produce some of our food and many of our pharmaceutical products, and much more. Through readings, discussions, field trips, and laboratory investigations, students explore the remarkable diversity in habitats and metabolic activities exhibited by the microbial world we encounter every day. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 315. Enrollment limited to 20.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> K. Palin.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s27"/><a name="BIOs27"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s27. Sensory Biology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the biology of sensation in humans and other organisms. It focuses on the chemical (taste, smell) and mechanical (touch, hearing) senses, and includes other topics such as human vision and bat and dolphin biosonar. Laboratory exercises examine our own senses (why, for example, do peppers seem hotter to some humans than others?), as well as those of other organisms, such as aversive behaviors to chemical or tactile stimuli in invertebrates, and electroreception in fish. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 102 or 103. Enrollment limited to 20.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> N. Kleckner.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C005">Sound (C005)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s28"/><a name="BIOs28"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s28. Emerging and Reemerging Infections.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Emerging and reemerging infections have the potential to impact all populations, human and nonhuman, in all regions of the world. How are these infections defined and described? What types of organisms cause them? What mechanisms are involved? How do such infections spread within and between populations? How are they controlled? On the global scale, can emerging and reemerging infections be eliminated? These questions and related topics are explored through readings, discussions, and computer simulations. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 127. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> K. Palin.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s29"/><a name="BIOs29"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s29. Nature Photography.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of photographic techniques used by biologists in the field and laboratory, with emphasis on close-up photography of plants and animals. Additional areas covered include landscape and aerial photography, photomicrography, and preparation of photographs for lectures or publication. Required: access to a 35mm or digital single-lens reflex camera. Recommended background: one course in biology at the 100 level. There is a materials fee of $60.00 per student. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. R. Thomas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s31"/><a name="BIOs31"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s31. Avian Biology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Birds are among the most conspicuous animals in the environment, occupying terrestrial and aquatic niches from the tropics to the poles. This course examines the origin and diversification of birds and explores avian morphology, physiology, and behavior in an ecological and evolutionary context. Topics include flight, communication, feeding, migration, and reproduction. The course includes a laboratory and requires several extended field trips. Prerequisite(s): BIO 270. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 335. Enrollment limited to 12. D. Dearborn.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s33"/><a name="BIOs33"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s33. Phenotypic Plasticity/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The ability of organisms to express different morphological, physiological, and behavioral traits in different environments has emerged as a key principle in modern biology. This course explores the proximate physiological basis of this phenotypic plasticity. Other topics include the genetic basis and evolution of phenotypic plasticity, as well as the roles of plasticity in health and disease. Examples are drawn from both animal and plant studies. The course is organized around discussion of the primary scientific literature and research projects selected with reference to research interests of the instructor. Prerequisite(s): BIO 190. Recommended background: BIO 270. Enrollment limited to 8. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> R. Bavis.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s34"/><a name="BIOs34"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s34. Electron Microscopy/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to the principles of electron optics with emphasis on biological applications. Topics covered in classroom and laboratory activities and on field trips include use of the scanning electron microscope, use of associated X-ray dispersive and cytochemical techniques, preparation of specimens for scanning and transmission electron microscopy, and interpretation of data. Special interest topics are chosen by students for independent research projects. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 341. Enrollment limited to 8.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> R. Thomas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s35"/><a name="BIOs35"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s35. Experimental Toxicogenomics/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students learn principles and techniques of toxicology, genomics, and developmental biology. Drawing on primary literature, students form hypotheses about organ systems and genes that are likely targets of developmental arsenic exposure. They test their hypotheses using a zebrafish model system. Laboratory techniques that monitor normal zebrafish development and assess gene expression are integral to the laboratory research component of the course. Students live and work for two weeks at the Mount Desert Island Biological Laboratory. Prerequisite(s): any 100-level biology or chemistry course. Enrollment limited to 16.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> R. Sommer.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s36"/><a name="BIOs36"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s36. Mammalogy/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students study the structure, taxonomy, behavior, ecology, evolution, and public health significance of mammals, and history of the science of mammalogy. Laboratory and field exercises emphasize anatomy, identification, capture techniques, habitat analysis, home-range estimation, and habitat characterization. Several day-long and overnight field trips are planned. Prerequisite(s): BIO 190. Recommended background: BIO 244. Enrollment limited to 18.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> R. Barry.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s37"/><a name="BIOs37"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s37. The North Woods.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An investigation of the patterns and history of New England's forests and associated plant communities, with an emphasis on field study and research. Students review the influences of geological patterns, climate, unusual soil and water conditions, natural disturbances, invasive plants and insects, and human activities on community type, occurrence, and history. Central to the course are visits to a variety of field sites, where students learn to describe the structure, composition, and history of several communities. Primary literature is emphasized. Prerequisite(s): BIO 270 or ENVR 310.  <span class="crsaddmod">Course reinstated beginning Short Term 2014.</span> Enrollment limited to 8.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> L. Johnson.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s39"/><a name="BIOs39"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s39. Community-Based Research in Biology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this course students investigate topics with biological significance within the local community. Using the scientific method and the principles of community-based research, students participate as a group in collaborative research with a community partner to address a topic of biological interest and concern. The topic of study is selected relative to the interests of the instructor and the community partner. Research areas may include, but are not limited to, environmental microbiology, toxicology, public health, medicine, and science education. This course requires extensive work in the local community. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 8.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> K. Palin.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s40"/><a name="BIOs40"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s40. Experimental Developmental and Molecular Biology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this hands-on, laboratory-based course, students learn and practice the scientific method. Living and working at the Mount Desert Island Biological Laboratory, known for its educational and research programs focusing on non-mammalian systems, students work with the important vertebrate model system, zebrafish, and utilize cutting-edge molecular and microscopy techniques to address questions related to protein pathways involved in the developmental process. Independent projects and oral presentations are a central requirement of the course. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 12.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> L. Williams.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s44"/><a name="BIOs44"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s44. Experimental Neuro/Physiology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of contemporary research techniques in the fields of neurobiology, physiology, and pharmacology. Topics may include the pharmacology of recombinant neurotransmitter receptors or the physiology and pharmacology of invertebrate neurons. This course requires extensive laboratory work in independent projects. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242. Enrollment limited to 12. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> N. Kleckner.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=BIOC">Biological Chemistry</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=NRSC">Neuroscience</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="BIOs50"/><h4 class="crsname">BIO s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>

               