<div class="Course"><a name="100"/><a name="CM/HI100"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/HI 100. Introduction to the Ancient World.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces the Greco-Roman world, and serves as a useful basis for 200- and 300-level courses in classical civilization. Within a general chronological framework students consider the ancient world under a series of headings: religion, philosophy, art, education, literature, social life, politics, and law. The survey begins with Bronze Age Crete and Mycenae and ends with the first century <span class="smcaps">B.C.E.</span>, as Rome makes its presence felt in the Mediterranean and moves toward empire. Enrollment limited to 60. (European.) (Premodern.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> D. O'Higgins.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="102"/><a name="CM/HI102"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/HI 102. Medieval Europe.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Far from being an "enormous hiccup" in human progress, the medieval centuries (circa 350&#8211;1350) marked the full emergence of Islamic, Byzantine, and West European civilizations. These powerful medieval cultures shape our present. The central theme of this introductory survey course is the genesis and development of a distinct Western European medieval civilization including its social, economic, political, and cultural aspects. Important topics include the devolution of the Roman Empire; the Christianization of the West; the origins of the Byzantine world; the rise of Islam; and the history of medieval women. Enrollment limited to 48. (European.) (Premodern.) Normally offered every year. M. Jones.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C034">French and Francophone Studies (C034)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="106"/><a name="CM/HI106"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/HI 106. Greek Civilization.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course considers 1) the archaic civilization of Homer, a poet celebrating the heroes of an aristocratic and personal world; 2) the classical civilization of Aeschylus, Sophocles, Aristophanes, and Phidias, the dramatists and sculptor of a democratic and political Athens; 3) the synthesis of Plato, celebrating the hero Socrates and attempting to preserve and promote aristocratic values in a political world. (European.) (Premodern.) Normally offered every year. J. Cole.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="108"/><a name="CM/HI108"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/HI 108. Roman Civilization: The Republic.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this course students explore the civilization and history of ancient Rome from the foundation of the  Republic around 510 <span class="smcaps">B.C.E.</span> until its collapse in civil war and its transformation into a monarchy under Julius Caesar and his nephew, Octavian. Each week the class convenes for lectures devoted to the political, social, and cultural history of the Republic. In addition, students meet once a week to discuss in detail primary sources for the period. Not open to students who have received credit for Classical and Medieval Studies/History 107. Enrollment limited to 60. (European.) (Premodern.) M. Imber.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="109"/><a name="CM/HI109"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/HI 109. Roman Civilization: The Empire.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this course students examine the civilization and history of ancient Rome from the Principate, the monarchy established by Octavian in 27 <span class="smcaps">B.C.E.</span>, until the end of Justinian's dynasty at the beginning of the seventh century of the Common Era. Each week the class convenes for lectures devoted to the political, social, and cultural history of the Empire. In addition, students meet once a week to discuss in detail primary sources for the period. Recommended background: Classical and Medieval Studies/History 107. Enrollment limited to 60. (European.) (Premodern.) M. Imber.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="111"/><a name="CM/EN111"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN 111. <span class="em">The Lord of the Rings</span> in Context.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines J. R. R. Tolkien's <span class="cite">Lord of the Rings</span> trilogy in a variety of contexts, including its sources, inspirations, uses, and audiences. Particular attention is paid to Tolkien's creative process and academic background, along with a focus on how Tolkien's books and Peter Jackson's films reinforce each other as modern cultural phenomena. Enrollment limited to 50. S. Federico.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121D"/><a name="CM/EN121D"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN 121D. Arthurian Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The story of King Arthur of Britain and his Knights of the Round Table is one of Western civilization's most enduring legends. This course explores those elements of the Arthur story that make it so universally compelling in addition to the ways in which its details have been adapted according to the needs and desires of its changing audience. Topics considered include feudal loyalty and kinship, women and marriage, monsters and magic, the culture of violence and warfare, and the stylistic and narrative features of the legendary mode. Students consider modern versions of the story by Marion Zimmer Bradley and T. H. White, Victorian versions by Tennyson and Beardsley, and, in modern English translations, French, English, and Latin versions made popular in the twelfth through fifteenth centuries. Not open to students who have received credit for Classical and Medieval Studies/English 121C. Not open to students who have received credit for CM/EN 121C. Enrollment limited to 25. S. Federico.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121F"/><a name="CM/EN121F"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN 121F. Tolkien's Middle Ages.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An examination of Tolkien's medieval influences through a study of Anglo-Saxon, Old Norse, and Middle English philology and literature, with particular attention to those texts taught and edited by Tolkien and to <span class="cite">The Lord of the Rings</span> as a form of mythology. 
 Enrollment limited to 25. S. Federico.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121N"/><a name="CM/EN121N"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN 121N. Victorian Medievalisms.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Tracing the stirrings of Victorian medievalism from the landscapes of Arthurian romance to the Gothic revival in literature, architecture, and art, this course examines how nineteenth-century visions of the past intersect with issues of gender, class, nationalism, industrialization, and faith. Special attention is given to the relationship between nostalgia, medievalism, and "the ache of modernism" in Thomas Hardy's late novels&#8212;in particular, how these impulses impact the traditional Victorian novel's project of social realism; the critical, rational vision it espouses; and its inevitable extinction as a culturally dominant form. Additional authors may include Tennyson, Browning, Arnold, Ruskin, Rossetti, Eliot, and Wilde. Enrollment limited to 25. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="130"/><a name="INDS130"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 130. Food in Ancient Greece and Rome.</h4><span class="CourseDesc"> Participants in this course study food in ancient Greece and Rome: the history of the food supply for agrarian and urban populations; malnutrition, its probable impact on ancient economies, and its uneven impact on populations; famine; the symbolism of the heroic banquet&#8212;a division of the sacrificial animal among ranked members of society, and between men and gods; cuisine and delicacies of the rich; forbidden food; the respective roles of men and women in food production, and their unequal access to food supply; dietary transgression; and sacred food. Cross-listed in classical and medieval studies, history, and women and gender studies. Not open to students who have received credit for Classical and Medieval Studies s28. Enrollment limited to 60. (European.) (Premodern.) D. O'Higgins.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C083">Material Culture (C083)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="160"/><a name="CM/RH160"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/RH 160. Classical Rhetoric.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Romans ran the ancient world by the sword, but also by the word. This course explores how they did the latter. Readings include classical works about rhetoric, examples of classical oratory and the variety of exercises by which the practice of rhetoric was taught. Writing assignments include analyses of speeches by classical orators, as well as a range of ancient rhetorical exercises such as fables, speeches of praise and invective, persuasive speeches to historical figures, and mock courtroom speeches. The course concludes with an examination of the Gettysburg Address and consideration of its debt to classical rhetorical theory. All readings are in English. Enrollment limited to 60. M. Imber.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C085">Language and Literacy (C085)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="200"/><a name="CMS200"/><h4 class="crsname">CMS 200. Ancient Comedy and Satire.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students read (in translation) the comic poets and satirists of Greece and Rome and investigate the nature and social context of ancient humor, satire, and invective. Authors include Homer, Hesiod, Archilochus, Semonides, Aristophanes, Menander, Terence, Horace, Seneca, and Petronius. Recommended background: Classical and Medieval Studies 100. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 60.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> D. O'Higgins.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C067">The Translated World (C067)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="202"/><a name="CMS202"/><h4 class="crsname">CMS 202. Greek Tragedy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to fifth-century Athenian tragedies in English translation. The plays form the primary focus of the course, but there are many related topics of discussion: the origin of tragedy and its religious significance, its political context and content, tragedy's audience and affective power, tragedy's self-conscious relationship with epic and lyric. Students also read and discuss a representative selection of modern criticism on Greek tragedy. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 60.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> H. Walker.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C067">The Translated World (C067)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="203"/><a name="CM/HI203"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/HI 203. Great Wars of Greek Antiquity.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Much of the perennial appeal of the history of the Persian Wars and the Peloponnesian War lies in storied confrontations of East and West, empire and freedom, rise and fall, folly and intelligence, war and peace, victory and defeat. More of the interest for the reflective student lies in the critical use of the classical sources, especially Herodotus and Thucydides, and in the necessary qualification of those too-simple polarities, East/West, empire/freedom, rise/fall, folly/intelligence, war/peace, victory/defeat, and, of course, good/bad.  Enrollment limited to 40. (European.) (Premodern.) J. R. Cole.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="204"/><a name="CM/WS204"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/WS 204. Gender and the Body in Ancient Greece.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">How did people in ancient Greece think about the categories of male and female? How did these categories intersect with others, such as social status, age, and ethnicity? This course considers issues of gender in archaic and classical Greece and looks at how Greek men and women thought about the body, sexuality, and "transgressive" behavior and individuals. Students analyze literary texts (in translation) as well as medical, religious, and legal evidence&#8212;inscriptional and textual&#8212;and modern scholarship. Not open to students who have received credit for Classical and Medieval Studies 201. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 35.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> D. O'Higgins.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="205"/><a name="CMS205"/><h4 class="crsname">CMS 205. Two Thousand Years of Classical Myth.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Using Ovid's <span class="cite">Metamorphoses</span> as a foundation, this course traces (in English) some of the many versions of Greco-Roman myths through medieval, Renaissance, and modern times, in Europe and the Americas, primarily in literary reworkings, but including some examples from art and music as well. Reading portions of Ovid in the original language is encouraged for students with one or more years of Latin. Not open to students who have received credit for Classical and Medieval Studies s18. Enrollment limited to 30. T. Hayward.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C067">The Translated World (C067)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="206"/><a name="CM/EN206"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN 206. Chaucer.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Reading and interpretation of <span class="em">The Canterbury Tales,</span> the greatest work of the fourteenth-century Middle-English poet. All works are read in Middle English.  Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Not open to students who have received credit for English 206. Enrollment limited to 25. (Pre-1800.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Normally offered every year. S. Federico.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="207"/><a name="CM/HI207"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/HI 207. The Roman World and Roman Britain.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Roman Empire is famous for its decline and fall. Stretching from the Euphrates to the Atlantic, however, this remarkable multiethnic empire persisted for 500 years. Its story is a fascinating example of what Theodore Mommsen tagged the moral problem of "the struggle of necessity and liberty." This course is a study of the unifying and fragmenting forces at work on the social, economic, and political structures of the Roman imperial world. Key themes include the western provinces and Roman Britain, the effects of Romanization on conquered peoples, and the rise of Christianity. The survey begins with the reign of Augustus and concludes with the barbarian invasions of the fifth century.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. (European.) (Premodern.) M. Jones.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C059">Colonialism (C059)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="208"/><a name="INDS208"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 208. Introduction to Medieval Archeology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Middle Ages were a time of major cultural changes that laid the groundwork for Northwest Europe's emergence as a global center of political and economic power in subsequent centuries. However, many aspects of life in the period from 1000 to 1500 <span class="smcaps">C.E.</span> were unrecorded in contemporary documents and art, and archeology has become an important tool for recovering that information. This course introduces the interdisciplinary methods and the findings of archeological studies of topics including medieval urban and rural lifeways, health, commerce, religion, social hierarchy, warfare, and the effects of global climate change. Cross-listed in anthropology, classical and medieval studies, environmental studies, and history. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. (Premodern.) Offered with varying frequency. G. Bigelow.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C025">Archeology and Material Culture (C025)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="209"/><a name="CM/HI209"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/HI 209. Vikings.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Vikings were the most feared and perhaps misunderstood people of their day. Savage raiders branded as the Antichrist by their Christian victims, the Vikings were also the most successful traders and explorers of the early Middle Ages. The Viking Age lasted for three centuries (800&#8211;1100 <span class="smcaps">C.E.</span>), and the Vikings' world stretched from Russia to North America. Study of the myth and reality of Viking culture involves materials drawn from history, archeology, mythology, and literature. Prerequisite(s): History 102. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. (European.) (Premodern.) M. Jones.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="218"/><a name="CM/RE218"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/RE 218. Greek and Roman Myths.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Did the Greeks and Romans believe their myths about winged horses, goddesses, and golden apples? How are myths related to the religious, political, and social world of Greece and Rome? This course examines Greek and Roman myths from a variety of theoretical perspectives in order to understand their meaning in the ancient world and their enduring influence in Western literature and art.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 60. L. Maurizio.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C067">The Translated World (C067)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="232"/><a name="AV/CM232"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/CM 232. Pyramid and Ziggurat.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A survey of the art and architecture of the ancient worlds of Egypt and the Near East, with attention given to topics including women in ancient Egypt, the Kingdom of Kush, and current developments in archeology. Not open to students who have received credit for Art and Visual Culture/Classical and Medieval Studies s23. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 50. R. Corrie.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="236"/><a name="CM/RE236"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/RE 236. Introduction to the New Testament.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Readings in the New Testament and related Greek and early Christian literature. Studies of the gospels include investigation into the nature of the early Jesus movement and Jesus' place in the Judaism of his day, the interpretation of Jesus' teaching in the context of Roman-occupied Palestine, and the growth of the Jesus tradition in the early Church. Topics such as the diversity of ideas about salvation, influence of Greco-Roman religious thought, the place of women in the early Church, the break between Christianity and Judaism, and the formation of the early Church in its first century are covered in the study of the New Testament epistles (emphasis on the apostle Paul's epistles) and the book of Revelation. Not open to students who have received credit for Religious Studies 236. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. C. Baker.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="238"/><a name="CM/RE238"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/RE 238. Inventing Judaism in Antiquity.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The millennium between 500 <span class="smcaps">B.C.E.</span> and 500 <span class="smcaps">C.E.</span> saw the gradual invention of a culture that has come to be known as Judaism. This course introduces the significant historical events and texts that were part of this cultural process, as well as the daily practices, institutions, ideologies, and movements associated with it.  The approach is both historical and thematic with close reading of archeological and written sources including texts from the Dead Sea Scrolls, New Testament (substantially authored by Jews), later Hebrew Bible and Apocrypha, Philo, Josephus, and the early rabbinic corpus.  Topics include biblical interpretation; creation, adaptation, and transmission of traditions; identity and self-definition; accommodation and resistance; sectarianism and the invention of Jewish and Christian orthodoxies; theories about messiahs, afterlife, and a world-to-come. Not open to students who have received credit for Religious Studies 238. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. C. Baker.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="240"/><a name="CM/RE240"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/RE 240. History of Christianity I: Conflict, Self-Definition, and Dominance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is a study of the convictions, controversies, and conflicts by which an egalitarian Jewish revitalization movement in Palestine became a worldwide religion. Students follow Christianity's development from martyrdom and persecution to a state-sponsored religion of the Roman Empire, from internal heresy and schism to the "One Great Holy and Apostolic Catholic Church." Special attention is given to regional diversity and the changing place of women in the church. Not open to students who have received credit for Religious Studies 241. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. C. Baker.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="241"/><a name="AV/CM241"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/CM 241. The Art of Islam.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Art of the Islamic world from its roots in the ancient Near East to the flowering of Safavid Persia and Mughal India in the sixteenth, seventeenth, and eighteenth centuries. Developments are traced through architecture, painting, ceramics, textiles, and metalwork. Consideration is given to the continuity of the Near Eastern artistic tradition and Islamic art in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 50.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> R. Corrie.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="251"/><a name="AV/CM251"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/CM 251. The Age of the Cathedrals.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An investigation of medieval architecture from the Early Christian era to the end of the Gothic period in Europe, including Russia and the Byzantine East. Emphasis is placed on the development of Christian architecture and the emergence of the Gothic cathedral in the context of European political and social history before 1500. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 49.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> R. Corrie.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="252"/><a name="AV/CM252"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/CM 252. Art of the Middle Ages.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In Europe from the Early Christian era to the end of the Gothic age, from 300 to 1450 <span class="smcaps">C.E.</span>, precious objects, manuscripts, wall paintings, and stained glass were produced in great quantities. The course traces the development of these and other media, including tapestry and sculpture. The roles of liturgy, theology, and technological and social changes are stressed. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 50.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> R. Corrie.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C083">Material Culture (C083)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="253"/><a name="CM/HI253"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/HI 253. Introduction to Roman Law.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to the Roman legal system, as a process, a source of substantive law, and the origin of a particular kind of reasoning in the West. The course concentrates on a specific area of Roman law: either delict (akin to torts in the American legal system), family law, or criminal law. Teaching is mainly by the case law method used in law schools. Students spend a third of their time preparing for and participating in a mock trial that concludes the course. Recommended background: Classical and Medieval Studies 108 or 109. Enrollment limited to 40. (Premodern.) Offered with varying frequency. M. Imber.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C013">Law and Society (C013)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="265"/><a name="AV/CM265"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/CM 265. Florence to Bruges: The Early Renaissance in Europe.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course investigates the art and architecture of Northern and Southern Europe between 1250 and 1450. Students analyze the impact of theology, liturgy, social change, urbanism, gender, and social class on visual culture. Artists considered include Cimabue, Duccio, Giotto, Fra Angelico, Donatello, Brunelleschi, Jan van Eyck, and Rogier van der Weyden. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> R. Corrie.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C035">Renaissance: Arts and Letters (C035)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="268"/><a name="CM/RE268"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/RE 268. Religion and Politics in Three Medieval Traditions.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course compares three conceptions of the relationship between religion and politics in three medieval traditions &#8212;Judaism, Christianity, and Islam&#8212;through a careful examination of representatives from each: Rabbi Moshe ben Maimon /Maimonides, Thomas Aquinas, and Ibn Rushd/Averro&#235;s. Drawing on recent work in the field of comparative religious ethics, this course utilizes tools and techniques from comparative study of religion to illuminate the intersection or religion and politics in its varied complexity. Enrollment limited to 40. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="271"/><a name="CM/PL271"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/PL 271. Ancient Greek Philosophy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the basic philosophical ideas underlying Western thought as these are expressed in the writings of the Pre-Socratics, Socrates, Plato and Aristotle. Greek thought is discussed in its historical and social context, with indications of how important Greek ideas were developed in later centuries. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Not open to students who have received credit for Philosophy 271. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="CMS360"/><h4 class="crsname">CMS 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="376"/><a name="AV/CM376"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/CM 376. Seminar in Medieval and Renaissance Art.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar examines the visual culture of Europe and the Mediterranean basin in the Middle Ages and the Renaissance. In different years the seminar focuses on specific subjects, which may include manuscript illumination, regional architecture, Crusader art, and medieval urbanism. <br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C083">Material Culture (C083)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="376C"/><a name="AV/CM376C"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/CM 376C. Siena: Art and Social Memory.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">At the height of its power Siena, Italy, bankrolled much of Europe and from 1250 to 1450 produced images that influenced painting from England to the Islamic world. Studying the work of Sienese artists including Duccio, Simone Martini, and the Lorenzetti, this course investigates the ties between visual culture (including sculpture and architecture) and politics, economics, religion, urban structure, and social identity. Recommended background: at least one 200-level course in the history of art and visual culture or the equivalent, or a course in medieval or Renaissance history. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> R. Corrie.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C035">Renaissance: Arts and Letters (C035)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="376D"/><a name="AV/CM376D"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/CM 376D. Crusader Art and Architecture.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar investigates the visual and material culture of the Crusader states found between 1099 and 1500 from Jerusalem to Syria, Constantinople, Greece, and the islands of the Aegean. Focusing on manuscript and icon painting, sculpture, and church and military architecture of the Frankish states, it also addresses the related production of Armenian Cilicia, the Byzantine Empire, Cyprus, Greece, the Balkan kingdoms, Europe, and the Islamic Near East and North Africa, concluding with a consideration of the nineteenth- and twentieth-century fascination with the Crusades and the recent flowering of scholarship on Crusader art. Recommended background: at least one 200-level course in the history of art and visual culture or in a related field such as history or religious studies. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> R. Corrie.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="390D"/><a name="CM/HI390D"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/HI 390D. Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Edward Gibbon's classic <span class="cite">Decline and Fall</span> is the most famous work of history written in English. This course uses it as an introduction to the problem of the collapse of complex, premodern societies and specifically the end of the Roman West. Changing historical explanations for the fall of Rome are a microcosm of Western historiography. Students also explore basic questions on the nature of history and historians. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (European.) (Premodern.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> M. Jones.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="390I"/><a name="CM/HI390I"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/HI 390I. Anglo-Saxon England.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar concentrates on Dark Age Britain (circa 400&#8211;800 <span class="smcaps">C.E.</span>). This period is a mystery wrapped in an enigma. Ignorance and obscurity offer one advantage to students: the sources are so few that they may be explored in a single semester. The course is designed to present typical kinds of early medieval evidence (saints' lives, chronicles, annals, charters, poetry, genealogy, archeology), introduce students to their potentials and difficulties, and then set a series of problems that requires application of these materials to gain an answer. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (European.) (Premodern.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> M. Jones.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="390J"/><a name="CM/HI390J"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/HI 390J. Law and Society in Ancient Rome.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This research seminar introduces students to the range of academic skills necessary to conduct research and write scholarly papers on topics in ancient Roman law. In addition to considering the actual substance and procedures of Roman law, students explore different methodologies that consider Roman law and the relationship of Roman law to the historical and social contexts in which Roman law evolved. Prerequisite(s): Classical and Medieval Studies/History 100, 102, 108, or 109. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> M. Imber.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C013">Law and Society (C013)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="390R"/><a name="CM/HI390R"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/HI 390R. The Catilinarian Crisis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar explores the causes of the Catilinarian crisis in the year 63 <span class="smcaps">B.C.E.</span>, and the consequences of Catiline for the Roman Republic. Students read and analyze the primary sources for the political career of Rome's great failed rebel, study the complex context of Roman politics during the thirty years between Sulla's and Caesar's successful dictatorships, and the careers and ambitions of Rome's prominent political and military leaders (Pompey, Crassus, Caesar, and Cicero), all of whom played critical roles in the Catilinarian crisis. Finally, students study and critique the often contradictory scholarly assessments of the Catilinarian crisis. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level course in classical and medieval studies or history, and one 200-level course in classical and medieval studies or history. Enrollment limited to 25. (European.) (Premodern.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> M. Imber.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395E"/><a name="CM/EN395E"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN 395E. Medieval Romance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Romance was the most popular literary genre of the later Middle Ages. Originating in France in the twelfth century, this highly adaptable form quickly became an international phenomenon, with numerous examples found across Europe and the British Isles. Many romances tell tales of amorous exploits, exotic travels, and quests for knowledge; the celebration of chivalric ideals is a central theme. But many of these tales seem to question and sometimes undermine the very ideals they otherwise espouse: courtly love mingles with sexual adventurism, for instance, and loyalty to one's lord often results in alienation or death. Students read a selection of romances from France and Britain (all texts are in modern English translation or manageable Middle English) with an eye toward how they variously articulate and deconstruct the notion of chivalry. Prerequisite(s): one English course. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Pre-1800.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> S. Federico.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395H"/><a name="CM/EN395H"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN 395H. Medieval Chivalry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the many vocabularies of chivalry that arose during the Western High Middle Ages (1100-1500), a period of profound cultural change. In response to shifts in marriage and property customs, the papal schism, the Black Death, social rebellions, and civil wars, texts produced in the age of chivalry feature pointed representations of aristocrats and peasants, courtly ladies and prostitutes, crusaders and heathens, not to mention tournaments, treason, weaponry, and outlawry. These timely and sensitive topics appear in such varied genres as romances, court poetry, courtesy literature, letters, legal documents, city charters, and conduct books. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Pre-1800.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Offered with varying frequency. S. Federico.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395R"/><a name="CM/EN395R"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN 395R. Gender Issues in Medieval Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The most popular forms of literature in the Middle Ages, including chivalric epic, courtly romance, hagiography, and fabliaux, work from specific assumptions regarding normative gender roles. The qualities of a perfect knight, for example, include certain types of gendered behavior, including casual promiscuity with women and an appetite for violence with men. This course examines literary representations of medieval gender roles in relation both to their origins (often in Church teachings) and their manifestations in the social world. Students read a number of late medieval poems, prose treatises, and excerpts from legal and theological documents. Readings are in (manageable) Middle English or in Modern English translation. Prerequisite(s): one English course. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Pre-1800.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> S. Federico.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="CMS457"/><h4 class="crsname">CMS 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Required of all majors. The research and writing of an extended essay in classical and medieval studies, following the established practices of the field, under the guidance of a supervisor in the classical and medieval studies program. Students register for Classical and Medieval Studies 457 in the fall semester and for Classical and Medieval Studies 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both Classical and Medieval Studies 457 and 458.   <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457, 458"/><a name="CMS457, 458"/><h4 class="crsname">CMS 457, 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Required of all majors. The research and writing of an extended essay in classical and medieval studies, following the established practices of the field, under the guidance of a supervisor in the classical and medieval studies program. Students register for Classical and Medieval Studies 457 in the fall semester and for Classical and Medieval Studies 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both Classical and Medieval Studies 457 and 458.   <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="CMS458"/><h4 class="crsname">CMS 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Required of all majors. The research and writing of an extended essay in classical and medieval studies, following the established practices of the field, under the guidance of a supervisor in the classical and medieval studies program. Students register for Classical and Medieval Studies 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both Classical and Medieval Studies 457 and 458.   <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s15"/><a name="CM/REs15"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/RE s15. Lost and Rejected Gospels.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Discoveries of "apocryphal gospels" &#8212; some only in the last few years &#8212; have uncovered lost traditions and beliefs of the early church, illuminating the complex process by which early medieval orthodox Christianity emerged from earlier diversity. Early Christians held widely divergent views of Jesus, the apostles, and other early leaders&#8212;traditions that were lost in the emerging orthodoxy. Who were these early leaders? How did they come to be perceived so differently? Why were so many of these ideas suppressed? Readings consist of several apocryphal gospels, including those of Thomas, Peter, Judas, and Mary, and several canonical Gospels for comparison. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s17"/><a name="CMSs17"/><h4 class="crsname">CMS s17. Readings in the <span class="em">Odyssey</span> of Homer.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The <span class="em">Odyssey</span> has proved an inspiring and inexhaustible text over the centuries. This course explores the poem in detail, examining its cultural and literary context and considering modern approaches to this most enigmatic text. The course is taught in English, but students who have completed one or more years of ancient Greek are encouraged to read sections in Greek, and learn how to "perform" the poetry. Not open to students who have received credit for Classical and Medieval Studies s27. Enrollment limited to 15. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C067">The Translated World (C067)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s23"/><a name="AV/CMs23"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/CM s23. Ancient Egypt: Abydos to Meroe.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course surveys the art and architecture of ancient Egypt, with attention given to topics including women in ancient Egypt, the Kingdom of Kush, and the ancient Near East. The history of archeology and current developments in Egyptian archeology are also considered. Some day trips are planned. Not open to students who have received credit for Art and Visual Culture/Classical and Medieval Studies 232. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> R. Corrie.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s29"/><a name="CM/ENs29"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN s29. The Worlds of J. R. R. Tolkien.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">J. R. R. Tolkien, in his double roles as popular writer and Oxford medievalist, taught countless numbers of readers to appreciate many of the central themes of medieval literature. These overarching themes&#8212;including the relationship between the natural and the supernatural spheres, the struggle between good and evil, and the morally ambivalent status of monsters and magicians&#8212;are largely found in early Celtic and Norse mythology. In this course students analyze these myths in an attempt to better understand where Tolkien's <span class="cite">Hobbit</span> is coming from, and how the novelist adopted and adapted medieval material for his modern audience. All texts are read in modern English. Enrollment limited to 30. S. Federico.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s33"/><a name="CM/ENs33"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN s33. Screening the Middle Ages.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines cinematic representations of the Middle Ages, focusing especially on the cultural energies that produce certain visions of the past. The films offer an opportunity to reflect on how our various modern designs on (and desires for) the medieval illuminate the present as much as they animate the past. Students read selections from medieval history and poetry (in translation or manageable Middle English) in conjunction with daily viewings and written assignments; secondary readings are drawn from modern and postmodern film criticism and theory. Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. S. Federico.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="CMSs50"/><h4 class="crsname">CMS s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="101"/><a name="GRK101"/><h4 class="crsname">GRK 101. Elementary Ancient Greek.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The objective of the course is to begin a study of classical Greek as a foundation for upper-level reading courses. It covers the basics of grammar, syntax, and vocabulary building. Students learn to read Greek sentences and passages and to translate from English into Greek. During the early stage much learning by rote of forms and rules is necessary, but students find that Greek is a structured and beautiful language, and the pleasure of reading "in the original" is inestimable. Normally offered every year. D. O'Higgins, Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C020">Ancient Greek (C020)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="101-102"/><a name="GRK101-102"/><h4 class="crsname">GRK 101-102. Elementary Ancient Greek.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The objective of the course is to begin a study of classical Greek as a foundation for upper-level reading courses. It covers the basics of grammar, syntax, and vocabulary building. Students learn to read Greek sentences and passages and to translate from English into Greek. During the early stage much learning by rote of forms and rules is necessary, but students find that Greek is a structured and beautiful language, and the pleasure of reading "in the original" is inestimable. Normally offered every year. D. O'Higgins, Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C020">Ancient Greek (C020)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="102"/><a name="GRK102"/><h4 class="crsname">GRK 102. Elementary Ancient Greek.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The objective of the course is to begin a study of classical Greek as a foundation for upper-level reading courses. It covers the basics of grammar, syntax, and vocabulary building. Students learn to read Greek sentences and passages and to translate from English into Greek. During the early stage much learning by rote of forms and rules is necessary, but students find that Greek is a structured and beautiful language, and the pleasure of reading "in the original" is inestimable. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C020">Ancient Greek (C020)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="201"/><a name="GRK201"/><h4 class="crsname">GRK 201. Classical Prose.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Called the "age of enlightenment," classical Greece witnessed the invention of democracy, philosophy, and medicine, to name but a few. Students read Plato, Thucydides, Demosthenes, or Lysias in order to understand how and why the Greeks created these disciplines and institutions. Prerequisite(s): Greek 101 and 102.  Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C020">Ancient Greek (C020)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="202"/><a name="GRK202"/><h4 class="crsname">GRK 202. Classical Poetry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">From Oedipus' self-blinding to the trial of a cheese grater, Athenian tragedies and comedies portray the human condition and the Athenian political world. Students read the works of the comedians, Aristophanes and Menander, and the tragic poets, Aeschylus, Sophocles, and Euripides, who dramatized and satirized the human condition. Prerequisite(s): Greek 101 and 102. Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C020">Ancient Greek (C020)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="203"/><a name="GRK203"/><h4 class="crsname">GRK 203. Prose about Archaic Greece.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">As the population exploded in archaic Greece, so did political, social, religious, and cultural institutions. The Persians invaded Greece, the Olympics were inaugurated, tyrants were overthrown, and law courts invented. Students examine these momentous events in archaic authors such as Herodotus and Antiphon or in later writers such as Plutarch and Pausanias. Prerequisite(s): Greek 101 and 102. Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C020">Ancient Greek (C020)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="204"/><a name="GRK204"/><h4 class="crsname">GRK 204. Poetry from Archaic Greece.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Homer sang about Troy's destruction and Odysseus' travels; Hesiod, about the birth of gods and his cheating brother. Sappho praised the power of Aphrodite; Alcaeus, the power of wine. Students explore how the poets in archaic Greece sang about their lives and their world. Prerequisite(s): Greek 101 and 102. Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C020">Ancient Greek (C020)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="301"/><a name="GRK301"/><h4 class="crsname">GRK 301. Classical Prose: Advanced.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course covers the same material as Greek 201 but is designed for students who have completed two or more years of college-level Greek. Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C020">Ancient Greek (C020)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="302"/><a name="GRK302"/><h4 class="crsname">GRK 302. Classical Poetry: Advanced.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course covers the same material as Greek 202 but is designed for students who have completed two or more years of college-level Greek. Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C020">Ancient Greek (C020)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="303"/><a name="GRK303"/><h4 class="crsname">GRK 303. Prose about Archaic Greece: Advanced.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course covers the same material as Greek 203 but is designed for students who have completed two or more years of college-level Greek. Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C020">Ancient Greek (C020)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="304"/><a name="GRK304"/><h4 class="crsname">GRK 304. Poetry from Archaic Greece: Advanced.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course covers the same material as Greek 204 but is designed for students who have completed two or more years of college-level Greek. Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C020">Ancient Greek (C020)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="GRK360"/><h4 class="crsname">GRK 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C077">Greek Civilization (C077)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="101"/><a name="LATN101"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN 101. Elementary Latin.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A humanistic introduction to classical Latin vocabulary, forms, and syntax, with special emphasis on reading the actual words of ancient authors. Relations to English grammar and etymology are stressed. The course concentrates on Latin-English translation, with some English-Latin composition. Latin 101 is not open to students with two or more years of Latin in secondary school.  Normally offered every year. M. Imber.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C010">Latin (C010)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="101-102"/><a name="LATN101-102"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN 101-102. Elementary Latin.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A humanistic introduction to classical Latin vocabulary, forms, and syntax, with special emphasis on reading the actual words of ancient authors. Relations to English grammar and etymology are stressed. The course concentrates on Latin-English translation, with some English-Latin composition. Latin 101 is not open to students with two or more years of Latin in secondary school.  Normally offered every year. M. Imber.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C010">Latin (C010)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="102"/><a name="LATN102"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN 102. Elementary Latin.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A humanistic introduction to classical Latin vocabulary, forms, and syntax, with special emphasis on reading the actual words of ancient authors. Relations to English grammar and etymology are stressed. Concentration on Latin-English translation, with some English-Latin composition. Latin 101 is not open to students with two or more years of Latin in secondary school.   Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C010">Latin (C010)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="201"/><a name="LATN201"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN 201. Prose of the Empire.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The persecution of Christians, the eruption of Mount Vesuvius, and Nero's fiddle are topics of the diverse literature of the Roman Empire. Students read letters, philosophical treatises, histories, and novels from the likes of Tacitus, Seneca, Pliny, and Suetonius. Prerequisite(s): Latin 101 and 102.  Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C010">Latin (C010)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="202"/><a name="LATN202"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN 202. Poetry of the Empire.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">From Ovid's fables of women turning into trees to Lucan's descriptions of battles and Seneca's drama of Thyestes who feasts on his sons, the tumultuous events of the Roman Empire find strange expression in the poets who could not write openly about the cruelties of their emperors. Students read the works of Ovid, Seneca, Lucan, Statius, and Martial.  Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C010">Latin (C010)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="203"/><a name="LATN203"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN 203. Republican Prose.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Roman Republic was imagined to be the result of fratricide and rape. Caesar crossed the Rubicon and Cicero's hands and ears were cut off and then hung in the Forum. The course explores the social, political, and religious foundations as well as the violence of the Roman Republic through the eyes of authors such as Livy, Cato, Cicero, Sallust, and Caesar. Prerequisite(s): Latin 101 and 102. Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C010">Latin (C010)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="204"/><a name="LATN204"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN 204. Republican Poetry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Why do slaves always have the leading roles in Roman comedy? Was Aeneas pious or power-hungry? Did Lesbia really have 300 lovers? The Roman Republic was explained, celebrated, criticized, and ignored in the works of its poets. The course answers why and how through a study of such writers as Plautus, Catullus, Virgil, and Horace. Prerequisite(s): Latin 101 and 102. Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C010">Latin (C010)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="301"/><a name="LATN301"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN 301. Prose of the Empire: Advanced.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course covers the same material as Latin 201 but is designed for students who have completed two or more years of college-level Latin. Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C010">Latin (C010)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="302"/><a name="LATN302"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN 302. Poetry of the Empire: Advanced.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course covers the same material as Latin 202 but is designed for students who have completed two or more years of college-level Latin. Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C010">Latin (C010)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="303"/><a name="LATN303"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN 303. Republican Prose: Advanced.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course covers the same material as Latin 203 but is designed for students who have completed two or more years of college-level Latin. Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C010">Latin (C010)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="304"/><a name="LATN304"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN 304. Republican Poetry: Advanced.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course covers the same material as Latin 204 but is designed for students who have completed two or more years of college-level Latin. Open to first-year students. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C010">Latin (C010)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="LATN360"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C010">Latin (C010)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365"/><a name="LATN365"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN 365. Special Topics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Designed for the small seminar group of students who may have particular interests in areas of study that go beyond the regular course offerings. Periodic conferences and papers are required.   Instructor permission is required.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="LATNs50"/><h4 class="crsname">LATN s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product.  Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=632&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>

               