<div class="Course"><a name="101"/><a name="ECON101"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 101. Principles of Microeconomics: Prices and Markets.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of competition and monopoly, antitrust policy and public-utility regulation, determination of wages and other sources of income, income distribution, and pollution and public policy.  Enrollment limited to 35. Normally offered every semester. L. Lewis, J. Hughes, Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="103"/><a name="ECON103"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 103. Principles of Macroeconomics: Income and Employment.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A survey of major economic issues in the United States, such as economic growth, employment, and inflation. Students discuss the causes and consequences of fluctuations in income, employment, and inflation, and analyze fiscal and monetary policies designed to correct them. Economics 101 is helpful preparation, but not required.  Enrollment limited to 35. Normally offered every semester. M. Daley.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="217"/><a name="ECON217"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 217. Introduction to Accounting.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The theory of accounting is presented to the beginner as knowledge fundamental to understanding any business enterprise. The course includes practice with accounting methods and exposure to financial statement relationships. Not open to students who have received credit for Economics s21.   Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. B. Farber.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="221"/><a name="ECON221"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 221. The World Economy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Trends and patterns in international trade and finance are discussed in relation to topics such as trade and growth, tariffs and trade restrictions, economic integration, and international economic cooperation and policy.  Not open to students who have received credit for Economics 334. Prerequisite(s): Economics 103.  Offered with varying frequency. W. Chen.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="222"/><a name="ECON222"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 222. Environmental Economics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The preservation of environmental quality and the struggle of people to improve their economic circumstances are often in conflict. This course explores the economic basis of environmental problems and examines alternative policies aimed at reducing environmental degradation. Among the topics are the deficiencies in the market system and existing property-rights system that contribute to environmental problems, cases where public intervention offers the potential for improvement, cases amenable to market-based approaches, and the public-policy tools available to promote environmental goals. Prerequisite(s) or corequisite(s): Economics 101. Not open to students who have received credit for Economics s36.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every year. L. Lewis.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="223"/><a name="ECON223"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 223. Law and Economics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces the use of economic methods to examine laws and legal institutions. The fundamental concepts of economics-scarcity, maximization, and marginal analysis are used to predict the effect of legal rules on behavior, and to evaluate how well a particular rule achieves its intended end. At another level, civil law may be viewed as another system of resource allocation and wealth distribution, as the legal system is often used to craft a remedy when markets fail in their allocative role. Topics may include property law, contract law, accident law, family law, criminal law, and copyright and trademark law. Prerequisite(s): Economics 101. Not open to students who have received credit for Economics s35.  Enrollment limited to 20. Offered with varying frequency. J. Hughes.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="228"/><a name="ECON228"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 228. Antitrust and Regulation.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course analyzes economic-policy issues of government intervention in the private sector through antitrust and regulatory policies. Specific topics examined include theories of monopoly and competition, the evolution of United States antitrust policy, key antitrust issues and cases, regulation of natural monopoly and oligopoly, capture theory, and comparative antitrust and regulatory policies. Prerequisite(s): Economics 101. Open to first-year students. Normally offered every other year. C. Schwinn.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="229"/><a name="AS/EC229"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/EC 229. Economics of Greater China.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Chinese are among the world's leading experimentalists in economics. The twentieth-century economic history of China, Taiwan, Hong Kong, and the overseas Chinese diaspora spans the entire gamut of economic regimes from virtually unrestricted competition to rigid state management. This course surveys economic development in Greater China with emphasis on understanding how institutions and institutional change affect economic and social development. Prerequisite(s): Economics 101 or 103.  Not open to students who have received credit for Economics 229. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 45. Normally offered every other year. M. Maurer-Fazio.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="230"/><a name="ECON230"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 230. Economics of Women, Men, and Work.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An examination of the changing roles of women and men in the market economy. Introductory topics include the family as an economic unit, discrimination, and occupational segregation. Other topics include the economics of marriage, fertility, divorce, child care, and the growing feminization of poverty. The final section of the course examines the feminist critique of the assumptions and methodology of neoclassical economics, and the potential for incorporating these insights into the practice of economics. Prerequisite(s): Economics 101.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 22. Offered with varying frequency. J. Hughes.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="231"/><a name="AS/EC231"/><h4 class="crsname">AS/EC 231. The Economic Development of Japan.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course surveys the development of Japan's economy. A brief historical introduction focuses on the preconditions for economic modernization and the role of the government in Japan's late nineteenth- and early twentieth-century experience. The course then concentrates on an overview of Japan's post-World War II experience of recovery, explosive growth, slowdown, and attempted reform. Students consider whether the Japanese economy operates according to principles, objectives, and structures that are substantially different from those of the West. Japan's economic impact on other East Asian countries and relatedness with the world economy are also explored. Prerequisite(s): Economics 101 or 103.  Not open to students who have received credit for Economics 231. Open to first-year students. Normally offered every other year. M. Maurer-Fazio.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="235"/><a name="ECON235"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 235. Growth, Inequality, and Globalization.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Over the past fifty years, economic growth has raised hundreds of millions of people out of poverty, while leaving the lives of additional hundreds of millions untouched or worse. The enormous expansion in world trade since the end of the Cold War has fueled concern about threats to national culture and identity and the homogenization of society. This course introduces students to classical and contemporary economic growth models and measures of income inequality. Students examine elements of trade theory such as comparative advantage, gains from trade, and trade liberalization in order to ascertain whether globalization may threaten economic growth. Prerequisite(s): Economics 101 or 103.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 22. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="250"/><a name="ECON250"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 250. Statistics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Topics include probability theory, sampling theory, estimation, hypothesis testing, and linear regression. Prospective economics majors should take this course in or before the fall semester of the sophomore year.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 36. Normally offered every semester. M. Murray.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="255"/><a name="ECON255"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 255. Econometrics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Topics include multiple regression using time series and cross-sectional data, simultaneous equation models, and an introduction to forecasting.  Prerequisite(s): Economics 250 and Mathematics 105.  Normally offered every semester. C. Schwinn.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="260"/><a name="ECON260"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 260. Intermediate Microeconomic Theory.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Compares models of perfect competition and market failure, with emphasis on the consequences for efficiency and equity. Topics include consumer choice, firm behavior, markets for goods and inputs, choice over time, monopoly, oligopoly, monopolistic competition, externalities, and public goods. Prerequisite(s): Economics 101 and Mathematics 105.  Normally offered every semester. A. Williams.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270"/><a name="ECON270"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 270. Intermediate Macroeconomic Theory.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This study of national income determination includes movements involving consumption, saving, investment, demand for money, supply of money, interest rates, price levels, wage rates, and unemployment. Monetary policy, fiscal policy, inflation, and growth models are considered. Prerequisite(s): Economics 101 and 103 and Mathematics 105.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="309"/><a name="ECON309"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 309. Economics of Less-Developed Countries.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course examines the causes of the poverty of nations, various potential paths to economic growth, and the effects of policies of the rich countries on less-developed countries. Included are such topics as industrialization, the "green revolution," population growth, environmental degradation, trade policies, debt, multinational corporations, and foreign aid. The development of individual countries is examined in light of the great diversity of experiences among developing economies. Prerequisite(s): Economics 255, 260, and 270. Normally offered every other year. M. Maurer-Fazio, Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="310"/><a name="ECON310"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 310. Economics of Not-for-Profit Firms.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course studies the not-for-profit (NFP) firm as an institutional form that society has used in response to market failures, such as those caused by the presence of jointly consumed goods, asymmetric information, or principal-agent problems. Examples are taken from industries where the NFP form is prevalent: health care, education, museums, performing arts, and public radio and television. Issues related to the financing of NFPs, including their capital structure and their reliance on donations as opposed to commercial revenues, are also explored. Prerequisite(s): Economics 255 and 260. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Winter 2006</span> Enrollment limited to 20. G. Perkins.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="311"/><a name="ECON311"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 311. Public Economics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An analysis of basic issues in the field of public finance. The course covers a wide range of topics, including the welfare implications of expenditure and taxation policies of governments, the economic rationale of governmental provision of goods and services, fiscal institutions in the United States, efficiency and distributive aspects of taxation, effects of taxation on household and firm behavior, intergovernmental fiscal relations, and the public debt.  Prerequisite(s): Economics 255, 260, and 270.  Normally offered every other year. M. Murray.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="318"/><a name="ECON318"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 318. Advanced Macroeconomics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Theories and empirical studies of business cycles: fixed-investment behavior, inventory activity, and monetary fluctuations. The course examines recent work on inflation, expectations, economic growth theory, and techniques in current use for forecasting general economic activity. Prerequisite(s): Economics 255 and 270.  Normally offered every other year. D. Aschauer, Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="320"/><a name="ECON320"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 320. Advanced Econometrics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Econometric estimation techniques beyond least squares, including instrumental variables, maximum likelihood, the generalized method of moments, and both non-parametric and simulation methods are introduced. Models for panel data, stochastically trending variables, and limited dependent variables are also discussed. Students' choice of projects determines which topics are considered in detail. Prerequisite(s): Economics 255.  Enrollment limited to 22. Offered with varying frequency. M. Murray.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="321"/><a name="ECON321"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 321. Monetary Policy and Financial Markets.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An analysis of money supply, money demand, alternative theories of the monetary mechanism, central banking, and the conduct of monetary policy. Prerequisite(s): Economics 255 and 270.  Normally offered every year. D. Aschauer, Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="324"/><a name="ECON324"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 324. Corporate Finance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The cost of capital, dividend policy, security valuation, portfolio theory, capital budgeting, and the efficient-markets hypothesis are among the topics investigated. Emphasis is on the testing of hypotheses derived from economic theory. Prerequisite(s): Economics 255 and 260.  Normally offered every year. C. Schwinn.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="325"/><a name="ECON325"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 325. Prices, Property, and the Problem of the Commons.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An analysis of water resources and fisheries economics. Topics include water allocation, scarcity and pricing, water rights, cost-benefit analysis, valuation, water markets, and problems related to common-property resources such as underground aquifers and fisheries. Economic incentives for pollution control including tradable pollution permit programs for water quality maintenance are also covered. Prerequisite(s): Economics 250, 255, and 260. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every year. L. Lewis.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="331"/><a name="ECON331"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 331. Labor Economics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of human resources and the labor market. Topics include racial and sexual discrimination, theories of unemployment and job search, income distribution and poverty, Becker's new household economics, unions and collective bargaining, and government intervention in the labor market. Prerequisite(s): Economics 255 and 260.  Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every other year. J. Hughes.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="333"/><a name="ECON333"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 333. International Trade.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Classical and modern theories of international trade analyzed in light of current trends and patterns in the world economy. Attention is focused on the gains from trade, the impact of tariffs and other types of trade restrictions on national economic welfare, the trade problems of less-developed countries, and the theory of economic integration. Prerequisite(s): Economics 255 and 260.  Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="334"/><a name="ECON334"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 334. International Macroeconomics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Study of the impact of international trade; international capital movements; and balance of payments policies on domestic output, employment, and price levels. Prerequisite(s): Economics 255 and 270.  Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. D. Aschauer, Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="339"/><a name="ECON339"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 339. Industrial Organization.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Theories of the firm are used to explain the organization of economic activity across markets and within firms. The effects of pricing behavior, merger activity, advertising, and research and development on efficiency and social welfare are examined. Prerequisite(s): Economics 255 and 260.  Normally offered every other year. C. Schwinn.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="348"/><a name="ECON348"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 348. Urban Economics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Microeconomic tools are applied to analyze cities. Among the topics are the spatial structure of cities, trends in urban development in the United States, urbanization and African development, industrial and residential location choices, rent control, housing subsidies, squatter settlements, racial segregation, and urban finance. Prerequisite(s): Economics 255 and 260.  Normally offered every other year. M. Murray.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="349"/><a name="ECON349"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 349. The Economics of Taxation.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Governments finance their activities by taxing or borrowing.  Do taxes promote economic efficiency?  Are taxes fair?  In this context and with a focus on the U.S tax structure, we will study taxes on personal and corporate income as well as taxes on consumption and wealth.  Repeal the &#191;death&#191; tax? Reduce taxes on capital gains?  Eliminate double taxation on dividends?  Replace our income tax with a flat tax plus a negative-income tax?  Would a VAT be better than an income tax? (What&#191;s a VAT?)  Are deficits a tax on future generations? These are but a few of the tax policy issues to be discussed. Prerequisite(s): Economics 255, 260, and 270. Course is subject to approval. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall 2006.</span> G. Perkins.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="ECON360"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="ECON457"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Prior to entrance into Economics 457, students must submit for approval a thesis proposal based on work done in a nonintroductory course. All majors take Economics 457; honors candidates take Economics 458 after completing Economics 457. Prerequisite(s): at least two 300-level economics courses.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457, 458"/><a name="ECON457, 458"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 457, 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Prior to entrance into Economics 457, students must submit for approval a thesis proposal based on work done in a nonintroductory course. All majors take Economics 457; honors candidates take Economics 458 after completing Economics 457. Prerequisite(s): at least two 300-level economics courses.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="ECON458"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Prior to entrance into Economics 457, students must submit for approval a thesis proposal based on work done in a nonintroductory course. All majors take Economics 457; honors candidates take Economics 458 after completing Economics 457. Prerequisite(s): at least two 300-level economics courses.  Department chair permission is required. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s19"/><a name="EC/SOs19"/><h4 class="crsname">EC/SO s19. Issues for a United Europe in the Twenty-First Century.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">As European integration deepens, issues related to governance, economic life, and identity emerge. A united Europe requires common political, economic, and cultural systems. This unit examines the nature, limitations, potential, and legitimacy of those systems, by providing firsthand visits to key countries, institutions, and  associations. Students visit Brussels, Paris, London, Copenhagen, and Barcelona. Different cities offer different opportunities to investigate political, economic, or cultural systems.  Not open to students who have received credit for Economics s19 or Sociology s19. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. F. Duina.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="ECONs21"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON s21. Principles and Applications of Accounting.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to the concepts and uses of accounting utilizing case studies. Emphasis is on the accounting cycle, construction and analysis of financial statements, asset valuation, and corporate accounting. Not open to students who have received credit for Economics 217.   Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. B. Farber.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s27"/><a name="EC/ESs27"/><h4 class="crsname">EC/ES s27. Sustaining the Masses.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students in this unit investigate the contradictions and complementarities between economic development and global economic integration on the one hand and environmental protection on the other. Students spend up to four weeks in China visiting farming communities, large- and small-scale industrial enterprises, reforestation sites, nature reserves, and pollution control facilities. They also meet with villagers, workers, and government officials. Linkages between local and international economics, politics, history, culture, and the environment are explored using China as a case study. Recommended background: one or more of the following: Economics 101, 222, 227, 229, or Environmental Studies 202.  Not open to students who have received credit for Economics s27 or Environmental Studies s27. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 10. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. M. Maurer-Fazio, J. Hughes.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s31"/><a name="ECONs31"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON s31. Economic Growth and Productivity Enhancement.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An intensive study of economic growth from theoretical and empirical perspectives, including the Solow growth model, the Ramsey optimizing model, and theories emphasizing imperfect competition and increasing returns to scale. This unit examines empirical studies of economic growth and factors found to be important determinants of growth in real output, with particular emphasis on productivity growth. Prerequisite(s): Economics 255 and 270. Not open to students who have received credit for Economics 235. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. D. Aschauer.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s33"/><a name="EC/ESs33"/><h4 class="crsname">EC/ES s33. Valuation of Human-Altered Ecosystems.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">How is the value of an ecosystem altered by human development? Answering this question requires an understanding of both economics and ecosystem structure and function. In this interdisciplinary unit, students explore the structure and function of ecosystems before and after human modification and the relationship of these characteristics to their economic value. Students focus on river systems in Maine and contrast these with the Mississippi River from source to sea. This course involves many day trips and two longer trips off campus. Prerequisite(s): Environmental Studies 203 or Economics 222. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 12. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. H. Ewing, L. Lewis.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s34"/><a name="ECONs34"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON s34. Democratic Enterprises and Corporate Governance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Democratic decision making, involving all the employees of a firm, represents a form of corporate governance that seems natural in a democratic society. Why, then, are so few firms governed in this manner? After examining democratically managed firms in the former Yugoslavia, firms in the Mondrag&#243;n community of Spain, and plywood cooperatives in the Pacific Northwest, this unit explores the economic incentives and political forces that have shaped the dominant, nondemocratic form of corporate governance found in democratic societies. Prerequisite(s): Economics 101 and 103.  Open to first-year students. Offered with varying frequency. C. Schwinn.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="ECONs50"/><h4 class="crsname">ECON s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>

               