<div class="Course"><a name="231"/><a name="EDUC231"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 231. Perspectives on Education.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to foundational perspectives (anthropological, historical, philosophical, psychological, and sociological) about education and their relationships to the realities present in contemporary schools and classrooms.  Students consider several large questions: What should be the purpose of education in a democratic society? What should be the role of the school? What should be the ideal of an educated person? Should this be the same for all students or differentiated in some way for particular individuals or groups of students? Who should participate in making decisions about schools? Students must complete at least thirty hours of fieldwork. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 28. Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="240"/><a name="EDUC240"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 240. Gender Issues in Education.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course considers education, especially classroom teaching, in relation to recent theory and research on gender. In addition to providing a feminist philosophical perspective on education, the course explores the implications of gender, race, class, and sexual orientation on ways of knowing, developing, and interacting for K-12 curriculum and classroom practice for both males and females. A thirty-hour field experience is required.   Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every year. A. Dodd.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="242"/><a name="ED/SO242"/><h4 class="crsname">ED/SO 242. Race, Cultural Pluralism, and Equality in American Education.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Through historical, political, and philosophical lenses this course explores the question: What would equal educational opportunity look like in a multicultural society? The course compares divergent approaches to the education of distinct racial/ethnic groups within the United States&#8212;African Americans, Asian Americans, European Americans, Hispanics, and Native Americans. In light of contextual perspectives in educational thought, the course confronts contemporary debates surrounding how the race/ethnicity of students should affect the composition, curriculum, and teaching methods of schools, colleges, and universities. Specific issues explored include bilingual education, college admissions, curriculum inclusion, desegregation, ethnic studies, and hiring practices. A thirty-hour field experience is required. Recommended background: Education 231. Not open to students who have received credit for Education 242 or Sociology 242. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every other year. S. Smith.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="245"/><a name="EDUC245"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 245. Literacy in Preschool and Elementary Years.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines how literacy is defined and developed through a child's early and elementary years from a variety of perspectives: social, educational, political, and linguistic. Students connect these theories with practice by exploring various methods and materials that foster literacy development in elementary students and by doing fieldwork in local schools. Working collaboratively with classroom teachers, students design and implement literacy development strategies and projects with elementary students. A thirty-hour field experience is required. Recommended background: Education 231 and Education/Psychology 262.  Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. H. Gurney.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="250"/><a name="EDUC250"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 250. Critical Perspective on Pedagogy and Curriculum.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines and critiques shifting historical and contemporary notions of good pedagogy and curriculum. Particular emphasis is given to the ways teaching can contribute to social justice. Possible models of critical teaching include: teachers who are professional researchers, saviors, caregivers, performers, "unteachers," and third parties; and teaching that critiques and transforms, that is culturally relevant, and that engages in activism. Students spend thirty hours in a local classroom and create a curriculum unit and statement of pedagogical philosophy that draws on the different models. Recommended background: Education 231. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="262"/><a name="ED/PY262"/><h4 class="crsname">ED/PY 262. Action Research.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Action research often begins with a general idea that some kind of improvement or change is desirable. For example, a teacher who is experiencing discipline problems in a classroom may seek an understanding of this issue with the help of trusted observers. In this course, students collaborate with local teachers or service providers on research projects that originate in their work sites. Class meetings introduce design issues, methods of data collection and analysis, and ways of reporting research. Prerequisite(s): Psychology 218 or Education 231. Not open to students who have received credit for Education 262 or Psychology 262. Enrollment limited to 15 per section. Normally offered every year. G. Nigro.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270"/><a name="EDUC270"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 270. Educating for Democracy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Troubling voter turnout rates and levels of civic participation in the United States raise questions about the health of our democracy. Youth, in particular, express a sense of alienation from government and formal political processes. What does this say about education for democracy? If education is vital to the success of democratic governance, what might be done in schools and other educational institutions to better engage young people in public life? This course explores the relationship between education and democracy and various approaches to civic and citizenship education. A thirty-hour field experience is required. Recommended background: Education 231. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Winter 2006.</span> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. S. Smith.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="280"/><a name="ED/WS280"/><h4 class="crsname">ED/WS 280. Globalization and Education.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this course students examine the impacts of globalization upon educational institutions, practices, and experiences. We live in an era characterized by global flows of ideas and information, commodities, and persons. This course explores how these transformative forces influence the educative process in different geographical, national, and cultural contexts. Topics address a set of concerns with enduring resonance to the field of educational studies including social inequity and change, relations of power, and constructions of race, gender, and social class. A thirty-hour field experience is required. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Fall 2006.</span> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 28. Normally offered every other year. P. Buck.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="343"/><a name="EDUC343"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 343. Learning and Teaching: Theories and Practice.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students explore learning and teaching with an emphasis on reflective practice. This seminar begins with an historical review of several theories about learners and the learning process as a basis of critically examining contemporary learning theory and practice. Students examine the ways in which various learning theories and the standards movement affect curriculum, classroom practice, and the roles of both children and teachers. They also consider how their teaching philosophies are bound by their views about human nature and the intellectual, behavioral, and ethical growth of children. A required thirty-hour field experience is individually defined by students' content-area and age-group interests. Recommended background: Education 231, Psychology 101. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="355"/><a name="EDUC355"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 355. Literacy Development and Assessment: Theory and Practice.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines literacy development and engages students in active literacy assessment and improvement in local schools. The course explores a variety of perspectives on literacy using the lenses of social, educational, political, and linguistic theory. Students collaborate with teachers in local schools to explore and use the Guided Reading Model of reading improvement and assessment. This provides, in turn, the knowledge base for a critical examination of the program as well as an understanding of its impact upon schools, teachers, and students as individuals and as communities. A thirty-hour field experience is required. Recommended background: Education 231, or Education/Psychology 262. Enrollment limited to 12. H. Gurney.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="EDUC360"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="362"/><a name="EDUC362"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 362. Basic Concepts in Special Education.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the characteristics of children who require special consideration in order to learn. It considers the ethical bases and the legal requirements for educating students with special needs. It explores ways all children can be helped to succeed in the mainstream classroom despite their different learning styles and abilities, physical impairments, and emotional/behavioral disorders. Attention is given to the influences of cultural, social, racial, and ethnic backgrounds, and gender. A thirty-hour field experience is required. This course meets the requirement of a course about teaching exceptional students in the mainstream classroom established by the State of Maine for certification. Recommended background: Education 231. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every year. A. Dodd.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365"/><a name="EDUC365"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 365. Special Topics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A course or seminar offered from time to time and reserved for a special topic selected by the department.  Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="378"/><a name="AN/ED378"/><h4 class="crsname">AN/ED 378. Ethnographic Approaches to Education.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Ethnography focuses on the daily lives and meaning-making processes of people who associate regularly in local networks, institutions, or communities. Ethnographers observe, interview, and participate in the routine activities of the people they study. They also explore the connections between locally situated activity and broader realms of symbolic meaning and social organization. This course  introduces students to interpretive methods with which to examine the webs of meaning that give shape to educational spaces. Through active engagement in empirical research in educational settings across the Lewiston-Auburn community, students grapple with theoretical assumptions, procedures, and standards of quality in ethnographic research. A thirty-hour field experience is required. Enrollment limited to 15. P. Buck.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="380"/><a name="ED/SO380"/><h4 class="crsname">ED/SO 380. Education, Reform, and Politics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The United States has experienced more than three centuries of growth and change in the organization of public and private education. The goals of this course are to examine 1) contemporary reform issues and political processes in relation to the constituencies of school, research, legal, and policy-making communities and 2) how educational policy is formulated, implemented, and evaluated. The study of these areas emphasizes public K-12 education but includes postsecondary education. Examples of specific educational policy arenas include governance, school choice (e.g., charter schools, magnet schools, and vouchers), school funding, standards and accountability, and parental and community involvement. A research-based field component of at least thirty hours is required. Recommended background: one or more courses in education and sociology. Not open to students who have received credit for Education 380 or Sociology 380. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. S. Smith.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="447"/><a name="EDUC447"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 447. Curriculum and Methods.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course continues study of the concepts needed to understand curriculum design and program evaluation, and helps students develop the skills needed to design and teach curriculum units in their subject area. The course is part workshop: students plan, develop, teach, and evaluate their own curriculum units. At the same time, students read about and reflect on classic questions in curriculum and instruction, such as: To what extent are teachers responsible for developing their own curriculum? Should curriculum and instruction focus on transmitting established knowledge, developing individuals' talents, or preparing successful members of society? Can teachers assess students' knowledge in ways that allow them to learn from the assessments? What particular teaching methods are appropriate for the different disciplines? Students develop a repertoire of methods to use in student teaching and in future teaching. Prerequisite(s): Education 231 and  460. Corequisite(s): Education 448 and 461. Normally offered every year. P. Buck, A. Dodd.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="448"/><a name="EDUC448"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 448. Senior Seminar: Reflection and Engagement.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The seminar helps students reflect on and engage with their experiences as teachers. Students are encouraged to develop their own philosophies of education and to use these philosophies in planning and teaching their classes. The seminar also addresses three areas of practice&#8212;technology, environmental education, and interdisciplinary approaches&#8212;and helps students incorporate these into their teaching. Prerequisite(s): Education 231, 362, and 460. Corequisite(s): Education 447 and 461. Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. A. Dodd, P. Buck.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="460"/><a name="EDUC460"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 460. Student Teaching I.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This is an intensive field experience in secondary education. Students begin by observing a host teacher in their academic field, spending one or two class periods each day in the high school. Soon they begin teaching at least one class per day. In regular, informal meetings, they are guided and supported by their host teachers, a supervisor from the Bates Department of Education, and other members of a supervisory support team. Students also meet weekly at Bates to address conceptual matters and to discuss problems and successes in the classroom. These weekly seminars include workshops in content area methods and extensive informal reflective writing. Students begin to move toward proficiency in four areas of practice: curriculum, instruction, and evaluation; classroom management, interactions, and relationships; diversity; time management and organizational skills. Prerequisite(s): Education 231 and 362.  Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. A. Dodd, P. Buck.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="461"/><a name="EDUC461"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC 461. Student Teaching II.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course continues and deepens the experiences and reflection begun in Education 460. Students spend four or five class periods each day in a local high school observing, teaching, and becoming fully involved in the life of the school. Students continue to meet regularly with their host teacher, Bates supervisor, and others on their supervisory support team. Although there are no weekly meetings for this course, students spend extensive time planning their classes and reflecting in writing on their experiences. Prerequisite(s): Education 231, 362, and 460. Corequisite(s): Education 447 and 448. Normally offered every year. A. Dodd, P. Buck.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s23"/><a name="EDUCs23"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC s23. Educating for Democracy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Voter turnout and civic participation in the United States are at an all-time low. Youth, in particular, express a sense of alienation from government and formal political processes. What does this say about education for democracy? If education is vital to the success of democratic governance, what might be done in schools and other educational institutions to better engage young people in public life? This unit explores the relationship between education and democracy and various approaches to civic and citizenship education. Students participate in a service-learning field experience (at least thirty hours) in order to investigate and inform education for democracy in local communities. Recommended background: Education 231. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. S. Smith.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s25"/><a name="EDUCs25"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC s25. Democratic Dialogue.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">How do democratic citizens talk and reason together in order to reach collective decisions? How are ideals of equality, respect, inclusion, and civility modeled in such processes? In recent years the theory of deliberative democracy, as well as practical models of deliberation and dialogue, have gained attention in a variety of national and international contexts ranging from scholarly research and policy formulation to grassroots political organizing. This unit explores the theoretical underpinnings of deliberative democracy and experiments with specific approaches to dialogue, particularly in relationship to public policy and uses of dialogue in educational settings. A thirty-hour field experience is required. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Short Term 2006</span> Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. S. Smith.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s27"/><a name="EDUCs27"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC s27. Literacy in the Community.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The field of "new literacy studies" calls into question the traditional emphasis upon discrete reading and writing skills. In an expanded definition scholars place literacy within anthropological and cross-cultural frameworks that attend to the embeddedness of reading and writing practices within families, communities, and cultures. This unit introduces students to the literature of new literacy studies and educational anthropology in conjunction with a thirty-hour service-learning placement in the Lewiston area. Students are asked to investigate the impact culturally informed knowledge and experience have upon the literacy practices of those community members with whom they work closely. Enrollment limited to 30. P. Buck.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s28"/><a name="ED/ENs28"/><h4 class="crsname">ED/EN s28. Children's Writing Workshop.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students read and discuss a wide range of literature for and by children as well as pertinent critical studies, and travel weekly to Dunn Elementary School in New Gloucester to work with third, fourth, and fifth graders on well-known poetry and fiction as well as the children's own creative writing. With help from the children, they produce a classroom magazine and organize a poetry/fiction reading. A thirty-hour field experience is required. Prerequisite(s): One course in either English or Education. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Short Term 2006</span> Enrollment limited to 12. Offered with varying frequency. L. Nayder.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="EDUCs50"/><h4 class="crsname">EDUC s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>

               