<div class="Course"><a name="121"/><a name="ENG121"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 121. Colloquia in Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Colloquia introduce students to the study of literature from a variety of perspectives, with a focus on such objects as author, genre, and literary period. These courses not only delve into their particular subject matter, they also allow a preliminary discussion of critical vocabulary and methods that will carry over into more advanced courses. Discussion and frequent writing assignments characterize each section. Prospective majors are urged to take at least one colloquium.  Enrollment limited to 25 per section.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121A"/><a name="ENG121A"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 121A.  Monsters, Magicians, and Medievalism.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Medieval literature is famous for its monsters and magicians: from the dragon of Beowulf to the fairies of romance and the Merlin of the Arthur story, supernatural beings play a significant role in the plot and purpose of narratives from the Middle Ages. Likewise, in modern stories about the Middle Ages (especially Tolkien's), magicians and monsters figure prominently. This course explores the multiple meanings and effects related to this population of supernatural beings; students consider how and why such creatures appear in the texts and how they help to define the genre of medievalism. They read a number of medieval texts (in modern English translation) and a sampling of modern texts about the Middle Ages. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. S. Federico.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121B"/><a name="ENG121B"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 121B. Introduction to Narrative Poetry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Reading a broad variety of poetry, students engage in a series of questions about the difference between poems that tell stories in a conventional sense and those that do not. Poets include Wordsworth, Rossetti, Frost, and Rich, among others. The colloquium seeks to foster an understanding of the pleasure and power of poetry through thinking and writing about poetry, reading poetry aloud, and writing poetry.  Enrollment limited to 25 per section. Offered with varying frequency. A. Thompson.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121C"/><a name="CM/EN121C"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN 121C. Arthurian Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The story of King Arthur of Britain and his Knights of the Round Table is one of Western civilization's most enduring legends. This course explores those elements of the Arthur story that make it so universally compelling in addition to the ways in which its details have been adapted according to the needs and desires of its changing audience. Topics considered include feudal loyalty and kinship, women and marriage, monsters and magic, the culture of violence and warfare, and the stylistic and narrative features of the legendary mode. Students consider modern versions of the story by Marion Zimmer Bradley and T. H. White, Victorian versions by Tennyson and Beardsley, and, in modern English translations, French, English, and Latin versions made popular in the twelfth through fifteenth centuries. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall  2005.</span> Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. S. Federico.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121C"/><a name="ENG121C"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 121C. Frost, Stevens, Williams.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Robert Frost, Wallace Stevens, and William Carlos Williams constitute a solid American modernist grain in twentieth-century poetry. Thorough reading of their work lets us question their surprising affinities and differences: What did each poet take to be the place and function of poetry? Does the regional/parochial flavor in Frost's work enhance or limit its impact? To what extent are we justified in deeming Stevens a philosophical poet? Does Williams's materialist aesthetic limit the range of his work, or deepen its impact? What vision of life in America does each seem to offer? Students may consider the work of tutelary ancestors, competitors, and critics, but the focus is on comprehensive reading, writing, and discussion of these poets' poems, early and late. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Winter 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 25. R. Farnsworth.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121E"/><a name="ENG121E"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 121E. Introduction to Poetry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to reading poetry through the close reading of British and American poems from the Renaissance to the present day. Topics include authorial intention, literary "meaning," cultural context, the diversity of traditional forms, and contemporary lyric genres. The course is based on the discussion of one or two poems each class day.   Enrollment limited to 25 per section. Normally offered every year. S. Dillon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121G"/><a name="EN/WS121G"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/WS 121G. Asian American Women Writers.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines from a sociohistorical perspective fictional, autobiographical, and critical writings by Asian American women including Sui Sin Far, Gish Jen, Maxine Hong Kingston, Trinh Minh-ha, Bharati Mukherjee, Tahira Naqvi, Cathy Song, Marianne Villanueva, and Hisaye Yamamoto. Students explore their issues, especially with concerns of personal and cultural identity, as both Asian and American, as females, as minorities, as (often) postcolonial subjects. The course highlights the varied immigration and social histories of women from different Asian countries, often homogenized as "Oriental" in mainstream American cultural representations. Not open to students who have received credit for English 121G or Women's Studies 121G. Enrollment limited to 25 per section. Offered with varying frequency. L. Shankar.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121H"/><a name="ENG121H"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 121H. The Bront&#235;s.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Reading a selection of fiction and poetry by the three Bront&#235; sisters, as well as critical essays about them, students consider questions of authorial intention, and discuss the relation between literature and history in the Victorian period.  Particular attention is paid to the Bront&#235;s' representations of gender and class, and to the interrelations between these social categories.    Not open to students who have received credit for First-Year Seminar 306. Enrollment limited to 25 per section. Offered with varying frequency. L. Nayder.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121K"/><a name="ENG121K"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 121K. Frankenstein's Creatures.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Focusing on the monstrous figures of nineteenth-century fiction, this course explores their cultural meaning for Victorians as well as ourselves, examining their ongoing fascination and purpose&#8212;their relation to changing conceptions of the marginal and "other" and to social norms and their violation. Students consider the tie between the monstrous or "unnatural" and the threat of class revolt, sexual "deviance," and imperial rise and fall. Readings include <span class="em">Frankenstein, Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde, Dracula,</span> and <span class="em">The War of the Worlds</span>, as well as contemporary revisions of these works in novels and films. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. L. Nayder.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121L"/><a name="ENG121L"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 121L. Modern Short Stories.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the short story and novella as characteristic twentieth-century genres, with a brief introduction to works in the ninteenth century. The course focuses on both "classic" and contemporary texts by writers selected from among Thomas Hardy, Henry James, Joseph Conrad, W. Somerset Maugham, James Joyce, D.H. Lawrence, Katherine Mansfield, Doris Lessing, David Lodge, Bernard Malamud, Susan Sontag, Susan Minot, and David Leavitt. Students also have the opportunity to experiment with writing a short story. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. L. Shankar.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121P"/><a name="ENG121P"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 121P. The Love Lyric and Society.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Poetry has been used to express love throughout the ages. But is love a form of ideology? Could love poems sustain traditional power relations? This course examines love sonnets written in the age of Shakespeare from two points of view: the celebration of individualistic expression and aesthetic brilliance central to formalism, and the analysis of lyric and society important to historical approaches. Writers include William Shakespeare, Mary Wroth, Louise Lab&#233;, John Donne, and Thomas Wyatt.  Not open to students who have received credit for First-Year Seminar 285. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. C. Malcolmson.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121T"/><a name="ENG121T"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 121T. Apprenticeship and Creative Mastery.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the early and late works of four American artists. Students examine how the achieved artistry of their mature work evolved out of the "coming of age" struggles reflected in their early work. They read the poetry of Robert Frost, the fiction of Edith Wharton and F. Scott Fitzgerald, and they view the early and late films of director John Huston.  Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. L. Turlish.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121W"/><a name="ENG121W"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 121W. Reading Lyric Poetry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to lyric poetry written in the last two centuries, and in varied cultural settings, from the "canonical" English and American classics to the contemporary, multicultural, and transnational. Poets studied may include Meena Alexander, Robert Browning, T. S. Eliot, Joy Harjo, Garrett Hongo, Audre Lorde, John Keats, Percy Shelley, Cathy Song, Wallace Stevens, Rabindranath Tagore, Alfred Tennyson, William Wordsworth, W. B. Yeats, and others. The focus is on "close reading" with some attention to the poets' varied historical and sociocultural contexts. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall 2005.</span> Not open to students who have received credit for First-Year Seminar 323. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. L. Shankar.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121X"/><a name="AA/EN121X"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/EN 121X. Music and Metaphor: The Sounds in African American Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">While African American musical traditions command attention on stages across the world, they have a unique home in African American literature. This course explores folk, sacred, blues, jazz, and hip hop music as aesthetic and sociopolitical resources for African American authors. Course texts may include poetry, drama, fiction, criticism, and theory. Authors include Sterling Plumpp, Toni Morrison, Jayne Cortez, Albert Murray, W. E. B. Du Bois, Zora Neale Hurston, Larry Neal, and Ralph Ellison. Not open to students who have received credit for African American Studies 121X, English 121X, or First-Year Seminar 287. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. K. Ruffin.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121Y"/><a name="ENG121Y"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 121Y. Stories, Plots, Poems.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Reading a broad variety of poetry, as well as selected examples of prose fiction, students engage in a series of questions about the difference between poems that tell stories in a conventional sense and those that do not. Poets include Wordsworth, Rossetti, Frost, and Rich among others. The colloquium seeks to foster an understanding of the pleasure and power of poetry through thinking and writing about poetry aloud, and writing poetry.  Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. C. Taylor.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="141"/><a name="ENG141"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 141. American Writers to 1900.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of ten to twelve American texts selected from the works of such writers as Bradford, Mather, Bradstreet, Edwards, Franklin, Cooper, Hawthorne, Fuller, Emerson, Thoreau, Jacobs, Melville, Douglas, Stowe, Wilson, Whitman, and Poe.   Enrollment limited to 25 per section. Normally offered every year. L. Turlish, C. Taylor.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="152"/><a name="ENG152"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 152. American Writers since 1900.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of ten to twelve American texts selected from the works of such writers as Dickinson, Twain, Gilman, Chesnutt, James, Adams, Dreiser, Hughes, Frost, Stein, Hemingway, Larsen, Fitzgerald, Faulkner, Pound, Eliot, Crane, Cullen, Wright, Stevens, Williams, Baldwin, Plath, Albee, Brooks, Walker, Ellison, Pynchon, and Morrison.   Enrollment limited to 25 per section. Normally offered every year. C. Taylor, L. Turlish.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="171"/><a name="ENG171"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 171. European Literature: European Tradition from Homer to Cervantes.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of major texts of European literature, read in English, with attention to their importance as both works of art and documents of cultural history. Texts include works by Homer, the Greek tragedians, Plato, Sappho, Virgil, Dante, Rabelais, Montaigne, Cervantes, and others.   Enrollment limited to 25 per section. Normally offered every year. S. Dillon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="201"/><a name="EN/ES201"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/ES 201. African and Diasporic Ecological Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">While it has always been part of global culure and politics, Africa is now recognized as a continent of import in a most necessary global conversation about ecological change. This course examines ecological influences on literature by Anglophone authors of African descent. The study of the aesthetic and cultural imprint of individual authors is informed by readings that detail broader issues affecting ecological perceptions in human groups. Students also examine interpretations of human biodiversity that have contributed to the neglect of African and African diasporic artistic and philosophic perspectives on ecological issues. Recommended background: course(s) in African American studies and/or environmental studies. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every year. K. Ruffin.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="206"/><a name="ENG206"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 206. Chaucer.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Reading and interpretation of <span class="em">The Canterbury Tales,</span> the greatest work of the fourteenth-century Middle-English poet. All works are read in Middle English.  Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Enrollment limited to 25. (Pre-1800.) Normally offered every year. A. Thompson.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="211"/><a name="ENG211"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 211. English Literary Renaissance (1509-1603).</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the Elizabethan Age through developments in literature, particularly the sonnet (William Shakespeare, Louise Lab&#233;, Philip Sidney, Mary Wroth) and Spenser's romance epic <span class="em">Faerie Queene</span>, studied in relation to medieval romances by Chr&#233;tien de Troyes and Marie de France.  Attention is given to developments in religion, politics, and society. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Enrollment limited to 25. (Pre-1800.) Offered with varying frequency. C. Malcolmson.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="212"/><a name="AA/EN212"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/EN 212. Black Lesbian and Gay Literatures.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines black lesbian and gay literatures in English from Africa, the Caribbean, the United Kingdom, the United States, and Canada. Students are introduced to critical and historical approaches for analyzing literature about black queer sensibilities.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. C. Nero.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="213"/><a name="ENG213"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 213. Shakespeare.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the major plays, with some emphasis on the biography of Shakespeare and the Elizabethan milieu. Students planning to take both English 213 and 214 are advised to take 213 first. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Enrollment limited to 25 per section. (Pre-1800.) Normally offered every year. C. Malcolmson, S. Freedman.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="213-214"/><a name="ENG213-214"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 213-214. Shakespeare.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the major plays, with some emphasis on the biography of Shakespeare and the Elizabethan milieu. Students planning to take both English 213 and 214 are advised to take 213 first. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Enrollment limited to 25 per section. (Pre-1800.) Normally offered every year. C. Malcolmson, S. Freedman.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="214"/><a name="ENG214"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 214. Shakespeare.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the major plays, with some emphasis on the biography of Shakespeare and the Elizabethan milieu. Students planning to take both English 213 and 214 are advised to take 213 first. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Enrollment limited to 25 per section. (Pre-1800.) Offered with varying frequency. S. Freedman.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="216"/><a name="ENG216"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 216. <span class="em">The Waste Land</span> and After.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the backgrounds, themes, and techniques of T. S. Eliot's <span class="em">The Waste Land</span> in terms of its influence upon subsequent American poetry and prose fiction. Primary readings include texts by Hart Crane, William Faulkner, John Berryman, and Bernard Malamud. Secondary readings and student presentations focus on background texts by such writers as Sir James Frazer, Jessie Weston, and Hermann Hesse. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. L. Turlish.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="220"/><a name="ENG220"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 220. Dickens Revised.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Focusing on several works that span Dickens's career, students place Dickens in his Victorian context and consider how and why his fiction has been adapted and reworked in the twentieth century. Students discuss film and musical adaptations as well as fictional reworkings, and examine changes in Dickens's reputation and the evolving cultural meaning of his stories. Novels, films, and musicals include <span class="em">Oliver!, Jack Maggs, The D. Case,</span> and <span class="em">The Mystery of Edwin Drood: The Solve-It-Yourself Broadway Musical</span>. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. L. Nayder.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="221"/><a name="ENG221"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 221. Dickens and Victorian Culture.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Reading Dickens's work as a novelist and journalist in the context of Victorian politics and culture, students consider his reputation as a social reformer and a disciplinarian as well as a literary genius, and focus on his varying representations of class conflict, criminality, and gender relations. Works include <span class="em">Sketches by Boz, Oliver Twist, Bleak House, Great Expectations,</span> and <span class="em">Our Mutual Friend</span>, in addition to critical and biographical studies. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Enrollment limited to 40. Offered with varying frequency. L. Nayder.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="222"/><a name="ENG222"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 222. Seventeenth-Century Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of significant writers of the seventeenth century. Writers may include William Shakespeare, John Donne, George Herbert, Aemilia Lanyer, John Milton, and Aphra Behn. Attention is given to the intellectual, political, and scientific revolutions of the age. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Enrollment limited to 25. (Pre-1800.) Offered with varying frequency. C. Malcolmson.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="223"/><a name="AA/EN223"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/EN 223. Survey of Literature of the Caribbean.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the literatures of the African diaspora in the Caribbean and the Caribbean diaspora in Canada, the United States, Great Britain, and France. Some texts are drawn from Anglophone authors such as Lamming, Anthony, Walcott, Brodber, Danticat, Lovelace, Brathwaite, and Denis Williams; others, from Francophone and Hispanophone writers, including Guillen, Carpentier, Cond&#233;, Chamoiseau, Depestre, Ferr&#233;, and Morej&#243;n. The course places each work in its historical, political, and anthropological contexts. Students are introduced to a number of critical theories and methodologies with which to analyze the works, including poststructuralist, Marxist, pan-African, postcolonial, and feminist. Prerequisite(s): one of the following: African American Studies 140, 162, 212, African American Studies/English 121X, Anthropology 155, 228, 234, 251, English 250, 292, 294 or 295. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2006.</span> Normally offered every other year. S. Houchins.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="226"/><a name="ENG226"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 226. Milton's <span class="em">Paradise Lost</span>.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Milton's Christian epic, <span class="em">Paradise Lost</span> (1668), which retells the story of man's fall from Paradise, is one of the most influential and interesting works in English literature. Students read this poem twice: once before midterm, with attention to internal form and structure, and then again afterwards, focusing on significant problems from the history of Milton criticism, and on the remarkable influence of Milton's poem in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. Enrollment limited to 25. (Pre-1800.) Offered with varying frequency. S. Dillon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="228"/><a name="ENG228"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 228. Narrative: Fact, Fun, and Fiction.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Narrative, like power after Foucault, has become a hot commodity. Institutions traditionally perceived as dealing with "the facts" are consciously using narrative and story as tools, now that attention has been drawn to ways in which they have always used them unconsciously. Meanwhile, the institution of fiction toys self-consciously with the accoutrements of fact and makes meta-statements about ontological status. In the context of our constructivist age, the course examines the hybrid nature of narrative posturings. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course and any one course from the following departments/programs: African American studies, philosophy, psychology, or sociology.  Enrollment limited to 25. D. Freedman.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="232"/><a name="ENG232"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 232. Eighteenth-Century Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of Restoration and eighteenth-century British authors, including Dryden, Congreve, Swift, Pope, Fielding, and Johnson. Attention is given to parallel developments in Continental literature and to continuity with Renaissance humanism.  Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  (Pre-1800.) Offered with varying frequency. S. Freedman.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="236"/><a name="INDS236"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 236. The Literatures of Women of the African Diaspora.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses primarily on the literatures of black women from Africa, the Caribbean, the United Kingdom, and Canada, but may examine some works from the United States. All of the texts are in English; some are from the Anglophone diaspora and others are translations from the Lusophone, Hispanophone, and Francophone black world. Students are introduced to historical, feminist, Pan-African, Marxist, and postcolonial critical approaches to analyze this richly diverse yet culturally and politically related body of work. Topics include slavery and migrations, the socioeconomic contexts of prolonged exile from the African continent, liberation struggles on the continent and in the diaspora, as well as the roles of women in these movements. Recommended background: any of the following: African American Studies 140A, African American Studies/Women and Gender Studies 201, African American Studies/Anthropology 251, African American Studies/English 253, Anthropology 228, or Political Science 235. Cross-listed in African American studies, English, and women and gender studies. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every year. S. Houchins.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="238"/><a name="ENG238"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 238. Jane Austen: Then and Now.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students read Austen's six major works, investigate their relation to nineteenth-century history and culture, and consider the Austen revival in film adaptations and fictional continuations of her novels. The course highlights the various and conflicting ways in which critics represent Austen, and the cultural needs her stories now seem to fulfill. Readings include <span class="em">Sense and Sensibility, Pride and Prejudice, Mansfield Park, Emma, Northanger Abbey,</span> and <span class="em">Persuasion</span>. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. L. Nayder.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="241"/><a name="ENG241"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 241. Fiction in the United States.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Critical readings of representative works by American writers such as Hawthorne, Twain, Howells, James, Crane, Norris, Chopin, Hurston, Dreiser, Dos Passos, Le Sueur, Fitzgerald, Stein, Faulkner, Cather, Steinbeck, Wright, Warren, Baldwin, and Welty. Discussions of individual novels examine their form within the context of the major directions of American fiction.  Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Enrollment limited to 25 per section. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="243"/><a name="ENG243"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 243. Romantic Literature (1790-1840).</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The theoretical foundations of English and European Romanticism, including its philosophical, critical, and social backgrounds. The course concentrates on Rousseau, Blake, Coleridge, Wordsworth, Byron, Shelley, and Keats. Attention is also given to Lamb, Hazlitt, De Quincey, Swedenborg, and other prose figures and critics of the period. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Enrollment limited to 25 per section. Offered with varying frequency. R. Farnsworth, S. Dillon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="245"/><a name="ENG245"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 245. Studies in Victorian Literature (1830-1900).</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Selected topics in the period, organized by author, genre, and historical connections. Special attention is given to philosophical backgrounds and the critical language of the day. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Enrollment limited to 25 per section. Offered with varying frequency. S. Dillon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="253"/><a name="AA/EN253"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/EN 253. The African American Novel.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An examination of the African American novel from its beginnings in the mid-1800s to the present. Issues addressed include a consideration of folk influences on the genre, its roots in the slave narrative tradition, its relation to Euro-American texts and culture, and the "difference" that gender as well as race makes in determining narrative form. Readings include narratives selected from among the works of such writers as Douglass, Jacobs, Wilson, Delany, Hopkins, Harper, Chesnutt, Johnson, Toomer, Larsen, Hurston, Wright, Petry, Ellison, Baldwin, Walker, Morrison, Marshall, Reed, and others. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Not open to students who have received credit for English 250. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. K. Ruffin.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="254"/><a name="ENG254"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 254. Modern British Literature since 1900.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to the birth of modern British literature and its roots, with attention to its social and cultural history, its philosophical and cultural foundations, and some emphasis on its relationship to the previous century. Texts are selected from the works of writers such as Forster, Lawrence, Joyce, Woolf, Mansfield, Eliot, Yeats, Orwell, Rushdie, and Lessing. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. L. Shankar.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="260"/><a name="ENG260"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 260. Literature of South Asia.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces fiction, poetry, and films by writers who are of South Asian descent, or who have considered the Indian subcontinent their home. Topics include British influence on South Asia, the partition of India, national identity formation, women's social roles, the impact of Western education and the English language, and the emergence of a new generation of postcolonial literary artists. Writers are selected from among Salman Rushdie, Arundhati Roy, Anita Desai, Ruth Prawer Jhabvala, Satyajit Ray, Rabindranath Tagore, Sarojini Naidu, Jhumpa Lahiri, Mahasweta Debi, U. R. Anantha Murthy, Amitav Ghosh, Ved Mehta, and Ismat Chugtai. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. L. Shankar.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="264"/><a name="ENG264"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 264. Modern Irish Poetry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the development and transformation of Anglo-Irish poetry in the twentieth century, especially as it responds to the political, social, and gender forces at work in Ireland's recent history. Beginning with brief but concentrated study of poems by W. B. Yeats and Patrick Kavanagh, the course then examines the work of inheritors of these major figures' legacies, including Seamus Heaney, Derek Mahon, Thomas Kinsella, Eavan Boland, Eamon Grennan, Paul Muldoon, and Medbh McGuckian. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. R. Farnsworth.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="268"/><a name="AA/EN268"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/EN 268. Survey of Literatures of Africa.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores folklore, myths, and literary texts of the African continent. These include works written by Anglophone authors such as Achebe,
Soyinka, Ngugi, Vera, Njau, Nwapa, and Head; those drawn from oral traditions of indigenous languages transcribed into English, such as <span class="cite">The Mwindo Epic</span> and <span class="cite">The Sundiata</span>; and those written by Lusophone and Francophone authors including B&#226;, Senghor, Liking, Neto, Mahfouz, and Kafunkeno. The course contextualizes each work historically, politically, and anthropologically. Students are introduced to a number of critical theories and methodologies with which to analyze the works, such as poststructural, Marxist, Pan-African, postcolonial, and feminist. Prerequisite(s): one of the following: African American Studies 140A, African American Studies/English 212X, 212, African American Studies/Rhetoric 162, Anthropology 155, 228, English 250, 292, 294, or 295. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2005.</span> Normally offered every other year. S. Houchins.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="275"/><a name="ENG275"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 275. English Novel.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the English novel from its origins to the early nineteenth century. Readings include selections from Homer's <span class="em">Iliad</span>, and novels by Defoe, Richardson, Fielding, Radcliffe, Austen, and Scott. Among the issues addressed by this course are the relation of the novel to the epic, and the social and political orientation of this new genre. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Enrollment limited to 25. (Pre-1800.) Offered with varying frequency. L. Nayder.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="291"/><a name="ENG291"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 291. Prose Writing.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A course for students who wish to have practice and guidance in the writing of prose. The course may alternate between fiction and nonfiction. Admission by writing sample. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. C. Taylor.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="292"/><a name="ENG292"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 292. Poetry Writing.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A course for students who wish to have practice and guidance in the writing of poetry. Admission by writing sample. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. S. Dillon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="294"/><a name="ENG294"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 294. Storytelling.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces cross-cultural forms, contexts, and strategies of storytelling in the process of analyzing the role of stories in everyday life. Primary readings include a range of stories characteristic of diverse traditions. Recommended background: introductory courses in literature, anthropology, or the sociology of knowledge. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25 per section. Offered with varying frequency. C. Taylor.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="295"/><a name="ENG295"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 295. Critical Theory.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Major literary critics are read, and major literary works are studied in the light of these critics. Critical approaches discussed may include neoclassical, Romantic, psychoanalytical, formalist, generic, archetypal, structuralist, and deconstructionist. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Enrollment limited to 25. (Critical thinking.) Normally offered every year. S. Freedman.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="297"/><a name="EN/WS297"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/WS 297. Feminisms.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course develops students' ability to analyze gender in relation to other issues, including race, class, and sexuality. Students explore the multiple theories of how these issues intersect in literature, including black feminism, socialist feminism, queer theory, deconstruction, and psychoanalytic theory. Some attention is paid to media feminism, both the brand of feminism popular in current movies and television shows, and media reactions to feminism. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Not open to students who have received credit for English 395L or Women's Studies 395L. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. C. Malcolmson.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="325"/><a name="INDS325"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 325. Black Feminist Literary Theory and Practice.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar examines literary theories that address the representation and construction of race, gender, and sexuality, particularly, but not exclusively, theories formulated and articulated by Afra-diasporic women such as Spillers, Ogunyemi, Henderson, Valerie Smith, McDowell, Busia, Lubiano, and Davies. Students not only analyze theoretical essays, but they use the theories as lenses through which to explore literary productions of women writers of Africa and the African diaspora in Europe and in the Americas, including Philip, Dangarembga, Morrison, Herron, Gayle Jones, Head, Cond&#233;, Brodber, Brand, Merle Collins, and Harriet Wilson. Prerequisite(s): African American Studies 140, 235, African American Studies/English 121X, 212, African American Studies/Women and Gender Studies 201, English 250, 294, 295, English/Women and Gender Studies 121G. Cross-listed in African American studies, English, and women and gender studies. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every other year. S. Houchins.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="ENG360"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365"/><a name="ENG365"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 365. Special Topics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Offered occasionally by a faculty member in subjects of special interest. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="391"/><a name="ENG391"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 391. Advanced Prose Writing.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Prerequisite(s): English 291.  Enrollment limited to 12. Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. R. Farnsworth.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="392"/><a name="ENG392"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 392. Advanced Poetry Writing.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Prerequisite(s): English 292.  Enrollment limited to 12. Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. R. Farnsworth.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395"/><a name="ENG395"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395. Junior-Senior Seminars.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Seminars provide an opportunity for concentrated work in a restricted subject area. Two such seminars are required for the English major. Students are encouraged to see the seminar as preparation for independent work on a senior thesis. They may also choose to use the seminar itself as a means of fulfilling the senior thesis requirement. Sections are limited to 15.  Instructor permission is required.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395A"/><a name="ENG395A"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395A. Godard and European Film.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Jean-Luc Godard is perhaps the most important filmmaker of the second half of the twentieth century. His films are essays in what images can do; they analyze narrative, structure, and sound. This course considers the major films of his career, from romantic early works like <span class="em">Breathless</span> (1959), to politically severe films like <span class="em">Weekend</span> (1967), to the philosophical meditation of <span class="em">In Praise of Love</span> (2001). Each week course participants study one film by directors such as Antonioni, Bergman, Dreyer, Fellini, Marker, Pasolini, Tarkovsky, and Truffaut. Taken together, Godard and these European directors show why twentieth-century film is truly the "the seventh art." Prerequisite(s): one English course. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Critical thinking.) S. Dillon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395B"/><a name="ENG395B"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395B. Dissenting Traditions in Twentieth-Century American Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar examines literature by or about those who have felt themselves outside the mainstream of American culture. Focusing on issues concerning poverty, class, race, ethnicity, gender, and sexuality, it places close reading in the context of cultural history and theory. Works include texts by such writers as Anaya, Baldwin, Erdrich, Hurston, Kingston, Naylor, Morrison, Pinzer, Roth, Silko, and Steinbeck. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. C. Taylor.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395C"/><a name="ENG395C"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395C. Frost, Williams, and Stevens.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">As inheritors of Emersonian slants on poetics and imagination, Robert Frost, Wallace Stevens, and William Carlos Williams constitute a solid American grain of modernism in poetry. Thorough reading of their work reveals their surprising affinities and differences. How dark a vision of life (social and existential) does each seem to have? What roles do wit, irony, verbal extravagance, and inherited poetic forms play in the work? What does each take to be the function of poetry in modern American life? The work of tutelary ancestors, competitors, and critics complements the substance of the course: comprehensive reading, writing, and discussion of these poets' poems and theoretical prose. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. R. Farnsworth.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395D"/><a name="ENG395D"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395D. Victorian Crime Fiction.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The seminar examines the detective fiction written by British Victorians, the historical context in which this literature was produced, and its ideological implications. Students consider the connection between gender and criminality, and the relation of detection to class unrest and empire-building. Readings include works by Charles Dickens, Mary Elizabeth Braddon, Wilkie Collins, Arthur Conan Doyle, and Grant Allen. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. L. Nayder.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395E"/><a name="CM/EN395E"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN 395E. Medieval Romance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Romance was the most popular literary genre of the later Middle Ages. Originating in France in the twelfth century, this highly adaptable form quickly became an international phenomenon, with numerous examples found across Europe and the British Isles. Many romances tell tales of amorous exploits, exotic travels, and quests for knowledge; the celebration of chivalric ideals is a central theme. But many of these tales seem to question and sometimes undermine the very ideals they otherwise espouse: courtly love mingles with sexual adventurism, for instance, and loyalty to one's lord often results in alienation or death. Students read a selection of romances from France and Britain (all texts are in modern English translation or manageable Middle English) with an eye toward how they variously articulate and deconstruct the notion of chivalry. Prerequisite(s): one English course. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. S. Federico.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395E"/><a name="EN/WS395E"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/WS 395E. Mary Elizabeth Braddon.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Known among Victorians as the "Queen of the Circulating Libraries," Mary Elizabeth Braddon (1835-1915) was immensely popular in her day. Reading a selection of Braddon's best- and lesser-known works, students explore the reasons for her popularity. They consider the subversive and conservative strains in Braddon's writing, her aims and accomplishments as a "sensation novelist," and the significance of her own unconventional lifestyle. Readings include a number of Braddon's novels, short stories, and plays, as well as biographical and critical studies.  Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. L. Nayder.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395F"/><a name="ENG395F"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395F. To Light: Five Twentieth-Century American Women Poets.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Concentrated study of the poetry (and some prose) of five major American poets:  Elizabeth Bishop, Gwendolyn Brooks, Sylvia Plath, Adrienne Rich, and Marianne Moore, whose various poetic stances and careers illuminate particular dilemmas facing female poets at mid-century&#8212;issues of subject matter, visibility, literary tradition, and ideology. Corollary readings may be drawn from the work of other poets, including Anne Sexton and Denise Levertov. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. R. Farnsworth.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395G"/><a name="ENG395G"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395G. Literature and Cultural Critique.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar uses theoretical ideas about cultural difference and power to inform the practical criticism of chosen texts, including Bessie Head's <span class="em">A Question of Power</span>, Gloria Anzaldua's <span class="em">Borderlands/La Frontera</span>, William Faulkner's <span class="em">Absalom, Absalom!</span>, Toni Morrison's <span class="em">Beloved</span>, Klamath's <span class="em">Oral Narratives</span>, and a performance of popular culture chosen by students. This course interrogates both the authority of "good" readers and the capacity of literature to surprise us with kinds of knowledge not included in our starting conceptions of the literary. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Critical thinking.) C. Taylor.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395H"/><a name="ENG395H"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395H. Codes of Love.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Roland Barthes states in <span class="cite">S/Z</span> that we always love according to code, be it romantic, chivalric, collegiate or other. Plato has one of the speakers in the <span class="cite">Symposium</span> say that the Athenians are <span class="em">"anomos"</span> (code-less) when it comes to love. Love is unique, private, excruciating and un-repeatable, while at once the opposite of those descriptions. Using Barthes' text, <span class="cite">A Lover's Discourse</span>, and Plato's <span class="cite">Symposium</span> as theoretical hooks, the course examines how representations of love cohere into recognizable forms and content; and how these operate and change with history and culture. Recommended background: course work in classics, psychology, or sociology. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2005.</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. D. Freedman.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395J"/><a name="ENG395J"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395J. The Gothic Tradition.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar traces the Gothic tradition from its European origins in the mid-eighteenth century to its current use by African American writers, and considers the subgenre from various critical perspectives.  Particular emphasis is placed on the politics of the Gothic: on its relation to revolutionary movements, on its representations of intimacy and violence, and on the ways in which Gothic novelists both defend and subvert prevailing conceptions of sexual and racial difference.  Writers studied include Horace Walpole, Matthew Lewis, Ann Radcliffe, Mary Shelley, Charlotte Bront&#235;, Wilkie Collins, Harriet Jacobs, and Gloria Naylor. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. L. Nayder.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395L"/><a name="EN/WS395L"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/WS 395L. Feminist Literary Criticism.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar examines feminist literary theories and the implications and consequences of theoretical choices. It raises interrelated questions about forms of representation, the social construction of critical categories, cross-cultural differences among writers and readers, and the critical reception of women writers. Students explore the use of literary theory through work with diverse texts. Not open to students who have received credit for English 395L or Women's Studies 400B. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Critical thinking.) Normally offered every year. L. Shankar, C. Malcolmson, C. Taylor.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395N"/><a name="ENG395N"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395N. Joyce's <span class="em">Ulysses</span>.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of James Joyce's novel as both a mimetic and self-reflexive fiction. Emphasis is given to the biographical and social contexts of the novel. Students consider the influence of such figures as Ibsen, Flaubert, and Krafft-Ebing on the novel. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. Recommended background: English 254 or 264. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. L. Turlish.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395O"/><a name="ENG395O"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395O. Poetry and Place.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Premised on William Carlos Williams's definition of culture as the relation of a place to the lives lived within it, this course begins with a brief exploration of Western conceptions of the pastoral, then focuses on nineteenth- and twentieth-century visions of nature's relation to the poetic imagination, where nature is understood to include ideas of wilderness, cultivated landscape, and even urban space. Psychological, political, philosophical, and prophetic preoccupations come to startling focus in poetries specifically responsive to the earth and locale. From several traditions a number of poets is considered from among Virgil, Horace, Marvell, Bash&#244;, Wordsworth, Emerson, Whitman, Dickinson, Baudelaire, Hardy, Frost, E. Thomas, W. C. Williams, Jeffers, Neruda, Kavanagh, Bishop, Snyder, Heaney, Momaday, Ammons, Berry, Walcott, Oliver, and Haines. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. R. Farnsworth.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395P"/><a name="ENG395P"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395P. Pre-1800 Women Writers.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The seminar considers the conditions that obstructed and supported writing by British women from the Middle Ages to the eighteenth century. Topics include changing accounts of gender difference, the possibility of a self-conscious female tradition, elite versus non-elite genres, and the emergence of the professional woman writer. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Pre-1800.) Offered with varying frequency. C. Malcolmson.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395Q"/><a name="CM/EN395Q"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN 395Q. Images of Sainthood in Medieval English Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The saints of the Christian church were not only central to the belief system of the European Middle Ages, they also provided an opportunity for rich and varied narrative and cultural constructions. The saints' legends found in the medieval English collection that is the focus of this course sometimes reveal more about the hopes and fears of the people by and for whom they were composed than about the saints themselves, but they are no less interesting for that reason. Translation of a chosen text, historical investigation, and creative rewriting all play a part in the process of acquainting students with the nature of narrative and the continuing hold the saints have upon our imagination. Prerequisite(s): English 206. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Pre-1800.) Offered with varying frequency. A. Thompson.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395Q"/><a name="EN/ES395Q"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/ES 395Q. Nature and Culture in European Art Film.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">European art film tends to be more realistic than Hollywood film, yet at the same time it is more conscious of its artifice. What does nature look like when framed in these art-conscious, self-reflexive terms? This course considers challenging masterworks of European cinema from the 1950s until today, with special attention to the place of nature in cinematic narrative and representation. Students watch two films each week and read several theoretical essays. Directors may include Ingmar Bergman, Andrei Tarkovsky, Jean-Luc Godard, Roberto Rossellini, and Claire Denis. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2006</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. S. Dillon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395S"/><a name="EN/WS395S"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/WS 395S. Asian American Women Writers, Filmmakers, and Critics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar studies from a literary and a sociohistorical perspective the fiction, memoirs, and critical theories of Asian American women such as Meena Alexander, Rey Chow, Chitra Banerjee Divakaruni, Ginu Kamani, Maxine Hong Kingston, Lisa Lowe, Bapsi Sidhwa, Cathy Song, Shani Mootoo, Jhumpa Lahiri, Joy Kogawa, and Hisaye Yamamoto. It explores their constructions of personal and national identity, as hybridized Asians and Americans, and as postcolonial diasporics making textual representations of real and "imaginary" homelands. Films by Trinh Minh-ha, Indu Krishnan, Deepa Mehta, Mira Nair, Jayasri Hart, and Renee Tajima are also analyzed through critical lenses. Not open to students who have received credit for English 395s. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Critical thinking.) Offered with varying frequency. L. Shankar.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395T"/><a name="ENG395T"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395T. The Delight of Comedy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">By the study and discussion of a range of examples, this course seeks to identify the delight of comedy and the profundity of the satisfaction, joy, and fulfillment it is capable of giving. Attention is given to, among other things, exactly what it is that is going on in comedy's use of surprise, shock, and bewilderment. The main examples are taken from poetry and drama: Chaucer's <span class="cite">The House of Fame</span> and <span class="cite">Wife of Bath's Tale</span>, Shakespeare's <span class="cite">The Taming of the Shrew</span> and <span class="cite">A Midsummer Night's Dream</span>, passages of Swift, Pope's <span class="cite">The Rape of the Lock</span>, extracts from novels by Dickens, and poems by Gwendolyn Brooks and Kenneth Koch. The course may also consider examples not originally written in English and not necessarily works of literature, such as Plato's <span class="cite">Symposium</span>, Rabelais' <span class="cite">Pantagruel</span>, Mozart's and Da Ponte's <span class="cite">Cosi fan tutte</span> and Fellini's <span class="cite">8 1/2</span>. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2005.</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. J. Newton.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395U"/><a name="ENG395U"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395U. Postmodern Novel.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The seminar examines diverse efforts to define "postmodernism." Students read novels by Joyce, Pynchon, Wallace, Eco, and Rushdie. Contemporary reviews, secondary criticism, narrative theory, issues of socially constructed reality, and some problems in the philosophy of language mark out its concerns. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course.  Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. S. Freedman.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395X"/><a name="ENG395X"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395X. "Pretty and Apt": Philosophical Method and the Study of Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Ancient Greek philosophers, in their efforts to explain their world, drew readily from literature. The same has not been the case for the most influential philosophers in the Anglo-American tradition. Literary commentary appears stinted in Wittgenstein's writings, hardly flourishes in Davidson, Putnam, Goodman, and Rorty. When we investigate European voices, such as Heidegger, Foucault, and Derrida, do we come away thinking differently about the fit between philosophy and literature? How does philosophical method apply to literature? Do varying accounts of metaphor, reference, or truth concern literary explanation? Concepts, such as Gricean maxims, Davidsonian intention, Cavellian presence, and Derridean markers form a ground to judge their aptness in reading literature. We, then, seek answers to Moth's query in <span class="cite">Love's Labors Lost</span>, "I pretty, and my saying apt? Or I apt, and my saying pretty?" Recommended background: Philosophy 234 and Philosophy 241 and English 295. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Winter 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. S. Freedman.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395Y"/><a name="ENG395Y"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 395Y. Colonialism and Literature in Early Modern England.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course considers the simultaneous development of "high" literature during the age of Shakespeare and colonial settlement in Ireland and the Americas, as well as British trade and exploration in Africa and Asia. Particular attention is paid to early versions of "race," the role of gender in representing "New World" encounters, and the relationship between travel narratives and scientific discourse. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English class.  Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Pre-1800.) Offered with varying frequency. C. Malcolmson.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395Z"/><a name="AA/EN395Z"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/EN 395Z. African American Literature and the Bible.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Bible is unmatched in its influence on African American literary and cultural traditions. No other book has inspired such a broad scope of oral and written work. From explorations of the Exodus narrative to the Gospel writers' parables of Jesus, this course examines the way Hebrew and Christian biblical texts have inspired African American artists. Beginning with oral traditions such as spirituals and sermons, students then consider the Bible's role in scribal literacy and political discourse, and conclude with its impact on contemporary writers. Students combine interpretation of biblical texts and course readings with literary/cultural theory and criticism. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English or African American studies course.  Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. K. Ruffin.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="ENG457"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students register for English 457 in the fall semester and for English 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both English 457 and 458.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457, 458"/><a name="ENG457, 458"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 457, 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students register for English 457 in the fall semester and for English 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both English 457 and 458.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="ENG458"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students register for English 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both English 457 and 458.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s10"/><a name="AV/ENs10"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/EN s10. A Cultural and Literary Walk into China.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This unit has two goals: 1) to offer an introduction to Chinese aesthetics through architecture, the fine arts, the performing arts, and literature; 2) to study how Buddhist aesthetic ideas expressed in rock-cut temples, monasteries, and garden design often reappear in altered ways in poems, plays, and epics. Students travel to seven historically important cities in China: Beijing, Datong, Luoyang, Xian, Shanghai, Hangzhou, and Suzhou. Recommended background: Art and Visual Culture 243, any course in Chinese language and literature, Asian Studies/Religion 208 and 309. Not open to students who have received credit for Art s10 or English s10. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 20. Offered with varying frequency. T. Nguyen, S. Freedman.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s20"/><a name="ENGs20"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG s20. NewsWatch.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">What criteria determine that some aspects of experience are regarded as newsworthy and others not? What conventions determine how to represent this news? What are the boundaries between journalism and other nonfictional narratives (history, essay, documentary, biography, for example)? What tensions exist between "all the news that's fit to print" and commercial, consumer-based media? This unit considers how diverse media collect, represent, and comment on the "news," drawing on media and cultural studies, discourse analysis, and narrative theory to critically explore both dominant media representations in the United States and alternatives to it, especially in foreign presses and/or alternatively supported media.  Offered with varying frequency. C. Malcolmson, C. Taylor.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s22"/><a name="CM/ENs22"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN s22. Reading Chaucer: A Brief Introduction to <span class="cite">The Canterbury Tales</span> in Middle English.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This unit focuses on learning to read late fourteenth-century Middle English in the dialect used by the most celebrated and influential poet of the medieval period, Geoffrey Chaucer, and on close study of the General Prologue and a small number of tales from <span class="cite">The Canterbury Tales</span>. Selections include The Wife of Bath's Prologue and Tale, one of the most frequently read and controversial Chaucerian texts. Students consider a few representative critical approaches to the contemporary problems The Wife poses, including questions of power, gender, and domestic violence. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2005.</span> E. Hansen.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s23"/><a name="ENGs23"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG s23. Beatniks and Mandarins: A Literary and Cultural History of the American Fifties.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An examination of established and adversarial culture in the American 1950s. Readings are in the literature and social commentary of such representative figures as Lionel Trilling, Norman Mailer, and Jack Kerouac. Some attention is given to film noir as the definitive Fifties cinematic style and to the phenomenon that wed the recitation of poetry to American jazz.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. L. Turlish.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s24"/><a name="ENGs24"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG s24. British New Wave Film.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Film followed culture in the 1960s, by rebelling against tradition and calling for new kinds of narrative and subject matter. The most famous "new wave" cinema developed in France, but British film also took a remarkable turn. Now films began to look more realistic than ever before, and working-class subjects were approached in unprecedented detail. Yet films also turned more surrealistic and fanciful, and some of these movies are as wild and enchanted as the contemporary music. Readings from 1960s culture supplement discussion of the films. Film directors may include Lindsay Anderson, Tony Richardson, John Schlesinger, Richard Lester, and Nicolas Roeg.  Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. S. Dillon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s25"/><a name="ENGs25"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG s25. Sociocultural Approaches to Children's Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This unit studies some of the "classics" in British and American literature written to educate and entertain children, including works by Lewis Carroll, Edward Lear, J. M. Barrie, Louisa May Alcott, R. L. Stevenson, A. A. Milne, E. B. White, Mildred Taylor, Robert McCloskey, Dr. Seuss, and Jean Fritz. By employing the tools of sociocultural and psychological analysis, students examine the formation of gendered, racial, cultural, and social class identities through childhood literary experiences. Some attention is given to film versions of children's stories. This course has a required service-learning component of work with elementary school children and teachers. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. L. Shankar.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s26"/><a name="EN/WSs26"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/WS s26. Felicia Skene.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This unit examines the life and writings of the largely forgotten Victorian novelist and social reformer, Felicia Skene (1821-1899). Students investigate Skene's life story and read a number of her works, including <span class="em">The Inheritance of Evil, Or, the Consequence of Marrying a Deceased Wife's Sister</span> (1849) and "Penitentiaries and Reformatories" (1865). Focusing on the novel <span class="em">Hidden Depths</span> (1866), students consider the subject of Victorian prostitution, its primary theme, and engage in the research necessary to produce a new edition of that work. Not open to students who have received credit for English s26 or Women's Studies s26. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. L. Nayder.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s27"/><a name="ENGs27"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG s27. Codes of Love.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Roland Barthes states in <span class="cite">S/Z</span> that we always love according to code&#8212;be it medieval chivalric, romantic, collegiate, or other. Plato has one of the speakers in the <span class="cite">Symposium</span> state that the Athenians are code-less when it comes to love. Using Barthes and Plato as opposable theoretical frameworks, this unit examines codes of love, consequences of their operation, and how they change. Prerequisite(s): one course in English. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every other year. D. Freedman.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s28"/><a name="ED/ENs28"/><h4 class="crsname">ED/EN s28. Children's Writing Workshop.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students read and discuss a wide range of literature for and by children as well as pertinent critical studies, and travel weekly to Dunn Elementary School in New Gloucester to work with third, fourth, and fifth graders on well-known poetry and fiction as well as the children's own creative writing. With help from the children, they produce a classroom magazine and organize a poetry/fiction reading. A thirty-hour field experience is required. Prerequisite(s): One course in either English or Education. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Short Term 2006</span> Enrollment limited to 12. Offered with varying frequency. L. Nayder.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s29"/><a name="CM/ENs29"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/EN s29. Tolkien's Middle Ages.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">J. R. R. Tolkien, in his double roles as popular writer and Oxford medievalist, taught countless numbers of readers to appreciate many of the central themes of medieval literature. These overarching themes&#8212;including the relationship between the natural and the supernatural spheres, the struggle between good and evil, and the morally ambivalent status of monsters and magicians&#8212;are largely found in early Celtic and Norse mythology. In this unit students analyze these myths in an attempt to better understand where Tolkien's <span class="cite">Hobbit</span> is coming from, and how the novelist adopted and adapted medieval material for his modern audience. All texts are read in modern English. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. S. Federico.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s29"/><a name="EN/RHs29"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/RH s29. Place, Word, Sound: New Orleans.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This unit offers an interdisciplinary and experiential approach to the study of New Orleans, the most African city in continental North America. The goal of the unit is to understand the impact of place on culture and aesthetic practices, learn how institutions represent New World and creole transformations of Africanity, and introduce students to historical and contemporary debates about African influences in the United States. Students examine cultural memory, questions of power, and definitions of cultural terrain as expressed in literature, art, music, and architecture. In addition to attending the seven-day Jazz and Heritage Festival, students visit various sites of literary, cultural, and historical significance to New Orleans. Recommended background: a course in African American studies offered in English, music, rhetoric, or African American studies.  Enrollment limited to 16. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. K. Ruffin, C. Nero.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s35"/><a name="ENGs35"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG s35. Constructing Catherine Dickens.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Combining literary and biographical study with archival research, this unit focuses on the neglected figure of Catherine Dickens, wife of the novelist, who was forced from her home in 1858 after twenty years of marriage and ten children. Reading conflicting accounts of Mrs. Dickens as well as her own unpublished letters and book (a cookbook), students examine her family life in the context of Victorian gender norms and marriage law, consider how and why she has been represented by critics and biographers, and construct their own portraits of her.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. L. Nayder.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s43"/><a name="ENGs43"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG s43. Shakespeare in the Theater.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of Shakespeare's plays in performance, intended to acquaint the student with problems that are created by actual stage production in the interpretation of the plays. Students see Shakespearean productions in various locations, including London and Stratford-on-Avon, England. Prerequisite(s): English 213 and 214. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="ENGs50"/><h4 class="crsname">ENG s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>

               