<div class="Course"><a name="107B"/><a name="CH/ES107B"/><h4 class="crsname">CH/ES 107B. Chemical Structure and Its Importance in the Environment.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Fundamentals of atomic and molecular structure are developed with particular attention to how they relate to substances of interest in the environment. Periodicity, bonding, states of matter, and intermolecular forces are covered. The laboratory (three hours per week) involves a semester-long group investigation of a topic of environmental significance. Not open to students who have received credit for Chemistry 107B or Environmental Studies 107B. Enrollment limited to 60 per section. Normally offered every year. T. Wenzel.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="108B"/><a name="CH/ES108B"/><h4 class="crsname">CH/ES 108B. Chemical Reactivity in Environmental Systems.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A continuation of Chemistry/Environmental Studies 107B. Major topics include thermodynamics, kinetics, equilibrium, acid/base chemistry, and electrochemistry. Biogeochemical cycles provide examples for course topics. The laboratory (three hours per week) analyzes the chemistry of marine environments. Prerequisite(s): Chemistry 107A or Chemistry/Environmental Studies 107B. Not open to students who have received credit for Chemistry 108B or Environmental Studies 108B. Enrollment limited to 60. Normally offered every year. R. Austin.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="200"/><a name="ENVR200"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 200. Imagining Open Spaces.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This interdisciplinary course explores the evolving practice of urban open space. Frederick Law Olmsted's contribution to the design of American urban parks, as well as their contested legacy in the Civil Rights era, form a core study, along with some introduction to urbanist theories of space. Discussion of bioregional and cultural contexts focuses on issues around reclaimed and constructed landscapes. Study of the literature of open spaces, and of the interventions of contemporary artists and composers, develops an "expanded field" of aesthetics. Students are asked to pursue a creative-critical project, involving onsite investigation, in spaces at once social and natural. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall 2006.</span> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. J. Skinner.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="201"/><a name="EN/ES201"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/ES 201. African and Diasporic Ecological Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">While it has always been part of global culure and politics, Africa is now recognized as a continent of import in a most necessary global conversation about ecological change. This course examines ecological influences on literature by Anglophone authors of African descent. The study of the aesthetic and cultural imprint of individual authors is informed by readings that detail broader issues affecting ecological perceptions in human groups. Students also examine interpretations of human biodiversity that have contributed to the neglect of African and African diasporic artistic and philosophic perspectives on ecological issues. Recommended background: course(s) in African American studies and/or environmental studies. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level English course. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every year. K. Ruffin.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="203"/><a name="ENVR203"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 203. Material and Energy Flow in Engineered and Natural Systems.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to central concepts in environmental science, the transport and transformation of matter and the generation of use of energy, through the study of specific cases. The laboratory links mathematical modeling of environmental systems to experimental activities. This course serves as the foundation for further study of environmental science at Bates College. Prerequisite(s): one science set: Biology 201 and one of the following: Biology 110, 120, 121, 124, 125, 168, First-Year Seminar 226 or any two of the biology 100-level courses listed above as long as one has a lab; or Chemistry 107A and 108A; or 107B and 108B; or any two geology 100-level courses which include Geology 103, 104 or Biology/Geology 112; or Physics 106, 107/s25 and 108. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every year. H. Ewing.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="204"/><a name="ENVR204"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 204. Environment and Society.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course provides an introduction to the ways in which people interact with the natural environment. It concentrates on two main issues: 1) How do people think about the relationship between the environment and society? 2) What are some key empirical issues in the environment-society relationship that illustrate the various ways of thinking about the environment? Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="205"/><a name="ENVR205"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 205. "Nature" in Human Culture.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course aims to introduce students to the dynamics between the natural environment and human culture. First, it seeks a theoretical framework for appreciating how cultural traditions screen human perceptions and hence grant human meaning to the natural world. Second, it studies selected interpretations of nature from the traditions of indigenous peoples, Asian cultures, and the Western experience. Third, the course considers the prospects for moving beyond inherited perspectives to fresh envisagements of the lands, the seas, and living creatures.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30 per section. Normally offered every year. C. Straub.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="208"/><a name="INDS208"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 208. Introduction to Medieval Archeology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Middle Ages were a time of major cultural changes that laid the groundwork for Northwest Europe's emergence as a global center of political and economic power in more recent centuries. However, many aspects of life in the period from 1000 to 1500 <span class="smcaps">C.E.</span> were unrecorded in contemporary documents and art, and archeology has become an important tool for recovering that information. This course introduces the interdisciplinary methods and the findings of archeological studies of topics including medieval urban and rural lifeways, health, commerce, religion, social hierarchy, warfare, and the effects of global climate change. Cross-listed in anthropology, classical and medieval studies, environmental studies, and history. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall 2005.</span> Open to first-year students. (Premodern.) G. Bigelow.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="211"/><a name="ES/HI211"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/HI 211. Environmental Perspectives on U.S. History.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the relationship between the North American environment and the development and expansion of the United States. Because Americans' efforts (both intentional and not) to define and shape the environment were rooted in their own struggles for power, environmental history offers an important perspective on the nation's social history. Specific topics include Europeans', Africans', and Indians' competing efforts to shape the colonial environment; the impact and changing understanding of disease; the relationship between industrial environments and political power; and the development of environmental movements. Recommended background: History 140, 141, or 142. Open to first-year students. Normally offered every other year. J. Hall.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="213"/><a name="ENVR213"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 213. Reading the Watershed: Nature and Place in Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Environmental thinkers from Gary Snyder to Wendell Berry have linked environmental responsiveness to localness and to an intimate knowledge of place and home. What role does literature, oral and written, play in producing, recording, and transmitting such knowledge? How are nature and the landscape around us remembered, imagined, shaped, mourned, and possibly protected by the stories, songs, and poems we humans create? In what ways do writers assign personal or spiritual significance to the landscape? This course uses our own locality of Northern New England and the watershed of the Androscoggin as a base to investigate these questions. Readings include stories from Abenaki oral literature, poems, and stories by contemporary local writers, as well as other selected American writers who have given a strong voice to regionalism in their work.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every other year. S. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="214"/><a name="ES/PL214"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/PL 214. Ethics and Environmental Issues.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of selected issues in environmental ethics, including questions about population growth, resource consumption, pollution, the responsibilities of corporations, environmental justice, animal rights, biodiversity, and moral concern for the natural world. The course explores debates currently taking place among environmental thinkers regarding our moral obligations to other persons, to future generations, to other animals, and to ecosystems and the Earth itself.  Not open to students who have received credit for Environmental Studies 214 or Philosophy 214. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. T. Tracy.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="215"/><a name="ES/RE215"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/RE 215. Environmental Ethics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Values are important influences on the ways human communities relate to ecological communities, and hence on the character of the interaction between persons and their natural worlds. The course examines a range of environmental issues as moral problems requiring ethical reflection. This ethical reflection takes into account both the cultural and religious contexts that have given rise to what is understood as a technological dominion over nature, and the cultural resources still remaining that may provide clues on how to live in friendship with the Earth. Recommended background: one course in philosophy or religion.  Not open to students who have received credit for  Environmental Studies 214 or 215, or Philospohy 214, or Religion 215. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every other year. T. Tracy.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="216"/><a name="ES/RU216"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/RU 216. "Nature" in Russian Culture.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">How does a given culture understand and represent its relationship to the specific geography of its place in the world? This course explores the cultural landscape of Russia through a broad range of literary works, visual images, and ethnographic studies. Students examine some of the following issues: the relationship between geography and national identity; the political uses of cultural landscape; the interaction of agriculture, official religion, and traditional belief in peasant culture; and the role of class and revolutionary reimaginings of nature in the Soviet era. Conducted in English.  Not open to students who have received credit for Environmental Studies 314 or Russian 314. Normally offered every other year. J. Costlow.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="217"/><a name="ENVR217"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 217. Mapping and GIS.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Geographical information systems (GIS) are computer-based systems for geographical data presentation and analysis. They allow rapid development of high-quality maps, and enable sophisticated examination of spatial patterns and interrelationships. This course begins with a consideration of maps and general principles of cartography. Then it introduces GIS software running on the Windows operating system. Students are introduced to common sources of geographic data, learn methods for collecting novel spatial data, and consider data quality. Finally, students learn to extend the capabilities of GIS software to tackle more advanced spatial analysis tasks. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="218"/><a name="ES/PS218"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/PS 218. U.S. Environmental Politics and Policy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the development and current state of environmental policy in the United States at the federal, state, and local levels, while at the same time placing the making of this policy in the broader context of American politics, economics, and society. The course begins with a short history of environmentalism and the current state of American environmental politics and policy. Students then take a case study approach to a specific environmental issue relevant to the local area. This case study provides an opportunity for students to meet and interact with stakeholders involved with this issue. Prerequisite(s): Environmental Studies 204 or any political science course. Not open to students who have received credit for Political Science 218. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every other year. P. Rogers.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="218"/><a name="INDS218"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 218. <span class="cite">Afroambiente</span>: Writing A Black Environment.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course studies the response of Black writers and intellectuals of the Spanish-speaking world to issues related to the natural environment. In three countries, Ecuador, Puerto Rico, and Equatorial Guinea, modernity has brought serious challenges to notions of economic progress, human rights, national sovereignty, as well as individual and communal identity. Course materials include written texts from local newspapers, magazines, as well as other sources of information, such as internet sites that discuss issues related to the environment and the arts. Recommended background: Spanish 207 or 208. Cross-listed in African American studies, environmental studies, and Spanish. Conducted in Spanish. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall 2005.</span> Not open to students who have received credit for Interdisciplinary Studies s21. Open to first-year students. Offered with varying frequency. B. Fra-Molinero.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="219"/><a name="INDS219"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 219. Environmental Archeology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Over the past two hundred years archeologists and scientists and humanists in many disciplines have worked together in researching the interactions of past human populations with the physical world, including plants, animals, landscapes, and climates. This course outlines the methods and theories used by archeologists, geologists, biologists, physicists, chemists, and historians in reconstructing past economies and ecologies in diverse areas of the globe. The course also discusses how archeology contributes to our understanding of contemporary environmental issues such as rapid climate change, shrinking biodiversity, and sustainable use of resources. Cross-listed in environmental studies, anthropology and history. Recommended background: Anthropology 103. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Winter 2006.</span> Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. G. Bigelow.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="225"/><a name="ENVR225"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 225. Comparative Environmental Politics and Policy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Variations in political forms, economic status, cultural contexts, and the natural environment are significant factors in shaping environmental politics and policy around the world. This course investigates these differences using the framework of political ecology, and explores the potential of comparative analysis between cases. The regions of Western Europe, post-communist Eurasia, East Asia, Latin America, and Africa are examined. Prerequisite(s): Environmental Studies 202 or 204.  Open to first-year students. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="228"/><a name="INDS228"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 228. Caring for Creation: Physics, Religion, and the Environment.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course considers scientific and religious accounts of the origin of the universe, examines the relations between these accounts, and explores the way they shape our deepest attitudes toward the natural world. Topics of discussion include the biblical creation stories, contemporary scientific cosmology, the interplay between these scientific and religious ideas, and the roles they both can play in forming a response to environmental problems. Cross-listed in environmental studies, physics, and religion.  Not open to students who have received credit for Environmental Studies 228, Physics 228, or Religion 228. Enrollment limited to 40. Offered with varying frequency. J. Smedley, T. Tracy.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="240"/><a name="ENVR240"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 240. Water and Watersheds.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Where does water go and what does it do? Humans across the globe extract, enjoy, use, waste, and conserve water and hence affect its distribution, movement, and quality. In this unit, students follow water from atmosphere to land to aquatic systems, emphasizing the controls on the movement and chemistry of water. They investigate not only the need of organisms for water but also the ways in which organisms, including humans, influence the distribution and chemistry of water. Some class meetings involve field and lab work. Recommended background: Chemistry 107A and 108A, 
or 107B and 108B. Prerequisite(s): one of the following: Environmental Studies 203, Geology 103 or Biology 101. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. H. Ewing.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="290"/><a name="ES/JA290"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/JA 290. Nature in East Asian Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">How have poets and other writers in Japan and China portrayed, valued, and responded to the myriad phenomena that Western tradition calls "nature"? What ideas have they used to construct the relationship between human beings and the environment? Do their views offer the modern world a possible antidote to its environmental ills? This course looks closely at several works from Japanese and Chinese traditions whose authors pay particular attention to the relationship between the self and the physical world the self observes. Specific writers may include Hitomaro, Saigy&#244;, Kamo no Chomei, Bash&#244;, Li Po, and Wang Wei. Conducted in English. Not open to students who have received credit for Environmental Studies 290 or Japanese 290. Open to first-year students. Offered with varying frequency. S. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="300"/><a name="ENVR300"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 300. Posthuman Science Fictions.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Science fiction endures as the privileged genre for exploring the big questions&#8212;ethical, philosophical, scientific&#8212;of our "posthuman" era. What does it mean to be human, when biotechnology muddles inheritance and blurs the boundaries between species? Does obsession with virtuality presage the "end of nature"? What do the troubling identities of <span class="cite">I, Robot</span> have to do with animal rights? Can we learn from utopian exercises in "terraforming" and apocalypse? In this reading- and writing-intensive course, a range of science fiction works, in literature and film, are paired with philosophical texts, from Plato to Haraway, and discussed in the light of environmental issues? Recommended background: Environmental Studies 205. Prerequisite(s): one of the following: English 121, Philosophy 150, or Environmental Studies 205. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2007.</span> Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. J. Skinner.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="310"/><a name="ENVR310"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 310. Soils.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Depending on one's point of view, soils are geological units, ecosystems, the foundation of plant life, a place for microbes to live, building material, or just dirt. This course takes a scientific perspective and explores the genesis of soils, their distribution and characteristics, and their interaction with plants. Field studies emphasize description of soils, inferences about soil formation, and placement within a landscape context. Labs investigate the chemistry of soils and their role in forestry and agriculture. Prerequisite(s): one chemistry set (Chemistry 107A-108A or 107B-108B) plus one course in either biology or geology. Recommended background: one 200-level geology course. Normally offered every other year. H. Ewing.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="320"/><a name="ES/JA320"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/JA 320. Haiku and Nature in Japan.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The concise, seventeen-syllable verse form known today as haiku rose to prominence in the popular culture of seventeenth-century Japan. With its emphasis on the experience of the present moment and its use of clear natural imagery, haiku is seen by many as defining the way generations of Japanese have perceived and related to the natural world. This seminar examines the poetics of haiku and linked verse <span class="em">(renku)</span> and looks at the expression of their aesthetics in recent Japanese literature and culture from architecture to the novel to Zen. Prerequisite: one course in Japanese or one course in environmental studies. Conducted in English. <span class="crsaddmod">Course prerequisite effective Fall 2004.</span> Normally offered every other year. S. Strong.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="325"/><a name="ENVR325"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 325. Seminar on World Agriculture.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar introduces students to the history of agriculture, the manner in which contemporary agriculture is practiced around the globe, and the ever-changing nature of agriculture and its relationships to the broader social and natural worlds. Two important themes are emphasized in this seminar. The first is the continuing, though often overlooked, importance of agriculture in the modern world. The second is that agriculture is a multidimensional activity with social, cultural, political, economic, and environmental elements. There is a field component where students engage in on-farm research using farming system theories and participatory research techniques. Prerequisite(s): two of the following: Environmental Studies 203, 204, and 205.  Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every other year. P. Rogers.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="345"/><a name="ENVR345"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 345. Seminar in African Wildlife Conservation.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar explores three periods of sub-Saharan African history&#8212;precolonial, colonial, and postcolonial&#8212;in order to assess the changing fortunes of wildlife, habitat, and communities during these eras. Unlike popular views of Africa as an Eden untouched by human activity, the seminar emphasizes the long history and continuing importance of interrelationships between human communities and wildlife in sub-Saharan Africa. While the empirical focus is most definitely on Africa, broader theoretical and policy issues that are applicable to wildlife conservation elsewhere in the world also play a prominent role in the course. Prerequisite(s): two of the following: Environmental Studies 203, 204, and 205. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every other year. P. Rogers.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="ENVR360"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365"/><a name="ENVR365"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 365. Special Topics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Offered occasionally on subjects of special interest. <br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395Q"/><a name="EN/ES395Q"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/ES 395Q. Nature and Culture in European Art Film.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">European art film tends to be more realistic than Hollywood film, yet at the same time it is more conscious of its artifice. What does nature look like when framed in these art-conscious, self-reflexive terms? This course considers challenging masterworks of European cinema from the 1950s until today, with special attention to the place of nature in cinematic narrative and representation. Students watch two films each week and read several theoretical essays. Directors may include Ingmar Bergman, Andrei Tarkovsky, Jean-Luc Godard, Roberto Rossellini, and Claire Denis. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2006</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. S. Dillon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="ENVR457"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course involves research for and writing of the senior thesis, under the direction of a faculty advisor, and participation in a weekly seminar with other environmental studies seniors under the supervision of an environmental studies faculty member. The seminar supplements students' one-on-one work with their advisors and provides a space for students to learn about each other's work. Guidelines for the thesis are published on the program Web site or are available from the program chair. Students register for Environmental Studies 457 in the fall semester and for Environmental Studies 458 in the winter semester.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457-458"/><a name="ENVR457-458"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 457-458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course involves research for and writing of the senior thesis, under the direction of a faculty advisor, and participation in a weekly seminar with other environmental studies seniors under the supervision of an environmental studies faculty member. The seminar supplements students' one-on-one work with their advisors and provides a space for students to learn about each other's work. Guidelines for the thesis are published on the program Web site or are available from the program chair. Students register for Environmental Studies 457 in the fall semester and for Environmental Studies 458 in the winter semester.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="ENVR458"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course involves research for and writing of the senior thesis, under the direction of a faculty advisor, and participation in a weekly seminar with other environmental studies seniors under the supervision of an environmental studies faculty member. The seminar supplements students' one-on-one work with their advisors and provides a space for students to learn about each other's work. Guidelines for the thesis are published on the program Web site or are available from the program chair. Students register for Environmental Studies 457 in the fall semester and for Environmental Studies 458 in the winter semester.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s20"/><a name="ES/RUs20"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/RU s20. Environment and Culture in Russia.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This unit introduces a broad range of environmental issues in contemporary Russia, and invites students to consider those issues in cultural and historical context. Students spend three and one-half weeks at different locations in European Russia and the Urals, visiting sites ranging from newly privatized farms and peasant markets to industrial centers and conservation areas. A period of intensive preparation at Bates is followed by visits and conversations in Russia that acquaint students with ecologists, activists, governmental officials, and ordinary Russian citizens. Recommended background: one course in Russian studies or environmental studies.  Enrollment limited to 12. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. J. Costlow.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="INDSs21"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS s21. Writing a Black Environment.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This unit studies the response of black writers and intellectuals of the Spanish-speaking world to issues related to the natural environment. In countries and regions of Afro-Hispanic majority the presence of the oil industry has brought serious challenges to notions of economic progress, human rights, and national sovereignty, as well as individual and communal identity. Writers from Esmeraldas, Ecuador, and Equatorial Guinea chronicle the contradictory discourses present in their societies between modernity, tradition, the idea of progress, and the degradation of the ecosystem. Recommended background: Spanish 202. Cross-listed in African American studies, environmental studies, and Spanish.  Not open to students who have received credit for African American Studies s21, Environmental Studies s21, or Spanish s21. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. B. Fra-Molinero.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s27"/><a name="EC/ESs27"/><h4 class="crsname">EC/ES s27. Sustaining the Masses.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students in this unit investigate the contradictions and complementarities between economic development and global economic integration on the one hand and environmental protection on the other. Students spend up to four weeks in China visiting farming communities, large- and small-scale industrial enterprises, reforestation sites, nature reserves, and pollution control facilities. They also meet with villagers, workers, and government officials. Linkages between local and international economics, politics, history, culture, and the environment are explored using China as a case study. Recommended background: one or more of the following: Economics 101, 222, 227, 229, or Environmental Studies 202.  Not open to students who have received credit for Economics s27 or Environmental Studies s27. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 10. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. M. Maurer-Fazio, J. Hughes.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s28"/><a name="ENVRs28"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR s28. Contemporary Maine Environmental Issues.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This field research unit gives students an opportunity to explore important local environmental issues and to begin the development of social science field research skills. Student research focuses on identifying relevant stakeholders and describing relations between stakeholders in terms of a specific environmental issue. Examples of relevant issues include, but are not limited to, urban planning and sprawl, wildlife management, impacts of recreational use, water quality, and brownfields redevelopment. During the first week the unit introduces students to topics and research methods. Student groups then undertake research under the supervision of the instructor. Research results and methodological lessons learned occupy the last week. Prerequisite(s): Environmental Studies 202 or 204.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. P. Rogers.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s28"/><a name="INDSs28"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS s28. Shetland Islands: Archeological Field Course.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The main element of this unit is the excavation of a late medieval/early modern farmstead at Brow, Shetland (Scotland). Early settlement in Shetland was on the margin of successful medieval colonization of the North Atlantic. The Brow site is a revealing
"laboratory" in which to explore the interaction of climate change and human settlement in a fragile coastal zone. A series of field trips in mainland Scotland place the Brow excavation in the wider context of settlement, environment,archeology and history ofScotland and the North Atlantic. Recommended background: Prior courses in Medieval history or archaeology. Cross-listed in history, environmental studies and classical and medieval studies. Not open to seniors. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Short Term 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 10. Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. M. Jones.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s32"/><a name="ES/GEs32"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/GE s32. Environmental Change in the Australian Outback.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This field-based unit explores the geology and environmental change that has occurred in central Australia over the last 125,000 years. Students spend four weeks exploring the millennial scale global climate events that are recorded in the sediments of the large interior playa lakes, dune fields, and fluvial systems. Evidence for environmental change coincident with colonization by the first human immigrants beginning 60,000 years ago and the expansion of the European pastoralists into the Australian Outback beginning 200 years ago is explored in the context of this unique geologic setting. Prerequisite(s): Geology 103 or 104. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2005.</span> Enrollment limited to 8. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. B. Johnson.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s33"/><a name="EC/ESs33"/><h4 class="crsname">EC/ES s33. Valuation of Human-Altered Ecosystems.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">How is the value of an ecosystem altered by human development? Answering this question requires an understanding of both economics and ecosystem structure and function. In this interdisciplinary unit, students explore the structure and function of ecosystems before and after human modification and the relationship of these characteristics to their economic value. Students focus on river systems in Maine and contrast these with the Mississippi River from source to sea. This course involves many day trips and two longer trips off campus. Prerequisite(s): Environmental Studies 203 or Economics 222. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 12. Instructor permission is required. Offered with varying frequency. H. Ewing, L. Lewis.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s36"/><a name="ENVRs36"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR s36. Ecopoetics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course seeks to provoke innovative responses to the environmental crisis. If poetics entails all-of-making, including literary, visual, musical and design arts, as well as reflections on making, what are the available creative and critical responses? Through the journal <span class="cite">ecopoetics</span> and beyond, students are exposed to a range of "eco" methodologies: soundscape, walking, and field guide practices, including methods for writing other species, biome investigations, edge studies, and ethnographic translation techniques. The course involves an extensive fieldwork component, and critical reflection, as well as collaborative publication, installation, and/or performance works. Submission of sample of critical or creative work, or a prospectus of such work, required for admission to the course. Recommended background: Environmental Studies 205. <span class="crsaddmod">New unit beginning Short Term 2007.</span> Enrollment limited to 18. Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s37"/><a name="ES/GEs37"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/GE s37. Introduction to Hydrogeology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Hydrogeology is the study of the interactions between water and earth materials and processes. This unit uses hydrogeology as a disciplinary framework for learning about groundwater processes, contamination, supply, use, and management. Students are engaged in class research projects along the Maine coast and within the Androscoggin River basin. Field and laboratory methods are learned in the context of these projects for determining groundwater flow and aquifer properties, collecting samples, and analyzing water quality. The final research project is both written and presented to the College community. Prerequisite(s): any 100-level Geology course or Environmental Studies 203. Enrollment limited to 16. Offered with varying frequency. B. Johnson.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s46"/><a name="ENVRs46"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR s46. Internship in Environmental Studies.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Projects may include hands-on conservation work, environmental education, environmental research, political advocacy, environmental law, or other areas related to environmental questions. Specific arrangement and prior approval of the Committee on Environmental Studies is required.   Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="ENVRs50"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>

               