<div class="Course"><a name="121O"/><a name="EN/ES121O"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/ES 121O. The Creative Spirit: Self and Nature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">What is the relationship among the spirit, the self, and nature? How does communion with nature help the creation and evolution of one&#8217;s sense of "self " and the soul&#8217;s journey? Is creativity connected with divinity? How have nineteenth-, twentieth-,  and twenty-first-century writers, artists, and spiritual thinkers described their connection with the self and the natural world? In this course, students create original poetry, poetic prose, visual art, and/or music within the context of inward reflection, contemplation, mindfulness, and meditation. Authors studied may include Frost, Elizabeth Gilbert, Jack Kornfeld, Mary Oliver, Shelley, Snyder, Cathy Song, Tagore, Thoreau, Whitman, David Whyte, Woolf, Wordsworth, and Yeats. 
 Enrollment limited to 25. L. Dhingra, J. Anthony.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C023">Improvisation and Experimentation in the Arts (C023)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C085">Language and Literacy (C085)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121Q"/><a name="EN/ES121Q"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/ES 121Q. The Lives of Rivers.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this colloquium, students read broadly&#8212;from the magical waterways of classical antiquity to the American folk tradition that takes us "down by the riverside"&#8212;in order to better understand the human need to write about rivers. Students consider verse by Whitman, Walcott, and Spark alongside Twain's stories of Huckleberry Finn and the classic angling novella <span class="cite">A River Runs Through It.  </span>From the local riparian zone on the banks of the Androscoggin, students follow contemporary currents of ecocritical inquiry, investigating moments when the landed human body is literally or figuratively swept away by a torrent of fresh water. Enrollment limited to 25. One-time offering. M. Wright.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="203"/><a name="ENVR203"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 203. Scientific Approaches to Environmental Issues/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to central concepts in environmental science&#8212;the function and interrelationship of physical, chemical, and biological systems&#8212;through the study of specific environmental issues. The laboratory links field studies of environmental systems to the scientific concepts and tools environmental scientists use. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> H. Ewing.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="204"/><a name="ENVR204"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 204. Environment and Society.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Environmental issues rarely have only physical dimensions. They most often also have social and political aspects.  This course familiarizes students with some of the major social scientific contributions to understanding how and why environmental problems arise, how they are defined, and how different groups are affected by and respond to them. The course first outlines the contemporary world system in which environmental debates take place and then identifies drivers of environmental change. Students then apply these ideas to a variety of ongoing environmental controversies, including climate change, agriculture, urbanization, biodiversity conservation, pollution, and environmental justice. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every year. E. Miller.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="205"/><a name="ENVR205"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 205. Lives in Place.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">What does it mean to live sustainably in place? This course investigates possible answers to that question by considering lives in place: particular stories, particular places, and multiple forms of storytelling about human relationship to the more than human world. From nature writing and calendars of nature to poetry, memoir, documentary, and the novel, humans (the "storytelling animal") demonstrate ways of living that enable us to reflect on the virtues, values, vices, and trade-offs of those lives. Keystones in this consideration include modernity and tradition, technologies of change, voices and points of view, animal agency, eating as agricultural act, consumption, and creativity. Students consider both classic and emerging texts and artists from a variety of periods and cultures, examples of humans' ongoing experiment in living on Earth. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every year. J. Costlow.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="208"/><a name="INDC208"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 208. Introduction to Medieval Archaeology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Middle Ages were a time of major cultural changes that laid the groundwork for Northwest Europe's emergence as a global center of political and economic power in subsequent centuries. However, many aspects of life in the period from 1000 to 1500 <span class="smcaps">C.E.</span> were unrecorded in contemporary documents and art, and archaeology has become an important tool for recovering that information. This course introduces the interdisciplinary methods and the findings of archaeological studies of topics including medieval urban and rural lifeways, health, commerce, religion, social hierarchy, warfare, and the effects of global climate change. Cross-listed in anthropology, classical and medieval studies, environmental studies, and history. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. (Premodern.) G. Bigelow.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C025">Archaeology and Material Culture (C025)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C048">Premodern History (C048)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="211"/><a name="INDC211"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 211. Environmental Perspectives on U.S. History.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the relationship between the North American environment and the development and expansion of the United States. Because Americans' efforts (both intentional and not) to define and shape the environment were rooted in their own struggles for power, environmental history offers an important perspective on the nation's social history. Specific topics include Europeans', Africans', and Indians' competing efforts to shape the colonial environment; the impact and changing understanding of disease; the relationship between industrial environments and political power; and the development of environmental movements. Cross-listed in American cultural studies, environmental studies, and history. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. (Modern. ) (United States.) J. Hall.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="214"/><a name="ES/PL214"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/PL 214. Environmental Ethics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of selected issues in environmental ethics, including questions about population growth, resource consumption, pollution, the responsibilities of corporations, environmental justice, animal rights, biodiversity, and moral concern for the natural world. The course explores debates currently taking place among environmental thinkers regarding our moral obligations to other persons, to future generations, to other animals, and to ecosystems and the Earth itself. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. P. Schofield.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="216"/><a name="ES/RU216"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/RU 216. Nature in Russian Culture.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">How does a given culture understand and represent its relationship to the specific geography of its place in the world? This course explores the cultural landscape of Russia through a broad range of literary works, visual images, and ethnographic studies. Students examine some of the following issues: the relationship between geography and national identity; the political uses of cultural landscape; the interaction of agriculture, official religion, and traditional belief in peasant culture; and the role of class and revolutionary reimaginings of nature in the Soviet era. Conducted in English. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. J. Costlow.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C024">Modern Europe (C024)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C078">Russian in St. Petersburg (C078)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C067">The Translated World (C067)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="217"/><a name="ES/GE217"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/GE 217. Mapping and GIS/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Geographical information systems (GIS) are computer-based systems for geographical data presentation and analysis. They allow rapid development of high-quality maps, and enable sophisticated examination of spatial patterns and interrelationships. In this course students learn the principles of GIS through extensive computer use of ArcGIS (ESRI). Geological and environmental projects introduce students to cartography, common sources of geographic data, methods for collecting novel spatial data, and data quality. Finally, students learn to extend the capabilities of GIS software to tackle more advanced spatial analysis tasks by completing an independent project. Lectures supplement the laboratory component of the course. Prerequisite: one 200-level course in environmental studies or one 100-level course in geology. Not open to students who have received credit for ENVR 220. Enrollment limited to 20.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> J. Eusden.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="219"/><a name="INDC219"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 219. Environmental Archaeology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Over the past two hundred years archaeologists, scientists, and humanists in many disciplines have worked together to understand the interactions of past human populations with the physical world, including plants, animals, landscapes, and climates. This course outlines the methods and theories used by archaeologists, geologists, biologists, physicists, chemists, and historians in reconstructing past economies and ecologies in diverse areas of the globe. The course also discusses how archaeology contributes to our understanding of contemporary environmental issues such as rapid climate change, shrinking biodiversity, and sustainable use of resources. Cross-listed in anthropology, environmental studies, and history. Recommended background: ANTH 103. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. (Premodern.) Normally offered every year. G. Bigelow.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C025">Archaeology and Material Culture (C025)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C051">Medieval Worlds (C051)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="220"/><a name="ENVR220"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 220. GIS across the Curriculum.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Geographical information systems (GIS) are computer-based systems for analyzing spatially located data. They allow rapid development of high-quality maps and enable sophisticated examination of spatial patterns and interrelationships. In this course students learn the principles of GIS through extensive use of the software ArcGIS (ESRI). Modules from across the curriculum introduce students to spatial data by exploring common data sources, data collection methods, data quality, and data presentation methods. Finally, students extend their capabilities in advanced spatial analysis tasks by undertaking an independent project. Not open to students who have received credit for ENVR 217 or ES/GE 217. Enrollment limited to 20.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> C. Parrish, H. Ewing.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="226"/><a name="ES/GE226"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/GE 226. Hydrogeology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Hydrogeology is the study of the movement and interaction of underground fluids within rocks and sediments.  This course uses hydrogeology as a disciplinary framework for learning about groundwater processes, contamination, supply, use, and management.  Students engage in practical applications of hydrogeology via discussions, guest lectures, research projects, problem sets, and hands-on experience. Students learn field and laboratory methods for determining and analyzing groundwater flow, contamination, and aquifer properties by working at local sites of interest in central Maine. Prerequisite(s): ENVR 203 or one 100-level geology course. Enrollment limited to 22.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> B. Johnson.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="227"/><a name="ENVR227"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 227. Catastrophes and Hope.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Disaster narratives can be both documentary and cautionary, attempting to describe what seems beyond human imagination. Such narratives may serve as dire warnings, offer glimpses of hope, spur us to change our lives, or scare us into denial. This course explores examples of disaster narratives from various cultures and time periods, considering the emotional, aesthetic, and civic function of discourses of disaster. In addition, students consider imaginations of disaster at the end of the cold war and in contemporary discussions of climate change. Prerequisite(s): ENVR 205. Enrollment limited to 30. J. Costlow.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="228"/><a name="INDC228"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 228. Caring for Creation: Physics, Religion, and the Environment.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course considers scientific and religious accounts of the origin of the universe, examines the relations between these accounts, and explores the way they shape our deepest attitudes toward the natural world. Topics of discussion include the biblical Creation stories, contemporary scientific cosmology, the interplay between these scientific and religious ideas, and the roles they both can play in forming a response to environmental problems. Cross-listed in environmental studies, physics, and religious studies. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> J. Smedley, T. Tracy.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="229"/><a name="ENVR229"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 229. The Electric Grid.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An exploration of electricity production, distribution, and consumption. Principles of electromagnetism are developed to provide an understanding of the design and function of the electric grid. Topics include the history of grid evolution, reliability and disruptions, organizational design, regulations, environmental impacts, energy storage, incorporation of renewable energy sources, and the smart grid. Prerequisite(s): CHEM 107A, ENVR 203, or any course in physics.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> J. Smedley.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="232"/><a name="BI/ES232"/><h4 class="crsname">BI/ES 232. Global Change in Terrestrial Systems.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this course students investigate how global change is affecting terrestrial ecosystems. Plants are the dominant organisms in these systems. Students discuss how adaptations to particular environments may favor or hinder individual species in the future, and how ecology and physiology interact when it comes to species responses to global change. They consider processes from the leaf to ecosystem levels and discuss how natural and agricultural systems are likely to be affected by changes in temperature and water availability, rising carbon dioxide and gaseous pollutants, and alterations in soil chemistry and nutrient availability. Prerequisite(s): BIO 117, 124, 190, or ENVR 203. Open to first-year students.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="240"/><a name="ENVR240"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 240. Water and Watersheds/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Where does water go and what does it do? In this course students follow water from atmosphere to land to aquatic systems, emphasizing the controls on the movement and chemistry of water in freshwater ecosystems. They investigate not only the need of organisms for water but also the ways in which organisms, including humans, influence the distribution and chemistry of water. Field and laboratory studies combine ecological, geological, and chemical approaches as well as an introduction to working with large data sets. Students are assumed to be proficient in the use of spreadsheets. Prerequisite(s): one of the following: ENVR 203; BIO 190, BI/GE 112, GEO 103, GEO 107. Recommended background: CHEM 107A and CHEM 108A. Enrollment limited to 18.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> H. Ewing.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="242"/><a name="AN/ES242"/><h4 class="crsname">AN/ES 242. Environment, Human Rights, and Indigenous Peoples.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">For decades environmentalists have used the image of the "ecological native" in their critique of industrialization while indigenous activists have framed their struggles for land rights and self-determination in environmental terms. Why and how have environmental and indigenous concerns merged? How are these connections used strategically? This course examines the struggles of the world's indigenous peoples in the context of an accelerating ecological crisis. Topics include Western ideas of indigenous people, indigenous self-representation, indigenous relations to modern nation-states and the United Nations, and the impacts of oil and mining, bio-prospecting, biodiversity conservation and climate change. Prerequisite(s): one of the following: ANTH 101, ENVR 337, 204, 350, or PLTC 250. Enrollment limited to 30. S. Pieck.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C037">Identity, Race, and Ethnicity (C037)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C072">Latin American Studies (C072)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="246"/><a name="BI/ES246"/><h4 class="crsname">BI/ES 246. Conservation Biology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Conservation biology incorporates biology, policy, and ethics, among other disciplines. This course introduces and analyzes conservation theory with emphasis on the biological aspects of conservation biology, but also exploring its interdisciplinary nature. Students examine conservation at many scales, including the conservation of populations, their genetic diversity, and the biodiversity of habitats. Applied aspects of conservation and sustainable development are illustrated through case studies and simulations. This course is a combination of discussion and applied methods. Some Saturday field trips are required. Prerequisite(s): BIO 190 or ENVR 203.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 40. (Community-Engaged Learning.)  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="258"/><a name="EN/ES258"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/ES 258. The Future Perfect Tense: Cli-Fi and Sense Making in the Anthropocene .</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The last decade saw the rise of a new genre: climate change fiction, or "Cli-Fi" for short. Like other forms of science fiction, Cli-Fi is shaped by a set of contemporary anxieties about human beings and their relationship with the environment and technology. But where science fiction is speculative, the world Cli-Fi characters occupy often looks a lot like earth. Intense drought spawns violence, racial discrimination, and migration. Resource scarcity breeds new international treaties and ethnic cleansing. What does it mean that the speculative genre has moved into the present tense? And in what ways can fiction create an imagined world that gives voice to resistance today?  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2017.</span> Enrollment limited to 25. One-time offering. E. Rush Mueller.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="266"/><a name="INDC266"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 266. Environmental History of China.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course investigates the deep historical roots that lie behind China's contemporary environmental dilemmas. From the Three Gorges Dam to persistent smog, a full understanding of the environment in China must reckon with millennia-old relationships between human and natural systems. In this course studenst explore the advent of grain agriculture, religious understandings of nature, the impact of bureaucratic states, and the environmental dimensions of imperial expansion as well as the nature of kinship and demographic change. The course concludes by turning to the socialist "conquest" of nature in the 1950s and 1960s and China's post-1980s fate. Cross-listed in Asian studies, environmental studies, and history.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2017.</span> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. (East Asian.) W. Chaney.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="271"/><a name="BI/ES271"/><h4 class="crsname">BI/ES 271. Dendrology and the Natural History of Trees/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this field-based course, students engage in the scientific study of the natural history and identification of trees and important shrubs native to New England, and some commonly planted non-native trees. Topics include the anatomy, function, taxonomy, biology, and uses of trees. Lecture topics support weekly outdoor laboratories, which include trips to such field sites as the Bates-Morse Mountain Conservation Area, Thorncrag Bird Sanctuary, and Wolfe's Neck State Park. Study of the woody flora of New England serves as a foundation for further work in biology, environmental studies, conservation, or related fields. Prerequisite(s): BIO 117, 124, 190, or ENVR 203.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 18. B. Huggett.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="272"/><a name="ES/PT272"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/PT 272. <span class="cite">Oikos</span>: Rethinking Economy and Ecology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Economy and ecology share the same Greek root: <span class="cite">oikos</span>, or "home." Both name relationships that are crucial to the sustenance of life, yet these two domains often appear to be locked in mortal combat. Why is the <span class="em">oikos</span> of modern life torn asunder? What is this split and how did it arise? Is reconciliation possible? If so, what might it entail? This course brings critical tools from political theory and science studies to bear on these questions, exploring a variety of attempts to rethink the relation between economy and ecology and to reconfigure the very nature of the categories themselves. Recommended background: one course in anthropology, economics, environmental studies, politics, or sociology. Not open to students who have received credit for ENVR 272. Enrollment limited to 30. (Philosophical, Literary, and Legal Studies.) (Political Economy.) E. Miller.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="301"/><a name="ENVR301"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 301. Politics of Nature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">What is nature and what does it mean to say that it has a politics? In one common understanding, nature is precisely that which stands apart from political dynamics, indicating a world of objective "facts" beyond human influence. Yet the concept of nature has long been implicated in relations of power, whether by making certain social relationships such as race, gender, and class seem inevitable or by lending strength to movements for liberation. This course examines the politics of nature through various lenses of poststructuralist, postcolonial, feminist, and Marxist political theory, ultimately seeking to imagine how nature itself might become a site for transformative democratic practice. Prerequisite(s): two of the following: AN/ES 242; ENVR 203, 204, 205, or 272; ES/PL 214; PHIL 150, 211, or 262; PLTC 191 or 202; SOC 204; or WGST 100. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> E. Miller.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="301M"/><a name="ES/HI301M"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/HI 301M. Maine: Environment and History.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to Maine history from its beginnings to the twentieth century, emphasizing the state's most pervasive theme, the environment. From aboriginal people to European colonists, different people have relied on the state's natural resources. Indeed, the environment shaped Maine's most prevalent industries. By the twentieth century, Maine emerged as a popular vacation destination, causing many to reflect on conservation efforts. This seminar explores the significance of locality in understanding the interaction between the environment and different people through time. Students develop a deeper sense of place in our community. Enrollment limited to 15. (Early Modern.) (Modern. ) (United States.) J. Hall.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C059">Colonialism (C059)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="310"/><a name="ENVR310"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 310. Soils/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Depending on one's point of view, soils are geological units, ecosystems, the foundation of plant life, a place for microbes to live, building material, or just dirt. This course takes a scientific perspective and explores the genesis of soils, their distribution and characteristics, and their interaction with plants. Field studies emphasize description of soils, inferences about soil formation, and placement within a landscape context. Labs investigate the chemistry of soils and their role in forestry and agriculture. Prerequisite(s): one of the following: BIO 270; BI/ES 271; CHEM 212 or 215; ENVR 203 or 240; GEO 210, 223, or 240.  Recommended background: one 200-level geology course and CHEM 108A or CH/ES 108B. Enrollment limited to 16.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> H. Ewing.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="321"/><a name="INDC321"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 321. <span class="em">Afroambiente</span>: Writing a Black Environment.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course studies the response of black writers and intellectuals of the Spanish-speaking world to issues related to the natural environment. In three countries, Ecuador, Puerto Rico, and Equatorial Guinea, modernity has brought serious challenges to notions of economic progress, human rights, and national sovereignty, as well as individual and communal identity. Course materials include written texts from local newspapers and magazines as well as other sources of information such as Internet sites that discuss issues related to the environment and the arts. All readings are in English. Cross-listed in African American studies, environmental studies, Latin American Studies, and Spanish.  <span class="crsaddmod"> <span class="crsaddmod"> B. Fra-Molinero.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C016">Bridging <span class="em">El Atl&#225;ntico</span> (C016)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C072">Latin American Studies (C072)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C032">Post/Colonial Issues in French and Spanish (C032)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=LAS">Latin American Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></span></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="333"/><a name="BI/ES333"/><h4 class="crsname">BI/ES 333. The Genetics of Conservation Biology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Conserving biodiversity is important at multiple scales, including genetic variation within species. Does a species have enough variation to evolve in a changing world? Are individuals differentially adapted to local environmental variation? In a captive population of a rare animal, which individuals should be bred to minimize the erosion of genetic variation? Lectures and labs cover the fundamentals of classical, molecular, and population genetics, applying them to current issues in biological conservation. Prerequisite(s): BIO 242 or 270. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 330. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> D. Dearborn.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="334"/><a name="ENVR334"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 334. Living with Animals: Perspectives from Literature and Film.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">When it comes to understanding our lives with the other animals, Boria Sax suggests that "biology is not nearly enough." We also need to study historical traditions, visionary imagination, and legacies of art and storytelling. This course explores what it has meant to live with both domesticated and wild animals, through close reading and study of selected poetry, essays, fiction and film. Enrollment limited to 18.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> M. Beck.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="337"/><a name="ENVR337"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 337. Social Movements, NGOs, and the Environment.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">As emerging transnational actors, social movements and nongovernmental organizations (NGOs) challenge state-centered paradigms with regard to environmental and other issues. But why do environmental movements arise in the first place? Do NGOs necessarily "do environmental good"? What solutions to the environment/development quandary do these forms of activism offer? The course first locates the context for NGOs and social movements within neoliberal globalization and the resource conflicts that emerge from its processes. Students consider topics and case studies in developed and developing countries, using them as a lens through which to understand the complexities of social and environmental change. Prerequisite(s): ANTH 101 or ENVR 204 and two additional courses in environmental studies. Not open to students who have received credit for AN/ES 337. Enrollment limited to 20.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Normally offered every year. S. Pieck.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="340"/><a name="ENVR340"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 340. Literatures of Agriculture.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the ways in which agrarian life has been imagined, written about, and lived in a wide array of cultural and historical settings. Classic pastoral suggests that the life of the countryside is a life of virtue and freedom from the entanglements of politics and the city. The actual experience of farm labor is often embedded in difficult political, economic, and environmental realities, even as farmers profess deep affection for their labor and the land. Students explore a broad range of genres, from agrarian essay to historical studies, memoirs, and novels, considering how different forms of writing articulate ideals, aspirations, and realities. Students visit local farms and interview local farmers. Prerequisite(s): ENVR 205. Enrollment limited to 15. J. Costlow.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="348"/><a name="ENVR348"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 348. Nature and the Novel.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The novel is the social genre <span class="em">par excellence</span>, filled with details of human lives and commentary on politics, philosophy, and morals. But novels are also ideal vehicles for thinking about nature, evocative of particular places, complex communities, legacies of injustice and possibility. Readings for this course, drawn primarily from twentieth-century authors, may include political/philosophical epic (Pasternak's <span class="cite">Doctor Zhivago</span>); the dystopian work of Zamiatin and McCarthy (<span class="cite">We</span>, <span class="cite">The Road</span>); feminist science fiction and agrarian visions of the good life (Atwood and Berry). Close readings of the novels are accompanied by essays in contemporary ecocriticism that help students think about what it means to read novels with environmental questions in mind. Prerequisite(s): ENVR 205. 
 Enrollment limited to 15. J. Costlow.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="350"/><a name="ES/LS350"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/LS 350. Environmental Justice in the Americas.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores issues of environmental justice in the western hemisphere by focusing on how lines of difference&#8212;especially race, class, and gender&#8212;mediate people's relationships to each other and to the natural world. How do power relations shape differential access to and control over resources? What makes people more or less vulnerable to environmental changes? The course applies critical social theory to case studies from across the Americas to explore how political, economic, and cultural forces shape environmental inequalities and how, in trying to address those inequalities, various groups challenge and broaden the assumptions and practices of modern environmentalism. Prerequisite(s): ENVR 204 and two additional courses in environmental studies or three courses in Latin American studies. Not open to students who have received credit for ENVR 350. Enrollment limited to 15. S. Pieck.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C072">Latin American Studies (C072)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="ENVR360"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester. Open to first-year students. Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365"/><a name="ENVR365"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 365. Special Topics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Offered occasionally on subjects of special interest. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="417"/><a name="ENVR417"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 417. Community-Engaged Research in Environmental Studies.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students work collaboratively to complete interdisciplinary semester-long project. Projects include work with previously identified community partners and may vary from year to year. The course deals explicitly with the issues and best practices arising from doing complex collaborative work in a community-engaged setting.  Prerequisite(s): ENVR 204 and 205. (Community-Engaged Learning.) Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="450"/><a name="ENVR450"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 450. Environmental Writing in the Public Sphere.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Building on research from previous environmental studies courses, students produce new writing for public audiences. They consider environmentally themed pieces as models for writing (e.g., advocacy scholarship, scientific writing, personal and lyrical essays, natural history); explore new media forms (radio and video essays); and examine theory on writing and web portfolios. Students' environmental writing develops through peer and professional review and culminates in a substantial piece of writing for a public audience. Web portfolios present the new scholarship and reflect on its creation, showing the process of learning, connections to environmental studies course work, and thematic links beyond Bates. Prerequisite(s): ENVR 203, 204, 205, and 417. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. M. Beck.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="ENVR457"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course involves research for and writing of the senior thesis, under the direction of a faculty advisor. Guidelines for the thesis are published on the program website and are available from the program chair. Students register for ENVR 457 in the fall semester.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="ENVR458"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course involves research for and writing of the senior thesis, under the direction of a faculty advisor. Guidelines for the thesis are published on the program website and are available from the program chair. Students register for ES 458 in the winter semester.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s15"/><a name="AV/ESs15"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/ES s15. Photographing the Landscape.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course provides a context for studying and analyzing images of the landscape by viewing and discussing historic and contemporary landscape photographs. Questions considered include the role of the sublime in current landscape photography, beauty as a strategy for persuasion, perceptions of "natural" versus "artificial," and contemporary approaches in trying to affect environmental change. Students explore the depiction of the landscape by producing their own work, using "pinhole," black-and-white film, or digital photography. Recommended background: AVC 218 or 219. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 12. E. Morris.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C017">Evidence: Documentation and Reality (C017)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C029">Visible Ideas: 2D and 3D Design (C029)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s20"/><a name="ES/RUs20"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/RU s20. Environment and Culture in Russia.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces a broad range of environmental issues in contemporary Russia and invites students to consider those issues in cultural and historical context. A period of intensive preparation at Bates is followed by visits and conversations in Russia that acquaint students with ecologists, activists, governmental officials, and ordinary Russian citizens. Students spend three and one-half weeks at different locations in European Russia and the Urals, visiting sites ranging from privatized farms and peasant markets to industrial centers and conservation areas. Recommended background: one course in Russian studies or environmental studies. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. J. Costlow.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C078">Russian in St. Petersburg (C078)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="ES/GEs21"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/GE s21. Field Studies in Geology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to field studies in geology. Three different geologic settings (bedrock geology, geomorphology, and hydrology) are the focus of three week-long field projects. Each project is followed by laboratory analysis and compilation of the field data in the form of maps, cross sections, and lab reports. Students learn how to map and analyze spatial datasets using mobile GIS field methods and ArcGIS techniques as well as methods in environmental sampling and modeling. Students examine exposures of bedrock on the Maine coast, glacial features in downeast Maine, and river systems in central Maine.  This course provide students with a basic toolkit for fieldwork in geology and environmental studies. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level geology course. Enrollment limited to 30. B. Johnson, J. Eusden.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s25"/><a name="ES/REs25"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/RE s25. Food and the Sacred.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course provides an opportunity to explore food through ideas and practices considered sacred by Jews, Christians, Muslims, Buddhists, Hindus, indigenous peoples, and neo-pagans. Topics include feasting, fasting, farming, foraging, feeding the hungry, the five senses, and the fascinating fundamentals of dirt and water. There is a community-based learning component to this course undertaken outside class of time as well as hands-on individual and group projects. Prerequisite(s): one course in environmental studies or religious studies. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 15. (Community-Engaged Learning.) C. Baker.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C083">Material Culture (C083)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s29"/><a name="ENVRs29"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR s29. Walking: The Practice, Politics, and Pleasures of One's Own Two Feet.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Way of getting from point A to point B; mode of meditation and pilgrimage; radical environmental act; community builder; form of protest; almost impossible to do in many American suburbs. We do it every day, without thinking about it. This course gives students the chance to reflect on and practice this remarkable human mode of transportation. In addition to reading some classic walking texts and experimenting with how to write about walking, students talk with local people who plan sidewalks and trails, and who think about how to get more people moving. The core of the course is walking itself: urban strolls; woodland tracking; meditation; observation. The ability and willingness to walk in all weather is essential. Enrollment limited to 18. J. Costlow.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s34"/><a name="INDCs34"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC s34. Place, Community, and Transformation: Kingston, Jamaica.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course evaluates the feasibility of green space development in Kingston, Jamaica, a city marked by class disparities, political polarization, and the impoverishing impact of neoliberal economic policies. Through assigned texts students explore the city's physical and demographic development under colonial and postcolonial rule. They examine development initiatives, challenges, and failures through guest lectures and tours led by practicing architects, engineers, planners, environmentalists, and community workers. Students undertake ethnographic research in neighborhoods, parks, and public spaces on the use of outdoor recreational space, perceived needs, and food gardening practices to gather data that might guide future community-building green initiatives. Cross-listed in African American studies, anthropology, environmental studies, and Latin American studies. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Community-Engaged Learning.) C. Carnegie.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=LAS">Latin American Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s46"/><a name="ENVRs46"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR s46. Internship in Environmental Studies.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Projects may include hands-on conservation work, environmental education, environmental research, political advocacy, environmental law, or other areas related to environmental questions. Specific arrangement and prior approval of the Committee on Environmental Studies is required.   Instructor permission is required. (Community-Engaged Learning.) Normally offered every year. C. Parrish.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="ENVRs50"/><h4 class="crsname">ENVR s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>

               