<div class="Course"><a name="101"/><a name="EUS101"/><h4 class="crsname">EUS 101. Introduction to European Studies.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to major themes in European studies, considering the dynamic processes by which Europe and European identities have been defined since the cold war. They examine, among other questions, how Europe has changed in the wake of new economic and political realities, with the formation of international organizations, and in the face of shifting ethnic, religious, and cultural landscapes. By investigating these topics from various perspectives, students gain the interdisciplinary tools to understand the intricacies of an ever-changing Europe.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Not open to students who have received credit for FYS 297. Normally offered every year. D. Browne.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=EUS">European Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="120"/><a name="EUS120"/><h4 class="crsname">EUS 120. Kusturica: Gentle Barbarian or Barbaric Gentleman?.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Emir Nemanja Kusturica is one of the most celebrated contemporary filmmakers in Europe; he is also one of the most controversial. His films have brought him numerous festival awards including two Golden Palms at Cannes and a C&#233;sar, the French Oscar. But they have also brought severe criticism from some of Europe's intellectual celebrities such as Alain Finkielkraut and Slavoj Zizek. In this course, students examine all of Kusturica's feature films, and look at the social and political furor his work has generated since the mid 1990s. Films are subtitlted in English.

 Not open to students who have received credit for RUSS 120. Enrollment limited to 60. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C024">Modern Europe (C024)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="206"/><a name="EU/HI206"/><h4 class="crsname">EU/HI 206. The Empire Strikes Back; Or, the Ends of European Empires in the Twentieth Century.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In 1918, Woodrow Wilson famously outlined his Fourteen Points emphasizing the right of subject peoples to self-determination. While Wilson's was hardly the first critique of empire, it provided a framework for increasingly organized anti-colonial movements. Just as European empires reached their zenith, older rationales for empire became harder to maintain. Yet the end(s) of European empires were long in the making. Many would argue that we have yet to live in a postcolonial world. This course explores the changing arguments over the future of European empires, the contests for power, and their effects on individuals' lives across the globe.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. (European.) Normally offered every other year. C. Shaw.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="220"/><a name="EU/GR220"/><h4 class="crsname">EU/GR 220. Remembering War: The Great War, Memory, and Remembrance in Europe.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course focuses on ways in which the experience of the First World War changed established narratives of violence and armed conflict in Central Europe. It investigates how the new narratives became sites of memory, mourning, and remembrance in the twentieth and twenty-first centuries drawing on the examples from Germany, Poland, Czechoslovakia, and Hungary. Normally offered every other year. J. Kazecki.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C073">German in Berlin (C073)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C082">German in Vienna (C082)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="240"/><a name="EUS240"/><h4 class="crsname">EUS 240. Daily Life under Hitler and Stalin.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this course, students examine everyday life in two of the twentieth century's most brutal political systems: Hitler's Nazi Germany and Stalin's USSR. They pay particular attention to how these two totalitarian regimes dominated the public sphere from the late 1920s to the end of World War II, and examine the question of agency: To what extent were the citizens of the Third Reich and the USSR manipulated subjects, willing participants, or sympathetic fellow travelers? Not open to students who have received credit for INDS s13. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. (European.) D. Browne.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C024">Modern Europe (C024)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=EUS">European Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="248"/><a name="EUS248"/><h4 class="crsname">EUS 248. Narratives of the Austro-Hungarian Empire.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Created by the Compromise of 1867 as a dual monarchy, the Austro-Hungarian Empire comprised more than a dozen linguistic and many more ethnic and religious groups. While Vienna was the undisputed cultural capital of the Empire, local urban centers produced a remarkably diverse cultural landscape. Through readings, films, and art by Austrian, Polish, Czech, Romanian, Hungarian, and Jewish artists, students explore this multicultural periphery and consider national, ethnic, class, religious, and gender identities; conflict and cooperation in an age of nationalism; the relationship between center and margins; colonial and postcolonial attitudes; and the legacies of the Empire in today's Central and Eastern Europe.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> R. Cernahoschi.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C067">The Translated World (C067)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=EUS">European Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="254"/><a name="EU/GR254"/><h4 class="crsname">EU/GR 254. Berlin and Vienna, 1900&#8211;1914.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">From the beginning of the twentieth century to the outbreak of World War I, the capital cities of Berlin and Vienna were home to major political and cultural developments, including diverse modernist movements in art, architecture, literature, and music, as well as the growth of mass party politics.  The ascending German Empire and the multiethnic Habsburg Empire teetering on the verge of collapse provide the context within which this course examines important texts of fin-de-si&#232;cle modernism. Topics include urban growth and planning, German Expressionism, Austrian Impressionism, early German cinema, and Freud's case studies of hysteria. Conducted in English. <span class="crsaddmod">Reinstated and cross-listed beginning Fall 2015.</span> Not open to students who have received credit for GER 254. Open to first-year students. C. Decker.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C073">German in Berlin (C073)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C082">German in Vienna (C082)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C024">Modern Europe (C024)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C067">The Translated World (C067)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="261"/><a name="EUS261"/><h4 class="crsname">EUS 261. Slavic Europe.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A topical survey of Slavic culture as realized in a number of social institutions including the family, the church, the popular media, and the arts. Particular attention is given to texts, which examine both real and imagined communities and the unities and disunities that shape the identities of Europe's largest language family and the peoples who occupy more than half of the European continent. 
 Not open to students who have received credit for RUSS 261. Open to first-year students.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> D. Browne.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="324"/><a name="EU/SP324"/><h4 class="crsname">EU/SP 324. Memories of Civil War in European Film and Literature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Issues of memory and postmemory are one of the most relevant concerns in contemporary European culture. This course explores how these concerns are represented in film and narratives of several European civil wars in the twentieth century. Although the main focus is on representations of the Spanish conflict, students also consider the cases of the former Yugoslavia, Ireland, and Greece. Theories of memory (cultural and collective) and postmemory provide the framework for textual and cultural analysis. Recommended background: at least one course on Spanish (Spain), French, German, Russian, or English literature.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall 2015.</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every other year. F. L&#243;pez.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C019">Film and Media Studies (C019)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C089">Spanish in Tarragona (C089)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="351"/><a name="EU/SP351"/><h4 class="crsname">EU/SP 351. Iberian Modernisms: Modernity, Literature and Crisis in Portugal and Spain.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores literary and artistic responses to the social, political, and cultural crises of modernity in Portugal and Spain from 1890 to 1934. It traces the emergence of the concept of the "modern" in early twentieth-century Europe, and examines the particular forms and content of Iberian modernism in terms of key themes: language, the unconscious, sexuality and gender, religion, liberalism, Europe as Other, empire, and cosmopolitanism. Students discuss works translated into English by Portuguese and Spanish authors such as Antonio Machado, Fernando Pessoa, Pio Baroja, Concha Espina, and M&#225;rio S&#225;-Caneiro as well as contemporary film, art, and critical readings in history and cultural theory. Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every other year. D. George.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C089">Spanish in Tarragona (C089)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C018">Writing Spain (C018)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="EUS360"/><h4 class="crsname">EUS 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester. Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="390A"/><a name="INDS390A"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 390A. Sex and the Modern City: European Cultures at the Fin-de-Si&#232;cle .</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Economic and political change during the 1800s revolutionized the daily lives of Europeans more profoundly than any previous century. By the last third of the century, the modern city became the stage for exploring and enacting new roles, new gender identities in particular. This course examines the cultural reverberations of these cataclysmic changes by focusing on sex, gender, and new urban spaces the decades around the turn of the twentieth century. Students consider the writings of Zola and Freud, investigate middle-class flirtations with the occult, and read about sensational crimes like those of Jack the Ripper. Cross-listed in European studies, history, women and gender studies. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 15. (European.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Normally offered every other year. C. Shaw.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="EUS457"/><h4 class="crsname">EUS 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course involves research for and writing of the senior thesis, under the direction of a faculty advisor. Students register for EUS 457 in the fall semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for EUS 457 in the fall semester and EUS 458 in the winter semester.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="EUS458"/><h4 class="crsname">EUS 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course involves research for and writing of the senior thesis, under the direction of a faculty advisor. Students register for EUS 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for EUS 457 in the fall semester and EUS 458 in the winter semester.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s20"/><a name="EUSs20"/><h4 class="crsname">EUS s20. Transylvanian Journey: Myth, Reality, and the Traveler "beyond the Forest.".</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Transylvania&#8212;"The Land beyond the Forest"&#8212;is known in popular culture as the mythical home of Dracula and the locale of awe-inspiring adventures. This course offers students the chance to investigate some of the persisting myths about Transylvania, their origins and their transmission, as well as the reassessment of the province's image since the removal of Romania's communist government in 1989. On campus, students familiarize themselves with the complexities of Transylvania's image through readings and discussions of travel narratives before traveling to Transylvania for a two-week tour in preparation for their own collaborative travel account. Enrollment limited to 14. Instructor permission is required. R. Cernahoschi.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C024">Modern Europe (C024)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="EU/GRs21"/><h4 class="crsname">EU/GR s21. Weimar and Berlin: German Culture in European Context.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course traces the sociopolitical transformations that inform Germany's current role in the European Union through the example of two very different capitals: Weimar, the sleepy hamlet turned Germany's premier intellectual center, and Berlin, the once-divided city reinvented as intercultural meeting place. Using selected sites in the two cities, students focus on key moments in German history, which absorbed international trends and, in turn, reverberated across Europe. On campus and in Germany, students learn about important intellectual developments from the Reformation to the present day, cultural personalities and artifacts, and the crises and cooperations that produced them. Enrollment limited to 16. Normally offered every other year. R. Cernahoschi, J. Kazecki.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C073">German in Berlin (C073)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C082">German in Vienna (C082)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s22"/><a name="EU/PTs22"/><h4 class="crsname">EU/PT s22. Politics of Memory in Central and Eastern Europe.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The twentieth century cast a long shadow over Eastern and Central Europe: two world wars, several mass expulsions and deportations, the imposition of Soviet-style dictatorships, and, most tragically, the Holocaust. Each country has its share of victims, villains, heroes, cowards, and collaborators. Efforts to make sense of this history, even after all these years, remain a topic of intense political debate.  This course examines historical writings, films, museums, and monuments to examine the politics of memory in East and Central Europe. Why does historical memory of these events continue to have such emotional and political power in this region? What choices are made in memorializing history, and what are their contemporary political implications?  <span class="crsaddmod">Course reinstated and crosslisted beginning Short Term 2015.</span> Enrollment limited to 30. (Identities and Interests.) (Philosophical, Literary, and Legal Studies.) J. Richter.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s23"/><a name="EUSs23"/><h4 class="crsname">EUS s23. Dracula Looks in the Mirror: Popular Imagination and Transcultural Adaptation.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Dracula is one of the most widely adapted literary figures, with roots in both history and myth. In this course, studenst investigate the origins of the figure as well as into its multiple transcultural reflections. Through the figure of Dracula, we also investigate questions about the forms, processes, agents, audiences, and contexts of adaptations. A creative component allows students to adapt Dracula to a context of their own choice.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2015.</span> Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. R. Cernahoschi.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s26"/><a name="EUSs26"/><h4 class="crsname">EUS s26. Russian and East European Film.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">From the early years of the Russian avant-garde to the post-Communist era of blockbusters, Russian and East European cinema offers an intriguing and important perspective on life in Europe. This course introduces students to the avant-garde cinema of Eisenstein and Vertov, the Soviet propaganda films of the 1930s, the Czech New Wave, the Yugoslav Black Wave, the Polish Film School, the aesthetic and moral questions of post-Communist filmmakers, and new directions in filmmaking of the twenty-first century. Films are in the original languages, with subtitles. All reading and writing is in English. Not open to students who have received credit for RUSS s26. D. Browne.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C019">Film and Media Studies (C019)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C024">Modern Europe (C024)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C069">Russian Language (C069)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="EUSs50"/><h4 class="crsname">EUS s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>

               