<div class="Course"><a name="115"/><a name="EXDS115"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS 115. Bates Science Fellows.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">What does it mean to "think like a scientist"? In this course, students apply knowledge and skills from other science and mathematics courses to the study of contemporary issues in science. This year-long sequence integrates scientific and quantitative concepts commonly covered in first-year science and math courses. With readings, class discussions, individual and group work, students examine and analyze case studies and the scientific literature on various topics. Throughout the course, emphasis is given to how we develop and understand scientific knowledge. One-half course credit is granted upon completion of the course. Corequisite(s): CHEM 107A. Not open to students who have received credit for INDS 115. Enrollment limited to 12. Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. J. Smedley.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="116"/><a name="EXDS116"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS 116. Bates Science Fellows.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A continuation of EXDS 115. One-half course credit is granted upon completion of the course. Prerequisite(s): EXDS 115. Corequisite(s): CHEM 108A. Not open to students who have received credit for INDS 116. Enrollment limited to 12. Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. J. Smedley.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s11"/><a name="EXDSs11"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s11. Financial Accounting.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is an introduction to the framework, basic concepts, and generally accepted accounting principles and standards underlying financial accounting systems. Students learn to analyze and record financial transactions form a source document through the entire accounting cycle. Accounting concepts include merchandising operations, inventory costing methods, internal controls and cash, receivables, liabilities, and long-term assets including intangibles. Students create basic financial statements and apply analytical tools to these and to statements from real companies.  Additionally, ethical issues in accounting are discussed as relevant topics arise. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="EXDSs21"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s21. Life Architecture: Designing Your Future Work.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Everyone works, whether for pay or for pleasure, in public or in private, with gusto or with dread. This course supports students as they prepare for a lifetime of work by encouraging consideration of the philosophical components of their plan including identifying and developing personal attributes correlated with career well-being, exploring the context of vocational decision making, and contemplating how meaning and purpose can be infused into any work. They also consider the pragmatic components, discussing how mentors can be cultivated, how jobs are best secured, and the practical considerations that can hold people back from realizing their visions. Not open to first-years or sophomores. Enrollment limited to 30. R. Fraser-Thill.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s30"/><a name="EXDSs30"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s30. Grant Writing across the Disciplines.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to the work and writing under taken by scholars, scientists, and artists at two crucial moments: when they have an idea for a project and when they have completed the project. Working in and across a variety of disciplines, students learn the methodologies for garnering support for arts and research endeavors. Students develop an individual project and pursue the examination and implementation of discipline-specific approaches to publication, performance, or the deployment of studies or experiments. In addition to focusing on interdisciplinary scholarship and arts, this course provides a tool kit for students pursuing graduate school, fellowships, and grants. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> R. Strong.<br/></span></div>

               