<div class="Course"><a name="s11"/><a name="EXDSs11"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s11. Financial Accounting.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is an introduction to the framework, basic concepts and generally accepted accounting principles and standards underlying financial accounting systems.  Students will learn to analyze and record financial transactions form a source document through the entire accounting cycle.  Accounting concepts to be studied in detail include:  merchandising operations; inventory costing methods; internal controls and cash; receivables; liabilities; and long term assets including intangibles.  Students will create basic financial statements and apply analytical tools to these and thes tatements from real companies.  Additionally, ethical issues in accounting will be discussed as relevant toipcs arise.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2015.</span> Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s15C"/><a name="EXDSs15C"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s15C. Short Term Practicum: Social Change Organizing and Advocacy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces concepts, strategies, and skills employed in the professional careers of organizers and advocates for social change, the act of changing power structures in society and/or the outcomes of those power structures in order to reduce exploitation, human suffering, and denial of human rights. Practitioners lead students through the examination of in-depth case studies of social change efforts at the local, state, and national level. Topics include poverty, LGBTQ rights, voting rights, immigration, urban development, housing, racial justice, labor, gender equity and environmental justice. Students explore strategies and skills illustrated in each case study, in the context of social change advocacy and organizing careers and more broadly in the context of informed civic action. Students develop and present proposals for social change projects reflecting detailed knowledge of a social issue of particular interest to them and a thoughtful application of some specific skills and strategies covered in the course. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 16. Instructor permission is required. One-time offering. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s15E"/><a name="EXDSs15E"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s15E. Short Term Practicum: Entrepreneurship.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces the key elements and tools used by entrepreneurs as they develop, design and test a product or project. Class activities and case studies provide a basic understanding of entrepreneurship and the startup; the process of identifying a problem/opportunity which needs a solution; identifying and analyzing the appropriate market and competition; planning, developing and implementing the solution; and pitching the solution to its market and potential investors. The course will consist of case studies, guest entrepreneurs and individual and team activities. Final products: Business Plan Executive Summary, Elevator Pitch, multi-media presentation, final Pitch Event.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2015.</span> Enrollment limited to 16. Instructor permission is required. One-time offering. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s15F"/><a name="EXDSs15F"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s15F. Short Term Practicum: Music Production, Recording, and Mixing.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course provides a solid foundation of practical techniques for the new to intermediate recordist including signal flow analysis, optimization, structuring a session, budgeting time and finances, acoustics, mixing, and editing. The course is grounded in traditional rudiments and fundamentals, but focused on production that is nimble and forward thinking enough for the digital age. In addition to the technology, the course examines the musical, interpersonal, and organizational skills needed to make a record successfully &#8211; skills that extend beyond the realm of music production. Additionally, the course examines applications of audio technology beyond the realm of music production, including audio post-production for video and podcasting. The course focuses on imparting skills that can be applied to any digital audio workstation (DAW).  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2015.</span> Enrollment limited to 16. Instructor permission is required. One-time offering. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C005">Sound (C005)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s15G"/><a name="EXDSs15G"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s15G. Short Term Practicum: Urban Planning.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This practicum introduces a holistic, multi-disciplinary approach to city building that considers current issues of transportation, land use, equity, urban design, public health, sociology, and technology. Students have the opportunity to learn and apply basic tools that are fundamental to urban planning, including analysis, project metric development and mapping. The class will undertake an examination of leading sustainable town- and city- making practices throughout the nation and world. This examination will form the foundation for designing and implementing a physical pilot project aimed at improving local street design and public space.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2015.</span> Enrollment limited to 16. Instructor permission is required. One-time offering. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s15H"/><a name="EXDSs15H"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s15H. Short Term Practicum: Mediation and Restorative Justice.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces the philosophies and skills used by practitioners of Restorative Justice and Mediation. Restorative Justice seeks a humanistic response to conflict, wrongdoing and crime. Students learn the Restorative Justice techniques of circle facilitation, restorative language, and observation, focusing on its practice in the juvenile justice system, in communities, and on college campuses. Mediation immerses students in a problem-solving approach to resolving disputes. Drawing from diverse disciplines, coaching, class discussions, presentations, and role play, students gain a deeper understanding of conflict. Using the classroom as a conflict skills workshop, students acquire tools to improve communication and facilitate cooperation and collaboration. Students will receive a Certificate of Completion, proof of 40 hours of mediation training, a commonly accepted state and national standard for new Mediators.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2015.</span> Enrollment limited to 16. Instructor permission is required. One-time offering. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C030">Children, Adolescents, School (C030)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s19"/><a name="EXDSs19"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s19. Introduction to Computer Programming.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students are introduced to computer programming in the C++ programming language. They begin by learning an important three-step approach to computer programming: problem analysis, program design, and program coding. The course covers key programming concepts such as variables, operators, flow control, and I/O as well as some of the programming paradigms commonly used today. In the final week students gain exposure to additional programming languages in order to reinforce the programming concepts common to many languages. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 20.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s20"/><a name="EXDSs20"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s20. Introduction to Computer Programming.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to some of the foundational concepts of computer science. Students analyze problems and implement solutions using languages such as C, Java, Python, PHP or Javascript. Irrespective of the particular programming language used, the goal is to ensure that each student acquires the basic concepts to be prepared to learn any programming language on their own in the future. No prior programming experience is required.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2015.</span> Enrollment limited to 20. One-time offering. P. Jayawant.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s30"/><a name="EXDSs30"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s30. Grant Writing Across the Disciplines.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to the work and writing scholars, scientists, and artists do at two crucial moments: when they have an idea for a project, and when they have completed the project. Working in and across a variety of disciplines, students learn the methodologies for garnering support for arts and research endeavors. Students develop an individual project and pursue the examination and implementation of discipline-specific approaches to publication, performance, or the deployment of studies or experiments. In addition to focusing on interdisciplinary scholarship and arts, this course provides a tool kit for students pursuing graduate school, fellowships, and grants. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Short Term 2014.</span> Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> R. Strong.<br/></span></div>

               