<div class="Course"><a name="s15A"/><a name="EXDSs15A"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s15A. Short Term Practicum: Graphic Design.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces graphic design, technology, and the design profession. Through studio work, design research, and historical study, students acquire a foundation in the principles and elements of design, typography, and visual communication. Students address aesthetic and communication problems through the creation of identity, poster, publication, and user interface design. They gain proficiency in the use of industry-standard software, including Adobe Illustrator, Adobe Photoshop, and Adobe InDesign. They consider graphic design in relation to industrial design, the built environment, and emergent media. Contemporary business and problem-solving practices are also covered, including branding, design management, design thinking, and strategic innovation. During field trips students explore the breadth and depth of activity within the design profession. Journals, sketchbooks and a final project allow students to demonstrate the skills developed during the course. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2014.</span> Enrollment limited to 16. Instructor permission is required. One-time offering. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C036">Color: Sight and Perception (C036)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C029">Visible Ideas: 2D and 3D Design (C029)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s15B"/><a name="EXDSs15B"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s15B. Short Term Practicum: Health Care Administration.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces the American health care system, with a particular focus on problems faced in delivering and paying for quality health care and approaches to addressing those problems. After a brief overview of the U.S. health care system, specific topics to be explored include access to care, the role of primary versus specialty care, quality measurement, health care finance, legal and compliance issues, human resources, and approaches to continuous improvement. Through readings, class discussion with professionals in various roles in health care, job shadowing, and a final project, students examine ideals and aspirations in delivering high quality, affordable health care as well as practical limitations and barriers to doing so. They consider implications for leaders who seek to change the way health care is delivered, administered and paid for in the United States.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2014.</span> Enrollment limited to 16. Instructor permission is required. One-time offering. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s15C"/><a name="EXDSs15C"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s15C. Short Term Practicum: Social Change Organizing and Advocacy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces concepts, strategies, and skills employed in the professional careers of organizers and advocates for social change, the act of changing power structures in society and/or the outcomes of those power structures in order to reduce exploitation, human suffering, and denial of human rights. Practitioners lead students through the examination of in-depth case studies of social change efforts at the local, state, and national level. Topics include poverty, LGBTQ rights, voting rights, immigration, urban development, housing, racial justice, labor, gender equity and environmental justice. Students explore strategies and skills illustrated in each case study, in the context of social change advocacy and organizing careers and more broadly in the context of informed civic action. Students develop and present proposals for social change projects reflecting detailed knowledge of a social issue of particular interest to them and a thoughtful application of some specific skills and strategies covered in the course. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2014.</span> Enrollment limited to 16. Instructor permission is required. One-time offering. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s15D"/><a name="EXDSs15D"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s15D. Short Term Practicum: Digital Innovation.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">From startups to innovative projects within existing organizations, digital innovation and entrepreneurship are fast growing arenas that present exciting challenges and opportunities. This practicum focuses on the tools, techniques, and practices used by digital innovators as they develop, design, and test products. Students explore the history and current challenges in this field, and then work through a process of product discovery, market research, wireframing, branding, and product development. At each step in this process, students develop a foundation of relevant skills including coding, design, marketing, distribution across various platforms, and project management. They apply those skills to the development of a tangible product, and explore a wide range of professional roles within the broad field of digital innovation and entrepreneurship. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2014.</span> Enrollment limited to 16. Instructor permission is required. One-time offering. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s30"/><a name="EXDSs30"/><h4 class="crsname">EXDS s30. Grant Writing Across the Disciplines.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to the work and writing scholars, scientists, and artists do at two crucial moments: when they have an idea for a project, and when they have completed the project. Working in and across a variety of disciplines, students learn the methodologies for garnering support for arts and research endeavors. Students develop an individual project and pursue the examination and implementation of discipline-specific approaches to publication, performance, or the deployment of studies or experiments. In addition to focusing on interdisciplinary scholarship and arts, this course provides a tool kit for students pursuing graduate school, fellowships, and grants. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Short Term 2014.</span> Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> R. Strong.<br/></span></div>

               