<div class="Course"><a name="103"/><a name="GEO103"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 103. Earth Surface Environments and Environmental Change/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Earth's surface environments are in a constant state of change resulting from the interaction of its atmosphere, hydrosphere, biosphere, and lithosphere. Changes on the surface occur on various time scales from brief, severe storms to glaciations lasting thousands of years and changes in continents and ocean basin environments occurring over millions of years due to tectonic processes. Studies of surficial processes and materials illustrate the dynamic nature of the Earth and provide a key to understanding past and future environmental change. The lectures are complemented with field and laboratory study. Field experiences include day trips to the Maine coast, or the White Mountains. Enrollment limited to 52.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every year. M. Retelle.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="104"/><a name="GEO104"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 104. Plate Tectonics and Tectonic Hazards/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc"> Volcanoes, earthquakes, and tsunamis are examples of tectonic hazards that directly affect human populations. Yet the processes responsible for such natural hazards are an integral part of the global tectonic cycle that over millions of years results in the formation of ocean basins, mountain ranges, and the global-scale motion of continents. Study of active and ancient tectonic activity is key to forecasting future volcanic eruptions and earthquakes as well as global environment change. The laboratory component emphasizes understanding global tectonic processes and reconstructing the tectonic history of southwestern Maine through field studies. Enrollment limited to 52.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every year. G. Robert.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="107"/><a name="GEO107"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 107. Katahdin to Acadia: Field Geology in Maine/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The rocky coast and glaciated bedrock mountains of Maine have a rich 500-million-year geologic history. This hands-on, outdoor-oriented course on Maine's geologic history includes weekly half-day field trips to local geologic settings, two required day-long field trips to the Presidential Range and a Maine island, and one or two required weekend trips to Acadia National Park or Baxter State Park. Reading and making maps, recording field observations, writing papers, giving talks, and making posters about the variety of geologic environments are the major features of the course. The required trips involve strenuous hiking and sea kayaking. Appropriate outdoor clothing and footwear is needed. Not open to students who have received credit for FYS 327. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every year. J. Eusden.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="108"/><a name="GEO108"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 108. Global Environmental Change.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Earth's system is comprised of the dynamic interactions between its various components: the biosphere, lithosphere, hydrosphere, and the atmosphere. Currently, humans are perturbing these components at unprecedented rates, resulting in environmental change on regional and global scales. In this course, students examine the Earth system on multiple timescales and investigate current topics in global change, including the impact of greenhouse gases on global climate, sea level, El Ni&#241;o, global dimming, and ocean acidification. Two required day-long field trips to the Maine coast take place on weekends. Not open to students who have received credit for GEO 109. Enrollment limited to 44.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> B. Johnson.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="109"/><a name="GEO109"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 109. Global Change/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Earth's system is comprised of the dynamic interactions between its various components: the biosphere, lithosphere, hydrosphere, and the atmosphere. Humans are perturbing these components at unprecedented rates, resulting in environmental change on regional and global scales. In this laboratory course, students examine the Earth system on multiple timescales and investigate current topics in global change, including the impact of greenhouse gases on global climate, sea level, El Ni&#241;o, global dimming, and ocean acidification.  Laboratories include field trips to sites that illustrate environmental change on local and regional scales. Not open to students who have received credit for GEO 108. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every year. B. Johnson.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="111"/><a name="GE/PH111"/><h4 class="crsname">GE/PH 111. Polar Environment, Climate, and Ecosystems.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the global importance of the polar environment and ecosystem, and how they are affected by climate change. Topics include the physical environment of the polar regions, feedbacks on the global climate, the past history of glaciations, the polar ecosystem, and the change occuring now. Ice volume and sea level rise are estimated. Basic algebra and geometry are used throughout. Recommended background: basic algebra and geometry.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 60.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> R. Saha.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C056">Physics of the Large and Small (C056)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="113"/><a name="BI/GE113"/><h4 class="crsname">BI/GE 113. Marine Science.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An integrated, interdisciplinary overview of the chemistry, physics, geology, and biology of the world's oceans. Topics include chemical and physical properties of sea water, ocean circulation, evolution of the ocean basins, coastal geomorphology, the distribution and abundance of organisms in the major marine communities, the status of the world's major fisheries, and the role of the ocean in the global carbon cycle. Lectures are supplemented by demonstrations and occasional laboratory exercises, though the course does not fulfill the General Education laboratory requirement.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Not open to students who have received credit for BI/GE 112. Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> W. Ambrose.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="210"/><a name="GEO210"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 210. Sedimentary Processes and Environments/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The study of modern sedimentary processes and environments provides geologists with a basis for comparison with ancient deposits preserved in the rock record. The analysis of modern sedimentary environments and reconstruction of ancient environments permit stratigraphic reconstructions at regional and global scales. Laboratory work includes field studies of processes and interpretation of modern and ancient depositional systems. Prerequisite(s): one introductory geology course.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span>  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Normally offered every year. M. Retelle.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="217"/><a name="ES/GE217"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/GE 217. Mapping and GIS/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Geographical information systems (GIS) are computer-based systems for geographical data presentation and analysis. They allow rapid development of high-quality maps, and enable sophisticated examination of spatial patterns and interrelationships. In this course students learn the principles of GIS through extensive computer use of ArcGIS (ESRI). Geological and environmental projects introduce students to cartography, common sources of geographic data, methods for collecting novel spatial data, and data quality. Finally, students learn to extend the capabilities of GIS software to tackle more advanced spatial analysis tasks by completing an independent project. Lectures supplement the laboratory component of the course. Prerequisite: one 200-level course in environmental studies or one 100-level course in geology. Not open to students who have received credit for ENVR 220. Enrollment limited to 20.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> J. Eusden.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="223"/><a name="GEO223"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 223. Rock-Forming Minerals and Mineral Assemblages/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Many geochemical processes that occur within the lithosphere, such as crystallization of magmas, metamorphism, and weathering, are understood through the study of minerals and mineral assemblages. This course covers the occurrence, composition, and compositional variation of the common silicate minerals, the mineral reactions and assemblages typical of igneous, metamorphic, and sedimentary environments, and contemporary applications to a range of tectonic processes. The laboratory involves hand-specimen identification of minerals and the determination of mineral composition by optical microscopy, energy dispersive X-ray spectrometry, and X-ray diffraction. Prerequisite(s): one introductory geology course and CHEM 107A.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span>  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Normally offered every year. G. Robert.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="226"/><a name="ES/GE226"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/GE 226. Hydrogeology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Hydrogeology is the study of the movement and interaction of underground fluids within rocks and sediments.  This course uses hydrogeology as a disciplinary framework for learning about groundwater processes, contamination, supply, use, and management.  Students engage in practical applications of hydrogeology via discussions, guest lectures, research projects, problem sets, and hands-on experience. Students learn field and laboratory methods for determining and analyzing groundwater flow, contamination, and aquifer properties by working at local sites of interest in central Maine. Prerequisite(s): ENVR 203 or one 100-level geology course. Enrollment limited to 22.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> B. Johnson.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="230"/><a name="GEO230"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 230. Earth Structure and Dynamics/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The processes of mountain building and plate tectonics are understood by observing the structure and architecture of rocks. This course explores the nature and types of structures present in rocks that make up the Earth's crust. Fundamental concepts and principles of deformation are examined in a variety of field settings. The laboratory introduces the techniques used in descriptive and kinematic structural analysis. Several one-day excursions and one weekend field trip take place throughout Maine and the mountains of the northern Appalachians. Prerequisite(s): any introductory-level geology course.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span>  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Normally offered every year. J. Eusden.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="240"/><a name="GEO240"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 240. Environmental Geochemistry/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to the chemistry of geological processes that occur at the Earth's surface. Basic concepts of rock-water interactions, chemical equilibria, and biogeochemical cycling are presented in the context of natural settings as well as those influenced by anthropogenic activity. Students work on local environmental problems, which may include surface and groundwater contamination by salt, arsenic, nutrients, and/or heavy metals; acid mine drainage; and the history of lead deposition. The laboratory includes fieldwork and GIS, chemical analysis of environmental samples using inductively coupled plasma emission spectroscopy, and stable isotope ratio mass spectrometry and modeling using STELLA. Prerequisite(s): any 100-level geology course and CHEM 107A. Enrollment limited to 20.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span>  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Normally offered every year. B. Johnson.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C045"> North Atlantic Studies (C045)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="310"/><a name="GEO310"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 310. Quaternary Geology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Quaternary Period, representing the last 1.6 million years of geologic history, is characterized by extreme climatic fluctuations with effects ranging from globally synchronous glacier expansions to periods warmer than present. Records of the climatic fluctuations are contained in sediments on land and in the oceans and lakes and also in the stratigraphy of ice caps. This course examines various climate proxy records and the dating methods used to constrain them. Fieldwork focuses on the recovery of sediment cores from local lakes, while in-class labs emphasize physical, chemical, and paleontological analyses of the sediment cores. Prerequisite(s): any 200-level geology course. Not open to students who have received credit for GEO 311.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> M. Retelle.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="311"/><a name="GEO311"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 311. Quaternary Geology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Quaternary Period, representing the last 1.6 million years of geologic history, is characterized by extreme climatic fluctuations with effects ranging from globally synchronous glacier expansions to periods warmer than present. Records of the climatic fluctuations are contained in sediments on land and in the oceans and lakes and also in the stratigraphy of ice caps. This course examines various climate proxy records and the dating methods used to constrain them. Fieldwork focuses on the recovery of sediment cores from local lakes, while in-class labs emphasize physical, chemical, and paleontological analyses of the sediment cores. Prerequisite(s): any 200-level geology course. Not open to students who have received credit for GEO 310.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> M. Retelle.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="315"/><a name="GEO315"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 315. Glacial Geology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Glaciers, ice caps, and ice sheets are presently located in high-latitude and high-altitude areas of the globe. However, during the height of the last ice age, about 18,000 years ago, major ice sheets extended to mid-latitudes from the polar regions and to lower elevations in mountainous regions of low latitudes. Lectures investigate processes of modern glaciers, evidence for former extent, and the cause of climatic variability between glacial and interglacial periods. The laboratory introduces students to glaciogenic sediments, stratigraphic analysis, glacial landforms, and field mapping. Several one-day local field trips and one overnight field trip take students to sites in Maine and northern New England. Prerequisite(s): any 200-level geology course. <span class="crsaddmod"/>  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span>  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> M. Retelle.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="316"/><a name="GEO316"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 316. Glacial Geology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Glaciers, ice caps, and ice sheets are presently located in high-latitude and high-altitude areas of the globe. However, during the height of the last ice age, about 18,000 years ago, major ice sheets extended to mid-latitudes from the polar regions and to lower elevations in mountainous regions of low latitudes. Lectures investigate processes of modern glaciers, evidence for former extent, and the cause of climatic variability between glacial and interglacial periods. The in-class labs introduce students to glaciogenic sediments, stratigraphic analysis, glacial landforms, and field mapping. Several one-day local field trips and one overnight field trip take students to sites in Maine and northern New England. Prerequisite(s): any 200-level geology course.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span>  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> M. Retelle.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="326"/><a name="GEO326"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 326. Igneous Petrology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Igneous processes have led to the formation of the Earth's core and have since recorded the crustal evolution of the planet. This course emphasizes the application of physical chemistry to the understanding of crystallization processes in magmas and the importance of melt physical properties for the emplacement of magma, the eruption of lava, and the textural evolution of igneous rocks. Key topics include the formation of magmas in different tectonic settings, the physical processes of volcanism, and fluid flow within the Earth. Laboratory work emphasizes petrologic modeling, the interpretation of igneous textures in hand sample and thin section, and field studies of igneous localities in Maine. Prerequisite(s): GEO 223. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> G. Robert.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="340"/><a name="GEO340"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 340. Stable Isotope Geochemistry/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The stable isotope composition of modern and ancient waters and biological materials has revolutionized our understanding of biogeochemical cycling at the Earth's surface and of environmental change. This course focuses on the theory and applications of stable isotope fractionation in water and biological materials for modern and past environmental research. The laboratory includes fieldwork within the Androscoggin River watershed and the Maine coast and use of a stable isotope ratio mass spectrometer. Students are engaged in projects that may include tracking changes in carbon cycling in lakes, salt marshes, and trees through time, and documenting changes in energy flow in modern and ancient marine food webs. The interdisciplinary nature of the subject material lends itself well to upper-level students from a variety of science majors. Prerequisite(s): CHEM 107A and any 200-level geology course. Recommended background: GEO 240. Enrollment limited to 10.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> B. Johnson.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="341"/><a name="GEO341"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 341. Stable Isotope Geochemistry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The stable isotope composition of modern and ancient waters and biological materials has revolutionized our understanding of biogeochemical cycling at the Earth's surface and of environmental change. This course focuses on the theory and applications of stable isotope fractionation in water and biological materials for modern and past environmental research. The course may include fieldwork within the Androscoggin River watershed and the Maine coast and use of a stable isotope ratio mass spectrometer. Students are engaged in projects that may include tracking changes in carbon cycling in lakes, salt marshes, and trees through time, and documenting changes in energy flow in modern and ancient marine food webs. The interdisciplinary nature of the subject material lends itself well to upper-level students from a variety of science majors. Prerequisite(s): CHEM 107A and any 200-level geology course. Recommended background: GEO 240. Enrollment limited to 10.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> B. Johnson.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="GEO360"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365"/><a name="GEO365"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 365. Special Topics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A course reserved for a special topic selected by the department.  Instructor permission is required.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="391"/><a name="GEO391"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 391. Seminar in Appalachian Geology/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the Appalachian Mountain Belt. The purpose of the course is to understand the tectonic evolution of the Appalachian Mountains. Plate tectonic models that are particularly helpful are discussed in detail. Students are expected to conduct independent work and give oral and written reports. Fieldwork includes several day trips and an overnight traverse through the northern Appalachians of Vermont, New Hampshire, and Maine. Prerequisite(s): any 200-level geology course.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> J. Eusden.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="GEO457"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The thesis is a program of independent research conducted by the student, on a field and/or laboratory problem, under the direction of a faculty mentor. Seniors participate in the regularly scheduled weekly seminar. Such participation includes preparation of a thesis proposal and a thesis outline, timely submission of written results, and oral progress reports of thesis research. Students are responsible for scheduling individual meetings with their faculty committee. A public presentation and an oral defense are scheduled during the final week of the semester. Students conducting a one-semester thesis register for GEO 457 in the fall semester. Students conducting a two-semester thesis must register for both 457 and 458.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="GEO458"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc"><h4 class="crsname">Senior Thesis</h4>The thesis is a program of independent research conducted by the student, on a field and/or laboratory problem, under the direction of a faculty mentor. Seniors participate in the regularly scheduled weekly seminar. Such participation includes preparation of a thesis proposal and a thesis outline, timely submission of written results, and oral progress reports of thesis research. Students are responsible for scheduling individual meetings with their faculty committee. A public presentation and an oral defense are scheduled the during the final week of the winter semester. Students register for GEO 458 in the winter semester.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. M. Retelle.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s10"/><a name="GEOs10"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO s10. Tetons, Yellowstone, and Craters of the Moon: Geology of the Northern Rockies and Columbia Plateau.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on developing students&#8217; geologic field skills in variety of geologic settings in the Northern Rockies of Idaho, Wyoming, and Montana. The course includes two detailed mapping projects and regional geology studies of igneous, sedimentary, and metamorphic rocks with additional emphasis placed on structural and economic geology. Field locations include the Craters of the Moon lava field, Yellowstone National Park, and Grand Teton National Park. Two week-long mapping activities allow the students to learn and practice a variety of geological field methods culminating in a geologic map. For the regional geology studies, students synthesize the geological history of the Northern Rockies, prepare and present a field guide for specific geologic localities, and practice their observation skills. Economic geology is explored at the Berkeley Copper Mine in Butte, and the Imerys talc mine near Ennis, both in Montana. This course includes camping in tents, some overnights in dorms, and communal meals prepared by the group. Recommended background: one introductory level geology or cross-listed geology class. Enrollment limited to 16. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span> J. Eusden, G. Robert.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="ES/GEs21"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/GE s21. Field Studies in Geology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to field studies in geology. Three different geologic settings (bedrock geology, geomorphology, and hydrology) are the focus of three week-long field projects. Each project is followed by laboratory analysis and compilation of the field data in the form of maps, cross sections, and lab reports. Students learn how to map and analyze spatial datasets using mobile GIS field methods and ArcGIS techniques as well as methods in environmental sampling and modeling. Students examine exposures of bedrock on the Maine coast, glacial features in downeast Maine, and river systems in central Maine.  This course provide students with a basic toolkit for fieldwork in geology and environmental studies. Prerequisite(s): one 100-level geology course. Enrollment limited to 30. B. Johnson, J. Eusden.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s23"/><a name="GEOs23"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO s23. Melts, Glasses, and Magmas/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Earth cools as magma transports heat from its interior to the surface, sometimes resulting in spectacular volcanic eruptions. This course explores the factors that control magma behavior in various geologic systems by studying fossil magma chambers in Maine, performing hands-on experiments with food analogs and molten rock in the laboratory at Bates, and working with industrial glass in the studios of the Corning Museum of Glass in Corning, New York. Prerequisite(s): any 100-level chemistry, geology, or physics courses. Enrollment limited to 18.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> G. Robert.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s24"/><a name="GEOs24"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO s24. Geology of the Southwestern United States.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on developing geologic field method and mapping skills in a variety of southwestern United States settings. Students work in a variety of rock types and structural styles to complete several field projects. Locations for projects include extension complexes of Death Valley, California; Proterozoic basement rocks of New Mexico; and fold-and-thrust and rift structures in the Franklin Mountains of Texas and New Mexico. Students also explore the tectonic history and development of the North American Cordillera. This course includes a camping experience, with accommodations in tents, with communal meals prepared by the group. Prerequisite(s): one introductory geology course. Enrollment limited to 8. Instructor permission is required. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s31"/><a name="GEOs31"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO s31. Limnology and Paleolimnology of Lakes in Northern New England/Lab.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course studies the present and past environmental conditions of lake basins in northern New England. Modern conditions such as thermal and chemical stratification and hydrologic and sedimentary inputs are monitored in local watersheds. Cores and acoustic profiles of bottom sediments are obtained to study the long-term climatic history. The course is project-oriented with several off campus, multi-day field trips. Students collect field data, perform laboratory analysis of core and water samples, and prepare a final report. Participants must be able to swim. Prerequisite(s): one of the following: GEO 103, 104, 107, or 109. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 12. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> M. Retelle.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s36"/><a name="GEOs36"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO s36. Coastal Hazards.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Humans have always lived along the world's coastlines. Constantly changing coastal landscapes, combined with increases in coastal populations, present a unique and challenging set of pressures for people living at the boundary between land and sea. In this course, students explore coastal processes (e.g., erosion, sea level rise, storm events, and tsunamis) and coastal features (e.g., beaches, salt marshes, and barrier islands) in a variety of geological settings. The first half of the course is spent studying sites in Maine; the second half of the course may be spent studying coastlines in Iceland and the Netherlands, two places where people have taken extreme measures to live by the sea and mitigate coastal hazards. Prerequisite(s): Any 100-level geology course  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 14.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> B. Johnson.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C063">Hazards in Nature (C063)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s39"/><a name="GEOs39"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO s39. Geology of the Maine Coast by Sea Kayak.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Six hundred million years of geologic history are preserved in the spectacular rock exposures of the Maine coast. Students learn how to interpret this geologic history by completing four one-week bedrock mapping projects of coastal exposures on offshore islands. Islands in Casco Bay, Penobscot Bay, and Acadia National Park are used as both base camps and field sites for these projects. Students travel to and from these islands in sea kayaks. Students are trained in kayaking techniques, sea kayak rescue and safety, and low-impact camping by a certified kayak instructor who stays with the group for the entire Short Term. No previous kayaking experience is necessary. Participants must be able to swim. Prerequisite(s): any 100-level geology course. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 10.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[L]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> J. Eusden.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C068">Environment, Place, History (C068)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C058">Field Studies: Natural Science (C058)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C007">The Geosphere (C007)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="GEOs50"/><h4 class="crsname">GEO s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>

               