<div class="Course"><a name="165"/><a name="INDS165"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 165. African American Philosophers.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on how African American philosophers confront and address philosophical problems. Students consider the relationship between the black experience and traditional themes in Western philosophy. Attention is also given to the motivations and context sustaining African American philosophers. Recommended background: African American Studies 140A or African American Studies/American Cultural Studies 119. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and philosophy.  Not open to students who have received credit for African American Studies 165. Enrollment limited to 40. Offered with varying frequency. J. McClendon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="208"/><a name="INDS208"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 208. Introduction to Medieval Archeology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The Middle Ages were a time of major cultural changes that laid the groundwork for Northwest Europe's emergence as a global center of political and economic power in more recent centuries. However, many aspects of life in the period from 1000 to 1500 <span class="smcaps">C.E.</span> were unrecorded in contemporary documents and art, and archeology has become an important tool for recovering that information. This course introduces the interdisciplinary methods and the findings of archeological studies of topics including medieval urban and rural lifeways, health, commerce, religion, social hierarchy, warfare, and the effects of global climate change. Cross-listed in anthropology, classical and medieval studies, environmental studies, and history. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall 2005.</span> Open to first-year students. (Premodern.) G. Bigelow.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="212"/><a name="INDS212"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 212. Writing/Righting Chinese Women.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is a survey of major writings by Chinese women, from Ban Zhao (40-120 <span class="smcaps">C.E.</span>), whose <span class="cite">nujie</span> is considered the early canon of female moral virtues, to the most recent novels by women writers who pride themselves in their audacity to write about their bodies. The course emphasizes ways women writers across time have countered various masculine constructions of silenced femininity and developed their own literary sensibility, especially in the context of China's modern development. Literary works explore topics that resonate with women's experience such as family, marriage, gender identity, sexuality, revolution, nation. and modernity. Conducted in English. Cross-listed in women and gender studies, Asian studies and Chinese. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2007.</span> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. H. Su.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="215"/><a name="INDS215"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 215. African American Culture through Sports.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Sports in African American life have served in a variety of ways to offer a means for social, economic, cultural, and even political    advancement. This unit examines how sports have historically formed and contemporaneously shape   the contours of African  American culture. Particular attention is given to such questions as the ethical dimension of segregation, the locus of gender equity, cultural imgages, and their political effects for African American athletes and the African American community. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies and philosophy. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2005.</span> Not open to students who have received credit for Interdisciplinary Studies s18. Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. J. McClendon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="218"/><a name="INDS218"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 218. <span class="cite">Afroambiente</span>: Writing A Black Environment.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course studies the response of Black writers and intellectuals of the Spanish-speaking world to issues related to the natural environment. In three countries, Ecuador, Puerto Rico, and Equatorial Guinea, modernity has brought serious challenges to notions of economic progress, human rights, national sovereignty, as well as individual and communal identity. Course materials include written texts from local newspapers, magazines, as well as other sources of information, such as internet sites that discuss issues related to the environment and the arts. Recommended background: Spanish 207 or 208. Cross-listed in African American studies, environmental studies, and Spanish. Conducted in Spanish. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall 2005.</span> Not open to students who have received credit for Interdisciplinary Studies s21. Open to first-year students. Offered with varying frequency. B. Fra-Molinero.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="219"/><a name="INDS219"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 219. Environmental Archeology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Over the past two hundred years archeologists and scientists and humanists in many disciplines have worked together in researching the interactions of past human populations with the physical world, including plants, animals, landscapes, and climates. This course outlines the methods and theories used by archeologists, geologists, biologists, physicists, chemists, and historians in reconstructing past economies and ecologies in diverse areas of the globe. The course also discusses how archeology contributes to our understanding of contemporary environmental issues such as rapid climate change, shrinking biodiversity, and sustainable use of resources. Cross-listed in environmental studies, anthropology and history. Recommended background: Anthropology 103. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Winter 2006.</span> Open to first-year students. Normally offered every year. G. Bigelow.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="228"/><a name="INDS228"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 228. Caring for Creation: Physics, Religion, and the Environment.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course considers scientific and religious accounts of the origin of the universe, examines the relations between these accounts, and explores the way they shape our deepest attitudes toward the natural world. Topics of discussion include the biblical creation stories, contemporary scientific cosmology, the interplay between these scientific and religious ideas, and the roles they both can play in forming a response to environmental problems. Cross-listed in environmental studies, physics, and religion.  Not open to students who have received credit for Environmental Studies 228, Physics 228, or Religion 228. Enrollment limited to 40. Offered with varying frequency. J. Smedley, T. Tracy.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="235"/><a name="INDS235"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 235. The Politics of Pleasure and Desire: Women's Independent and Third Cinema and Video from the African Diaspora.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines independent and Third cinema, and some written texts by women of African descent using contemporary theories of female pleasure and desire. By viewing and reading these cultural productions drawn from "high" and "low" culture in the light of a variety of film theories (i.e., feminist, womanist/black feminist, postcolonial, diasporic) as well as race-critical, feminist, and cultural theories, students explore the "textual" strategies that construct black female representations, and Afra-diasporic authors/directors and audiences as subjects and as agents of political change. Recommended background: any of the following: African American Studies 140A, African American Studies/Theater 225, African American Studies/Women and Gender Studies 201, Theater 102 or 110. Cross-listed in African American studies, rhetoric, and women and gender studies. Open to first-year students. Normally offered every other year. S. Houchins.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="236"/><a name="INDS236"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 236. The Literatures of Women of the African Diaspora.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses primarily on the literatures of black women from Africa, the Caribbean, the United Kingdom, and Canada, but may examine some works from the United States. All of the texts are in English; some are from the Anglophone diaspora and others are translations from the Lusophone, Hispanophone, and Francophone black world. Students are introduced to historical, feminist, Pan-African, Marxist, and postcolonial critical approaches to analyze this richly diverse yet culturally and politically related body of work. Topics include slavery and migrations, the socioeconomic contexts of prolonged exile from the African continent, liberation struggles on the continent and in the diaspora, as well as the roles of women in these movements. Recommended background: any of the following: African American Studies 140A, African American Studies/Women and Gender Studies 201, African American Studies/Anthropology 251, African American Studies/English 253, Anthropology 228, or Political Science 235. Cross-listed in African American studies, English, and women and gender studies. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every year. S. Houchins.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="239"/><a name="INDS239"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 239. Black Women in Music.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Angela Davis states, "Black people were able to create with their music an aesthetic community of resistance, which in turn encouraged and nurtured a political community of active struggle for freedom." This course examines the role of black women as critics, composers, and performers who challenge externally defined controlling images. Topics include: black women in the music industry; black women in music of the African diaspora; and black women as rappers, jazz innovators, and musicians in the classical and gospel traditions. Cross-listed in African American studies, music, and women and gender studies. Not open to students who have received credit for African American Studies 239, Music 239, or Women's Studies 239. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="240"/><a name="INDS240"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 240. Theory and Method in African American Studies.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course addresses the relationship between political culture and cultural politics within African American studies. Particular attention is paid to the contending theories of cultural criticism. Cornel West, Molefi Asante, Patricia Hill Collins, Angela Davis, bell hooks, Maramba Ani, and Henry Louis Gates Jr. are some of the theorists under review. Recommended background: African American Studies/American Cultural Studies 119 or significant work in political science, American cultural studies, or African American studies. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and philosophy.  Not open to students who have received credit for American Cultural Studies 240 or Political Science 240. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 50. Offered with varying frequency. J. McClendon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="250"/><a name="INDS250"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 250. Interdisciplinary Studies: Methods and Modes of Inquiry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Interdisciplinarity involves more than a meeting of disciplines. Practitioners stretch methodological norms and reach across disciplinary boundaries. Through examination of a single topic, this course introduces students to interdisciplinary methods of analysis. Students examine what practitioners actually do and work to become practitioners themselves. Prerequisite(s): African American Studies 140A or Women and Gender Studies 100, and one other course in African American studies, American cultural studies, or women and gender studies. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and women and gender studies. Not open to students who have received credit for African American Studies 250, American Cultural Studies 250, or Women's Studies 250. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every year. R. Herzig.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="260"/><a name="INDS260"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 260. United States Latina/Chicana Writings.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course rests on two conceptual underpinnings: Gloria Anzald&#250;a's <span class="em">Neueva Mestiza</span>, and the more recent <span class="em">"U.S. Pan-latinidad"</span> postulated by the Latina Feminist Group. The literary and theoretical production of Chicanas and Latinas is examined through these lenses. Particular attention is given to developing a working knowledge of the key historical and cultural discourses engaged by these writings and the various contemporary United States Latina and Chicana positionalities vis-&#224;-vis popular ethnic representations. The course also examines the function given to marketable cultural productions depending on the different agents involved. Cross-listed in American cultural studies, Spanish, and women and gender studies. Open to first-year students. Offered with varying frequency. C. Aburto Guzm&#225;n.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="262"/><a name="INDS262"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 262. Ethnomusicology: African Diaspora.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This introductory course is a survey of key concepts, problems, and perspectives in ethnomusicological theory drawing upon the African diaspora as a cross-cultural framework. This course focuses on the social, political, and intellectual forces of African culture that contributed to the growth of ethnomusicology from the late nineteenth century to the present. Cross-listed in African American studies, anthropology, and music.  Not open to students who have received credit for African American Studies 262, Anthropology 262, or Music 262. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every other year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="291"/><a name="INDS291"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 291. Exhibiting Cultures.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the politics of exhibiting cultures. Each week students analyze specific exhibitions of cultural artifacts, visual culture, and the cultural body as a means to evaluate the larger issues surrounding such displays. These include issues of race, colonialism, postcolonialism, and curatorial authority in relation to the politics of exhibiting cultures. A field trip to analyze an exhibition is a critical part of the students' experience in the course. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and art and visual culture. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="325"/><a name="INDS325"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 325. Black Feminist Literary Theory and Practice.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar examines literary theories that address the representation and construction of race, gender, and sexuality, particularly, but not exclusively, theories formulated and articulated by Afra-diasporic women such as Spillers, Ogunyemi, Henderson, Valerie Smith, McDowell, Busia, Lubiano, and Davies. Students not only analyze theoretical essays, but they use the theories as lenses through which to explore literary productions of women writers of Africa and the African diaspora in Europe and in the Americas, including Philip, Dangarembga, Morrison, Herron, Gayle Jones, Head, Cond&#233;, Brodber, Brand, Merle Collins, and Harriet Wilson. Prerequisite(s): African American Studies 140, 235, African American Studies/English 121X, 212, African American Studies/Women and Gender Studies 201, English 250, 294, 295, English/Women and Gender Studies 121G. Cross-listed in African American studies, English, and women and gender studies. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every other year. S. Houchins.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="339"/><a name="INDS339"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 339. Africana Thought and Practice.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar examines in depth a broad range of black thought. Students consider the various philosophical problems and the theoretical issues and practical solutions offered by such scholar/activists as W. E. B. Du Bois, Marcus Garvey, Kwame Nkrumah, Claudia Jones, C. L. R. James, Leopold Senghor, Amilcar Cabrah, Charlotta Bass, Lucy Parsons, Walter Rodney, and Frantz Fanon. Recommended background: a course on the Africana world, or a course in philosophy or political theory. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and philosophy. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. J. McClendon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="INDS457"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 457. Interdisciplinary Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Independent study and writing of a major research paper in the area of the student's interdisciplinary major, supervised by an appropriate faculty member. Students register for Interdisciplinary Senior Thesis 457 in the fall semester. Interdisciplinary majors writing an honors thesis register for both Interdisciplinary Thesis 457 and 458.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457, 458"/><a name="INDS457, 458"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 457, 458. Interdisciplinary Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Independent study and writing of a major research paper in the area of the student's interdisciplinary major, supervised by an appropriate faculty member. Students register for Interdisciplinary Senior Thesis 457 in the fall semester. Interdisciplinary majors writing an honors thesis register for both Interdisciplinary Thesis 457 and 458.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="INDS458"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 458. Interdisciplinary Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Independent study and writing of a major research paper in the area of the student's interdisciplinary major, supervised by an appropriate faculty member. Students register for Interdisciplinary Senior Thesis 458 in the winter semester. Interdisciplinary majors writing an honors thesis register for both Interdisciplinary Thesis 457 and 458.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s18"/><a name="INDSs18"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS s18. African American Culture through Sports.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Sports in African American life have served in a variety of ways to offer a means for social, economic, cultural, and even political advancement. This unit examines how sports have historically formed and contemporaneously shape the contours of African American culture. Particular attention is given to such questions as segregation, gender equity, cultural images, and their political effects for African American athletes and the black community. In addition to the required and recommended readings, lectures, and discussions, videos and films are central to the teaching and learning process. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and philosophy.  Not open to students who have received credit for American Cultural Studies s18, Interdisciplinary Studies 215, or Political Science s18. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Offered with varying frequency. J. McClendon.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="INDSs21"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS s21. Writing a Black Environment.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This unit studies the response of black writers and intellectuals of the Spanish-speaking world to issues related to the natural environment. In countries and regions of Afro-Hispanic majority the presence of the oil industry has brought serious challenges to notions of economic progress, human rights, and national sovereignty, as well as individual and communal identity. Writers from Esmeraldas, Ecuador, and Equatorial Guinea chronicle the contradictory discourses present in their societies between modernity, tradition, the idea of progress, and the degradation of the ecosystem. Recommended background: Spanish 202. Cross-listed in African American studies, environmental studies, and Spanish.  Not open to students who have received credit for African American Studies s21, Environmental Studies s21, or Spanish s21. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. B. Fra-Molinero.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s25"/><a name="INDSs25"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS s25. Black Terror.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This unit explores Gothic fiction and film, works that create an atmosphere of brooding and unknown terror and represent race and gender as sources of dread, of "the Horror. The Horror" Students read works by such authors as Sheridan Le Fanu, Bram Stoker, Toni Morrison, Nalo Hopkinson, Tananarive Due, Thulani Davis, Reginald McKnight, Jean Rhys, and Harriet Wilson. The films include <span class="cite">The Mark of Lillith</span>, <span class="cite">Dracula</span>, <span class="cite">Ganga and Hess</span>, <span class="cite">The Hunger</span>, and <span class="cite">Carmilla</span>. Using psychoanalytic, film, race, queer, and gender theories as tools, students excavate deeply embedded discourses of race, sex, and sexuality. Recommended background: any of the following: African American Studies/Theater 225, African American Studies/Theater 226, or Theater 102. Cross-listed in African American studies, rhetoric, and women and gender studies. Offered with varying frequency. S. Houchins.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s26"/><a name="INDSs26"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS s26. Reading in the Greek New Testament.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Intensive introduction to New Testament Greek. Students begin reading in the Gospel of John, while studying the Koine, or commonly spoken Greek language of late classical and early Christian times. No previous knowledge of Greek is assumed. Cross-listed in classical and medieval studies, Greek, and religion.  Not open to students who have received credit for Classical and Medieval Studies s26, Greek s26, or Religion s26. Enrollment limited to 8. Offered with varying frequency. R. Allison.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s27"/><a name="INDSs27"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS s27. The Viking World: Archeology and Ethnohistory.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">When the Vikings poured out of their Scandinavian homelands they transformed the early medieval world. Tales of their piracy and raiding dominate the written records of the time, but a growing volume of archeological and environmental evidence is shedding new light on the Vikings as explorers, founders of towns, traders, artisans, and specialists in northern agriculture and fishing. This unit emphasizes the findings of archeology and studies of Icelandic sagas in outlining the lifeways, historical impacts, and differing fates of the Scandinavian peoples from 800-1100 <span class="smcaps">C.E.</span> Cross-listed in anthropology, classical and medieval studies, and history. <span class="crsaddmod">New unit beginning Short Term  2005.</span> (Premodern.) Offered with varying frequency. G. Bigelow.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s28"/><a name="INDSs28"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS s28. Shetland Islands: Archeological Field Course.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The main element of this unit is the excavation of a late medieval/early modern farmstead at Brow, Shetland (Scotland). Early settlement in Shetland was on the margin of successful medieval colonization of the North Atlantic. The Brow site is a revealing
"laboratory" in which to explore the interaction of climate change and human settlement in a fragile coastal zone. A series of field trips in mainland Scotland place the Brow excavation in the wider context of settlement, environment,archeology and history ofScotland and the North Atlantic. Recommended background: Prior courses in Medieval history or archaeology. Cross-listed in history, environmental studies and classical and medieval studies. Not open to seniors. <span class="crsaddmod">New Course beginning Short Term 2006.</span> Enrollment limited to 10. Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. M. Jones.<br/></span></div>

               