<div class="Course"><a name="290"/><a name="AA/LS290"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/LS 290. The Afro-Hispanic Diaspora.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The 500-year presence of Africans and their descendants in the Spanish-speaking world has produced a significant body of literature by blacks and about blacks. Spanish America was the main destination of the African diaspora. Afro-Hispanic writers attest to the struggle for freedom and the abolition of slavery. Their literature shows how the participation of blacks in the wars of Latin American independence was a struggle for their emancipation. Afro-Hispanic writers in Spain, the Americas, and Africa use their art and ideas to address the postnational migrations of the twenty-first century, a diaspora that has not ceased. Recommended background: AAS 100.  <span class="crsaddmod">Course renumbered to INDS 290 beginning Fall 2015.</span> Open to first-year students. B. Fra-Molinero.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C016">Bridging <span class="em">El Atl&#225;ntico</span> (C016)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C059">Colonialism (C059)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C072">Latin American Studies (C072)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="290"/><a name="INDS290"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 290. The Afro-Hispanic Diaspora.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The 500-year presence of Africans and their descendants in the Spanish-speaking world has produced a significant body of literature by blacks and about blacks. Spanish America was the main destination of the African diaspora. Afro-Hispanic writers attest to the struggle for freedom and the abolition of slavery. Their literature shows how the participation of blacks in the wars of Latin American independence was a struggle for their emancipation. Afro-Hispanic writers in Spain, the Americas, and Africa use their art and ideas to address the postnational migrations of the twenty-first century, a diaspora that has not ceased. Recommended background: AAS 100. Cross-listed in African American studies, Latin American studies and Spanish. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall 2015 (renumbered from AA/LS 290).</span> Open to first-year students. B. Fra-Molinero.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C016">Bridging <span class="em">El Atl&#225;ntico</span> (C016)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C059">Colonialism (C059)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C072">Latin American Studies (C072)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=LAS">Latin American Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="302"/><a name="INDS302"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 302. Building a Room of Her Own: Writing the Caribbean Woman in Contemporary Contexts.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores feminine and feminist writing in the Hispanophone Caribbean with an emphasis on the body as a site of pleasure, race as social construct, and embodied experience and narrative as liberatory practice. Students engage the novel, testimonial literature, and short story to read the articulation of queer, meztiza, and black female subjectivities. This course acknowledges women authors from the circum-Caribbean region, both insular and continental, as wide-ranging as Puerto Rico, Colombia, Haiti/Dominican Republic, and Panama. Prerequisite(s): SPAN 216 and 230. Cross-listed in African American studies, Latin American studies, Spanish, and women and gender studies. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall 2015.</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every other year. M. Pettway.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="LAS360"/><h4 class="crsname">LAS 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester. Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="374"/><a name="INDS374"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 374. Chanting Down Babylon: Caribbean Popular Cultural Insurgency .</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Caribbean popular culture exerts influence on the world stage disproportionate to the region's size. This course examines the politics and creolized development of Caribbean popular culture through some of its best-known modes of expression such as music, the Trinidad Carnival, and the game of cricket. Placing these cultural forms in their historical and social contexts reveals their oppositional, dissenting qualities. By applying various critical analytical lenses, however, including gender and sexuality, ethnicity, nationalism, and transnationalism, the course also considers certain conservative undercurrents of these cultural formations. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, anthropology, and Latin American studies. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Fall 2015</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every other year. C. Carnegie.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="LAS457"/><h4 class="crsname">LAS 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An in-depth independent study of Latin America related to the student's major concentration. Majors register for LAS 457 in the fall semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for LAS 457 in the fall semester and LAS 458 in the winter semester.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="LAS458"/><h4 class="crsname">LAS 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An in-depth independent study of Latin America related to the student's major concentration. Majors register for LAS 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for LAS 457 in the fall semester and LAS 458 in the winter semester.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="LS/SPs21"/><h4 class="crsname">LS/SP s21. Human Rights and Social Art in Latin America: The Case of Nogales, Mexico.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on the social dynamics that generate social art committed to change in Latin America. Students examine three settings in which artists utilize the arts to generate aesthetic and production models that represent the "uniqueness of place." During ten days off-campus, students work with artists who engage technology to raise consciousness about the "needs of place."  In Nogales, Mexico, students consider human rights discourses that address migrants' dislocation. They also work with volunteers, hike the desert, and visit shelters to contextualize the social and natural environments. Prerequisite(s): SPAN 207. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. One-time offering. C. Aburto Guzm&#225;n.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1097&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C089">Spanish in Tarragona (C089)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s34"/><a name="INDSs34"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS s34. Place, Community, and Transformation: Kingston, Jamaica.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course evaluates the feasibility of green space development in Kingston, Jamaica, a city marked by class disparities, political polarization, and the impoverishing impact of neoliberal economic policies. Through assigned texts students explore the city's physical and demographic development under colonial and postcolonial rule. They examine development initiatives, challenges, and failures through guest lectures and tours led by practicing architects, engineers, planners, environmentalists, and community workers. Students undertake ethnographic research in neighborhoods, parks, and public spaces on the use of outdoor recreational space, perceived needs, and food gardening practices to gather data that might guide future community-building green initiatives. Cross-listed in African American studies, anthropology, environmental studies, and Latin American studies. <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2015.</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Community-Engaged Learning.) Normally offered every other year. C. Carnegie.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="LASs50"/><h4 class="crsname">LAS s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>

               