<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="LAS360"/><h4 class="crsname">LAS 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester. Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="LAS457"/><h4 class="crsname">LAS 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An in-depth independent study of Latin America related to the student's major concentration. Majors register for LAS 457 in the fall semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for LAS 457 in the fall semester and LAS 458 in the winter semester.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="LAS458"/><h4 class="crsname">LAS 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An in-depth independent study of Latin America related to the student's major concentration. Majors register for LAS 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for LAS 457 in the fall semester and LAS 458 in the winter semester.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="LS/SPs21"/><h4 class="crsname">LS/SP s21. Human Rights and Social Art in Latin America: The Case of Nogales, Mexico.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on the social dynamics that generate social art committed to change in Latin America. Students examine three settings in which artists utilize the arts to generate aesthetic and production models that represent the "uniqueness of place." During ten days off-campus, students work with artists who engage technology to raise consciousness about the "needs of place."  In Nogales, Mexico, students consider human rights discourses that address migrants' dislocation. They also work with volunteers, hike the desert, and visit shelters to contextualize the social and natural environments. Prerequisite(s): SPAN 207.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Short Term 2014.</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. One-time offering. C. Aburto Guzm&#225;n.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1000&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C089">Spanish in Tarragona (C089)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="LASs50"/><h4 class="crsname">LAS s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>

               