<div class="Course"><a name="101"/><a name="MATH101"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 101. Working with Data.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Techniques for analyzing data are described in ordinary English without emphasis on mathematical formulas. The course focuses on graphical and descriptive techniques for summarizing data, design of experiments, sampling, analyzing relationships, statistical models, and statistical inference. Applications are drawn from everyday life: drug testing, legal discrimination cases, and public opinion polling. Not open to students who have received credit for BIO 244, ECON 250 or 255, ENVR 181, MATH 215 or 315, PLTC 218, PSYC 218, or SOC 305.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> S. Balcomb.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="102"/><a name="MATH102"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 102. Mathematics across the Sciences.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course makes connections between the mathematics learned in math class and the mathematics used in several science courses. For example, how does the formula for the equation of a line relate to a set of data collected in physics, chemistry, biology, geology, or environmental studies? Students who wish to apply their mathematical knowledge to better understand scientific problems and students who want to strengthen their core mathematical skills are ideally suited to take this course. Not open to students who have received credit for MATH 106 or higher.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> M. Greer.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="105"/><a name="MATH105"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 105. Calculus I.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">While the word <span class="em">calculus</span> originally meant any method of calculating, it has come to refer more specifically to the fundamental ideas of differentiation and integration that were first developed in the seventeenth century. The subject's early development was intimately connected with understanding rates of change within the context of the physical sciences. Since then, it has proven to be widely applicable throughout the natural sciences and some social sciences, as well as crucial to the development of most modern technology. This course develops the key notions of derivatives and integrals and their interrelationship, as well as applications. An emphasis is placed on conceptual understanding and interpretation, as well as on computational skills. Graphing calculators are used in the course. Students are required to attend five additional 50-minute laboratory sessions at times to be arranged. Students must read the <a href="http://www.bates.edu/mathematics/academics/selecting-first-math-course/">mathematics department calculus questions page </a>before registering. Prior calculus work generally excludes students from this course. Not open to students who have received equivalent course credit through AP, IB, or A-Level examination scores. Successful completion of MATH 106 or 206 fulfills all Bates requirements for MATH 105. Not open to students who have received credit for MATH 206.  <span class="crsaddmod"/>

 Enrollment limited to 25 per section.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="106"/><a name="MATH106"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 106. Calculus II.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A continuation of Calculus I. Further techniques of integration, both symbolic and numerical, are studied. The course then treats applications of integration to problems drawn from fields such as physics, biology, chemistry, economics, and probability. Differential equations and their applications are also introduced, as well as approximation techniques and Taylor series. Graphing calculators are used in the course. Students are required to attend approximately six additional 50-minute laboratory sessions at times to be arranged. Recommended background: MATH 105 or equivalent. Students must read the <a href="http://bates.edu/mathematics/academics/selecting-first-math-course/">mathematics department calculus questions page </a>before registering. Not open to students who have received equivalent course credit through AP, IB, or A-Level examination scores. Successful completion of MATH 106 fulfills all Bates requirements for MATH 105. Successful completion of MATH 206 fulfills all Bates requirements for MATH 106. Not open to students who have received credit for MATH 206.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 25 per section.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="110"/><a name="MATH110"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 110. Great Ideas in Mathematics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Is mathematics composed of impenetrable formulas to be memorized, a series of insurmountable cliffs to be scaled? Are there individuals who can think logically and creatively, but never "do math"? In this course, students are asked to use their imagination to grapple with challenging mathematical concepts. The process enables them to master techniques of effective thinking, experience the joy of discovering new ideas, and feel the power of figuring out things on their own. Together they contemplate some of the greatest and most intriguing creations of human thought, from Pythagoras to the fourth dimension, from chaos to symmetry. Not open to students who have received credit for ECON 250 or 255 or any math course numbered 200 or above.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 40.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="205"/><a name="MATH205"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 205. Linear Algebra.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Vectors and matrices are introduced as devices for the solution of systems of linear equations with many variables. Although these objects can be viewed simply as algebraic tools, they are better understood by applying geometric insight from two and three dimensions. This leads to an understanding of higher dimensional spaces and to the abstract concept of a vector space. Other topics include orthogonality, linear transformations, determinants, and eigenvectors. This course should be particularly useful to students majoring in any of the natural sciences or economics. Prerequisite(s): MATH 105 or 106. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25 per section. Normally offered every semester. K. Ott, S. Ross, Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="206"/><a name="MATH206"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 206. Multivariable Calculus.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course extends the ideas of Calculus I and II to deal with functions of more than one variable. While calculations make straightforward use of the techniques of single-variable calculus, more effort must be spent in developing a conceptual framework for understanding curves and surfaces in higher-dimensional spaces. Topics include partial derivatives, derivatives of vector-valued functions, vector fields, integration over regions in the plane and three-space, and integration on curves and surfaces. Prerequisite(s): MATH 106. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every semester. M. Montgomery.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="214"/><a name="MATH214"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 214. Probability.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Probability theory is the foundation on which statistical data analysis depends. This course together with its sequel, MATH 215, covers topics in mathematical statistics. Both courses are recommended for math majors with an interest in applied mathematics and for students in other disciplines, such as psychology and economics, who wish to learn about some of the mathematical theory underlying the methodology used in their fields. Prerequisite(s): MATH 206. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every year. G. Coulombe.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="215"/><a name="MATH215"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 215. Statistics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The sequel to MATH 214. This course explores inferential methods in statistics. Topics may include sampling distributions, point and interval estimation, hypothesis testing, analysis of variance, and linear regression. While applications are discussed, considerable emphasis is placed on the mathematical theory of statistics. Prerequisite(s): MATH 214. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> G. Coulombe.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="219"/><a name="MATH219"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 219. Differential Equations.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A differential equation is a relationship between a function and its derivatives. Many real-world situations can be modeled using these relationships. This course is a blend of the mathematical theory behind differential equations and their applications. The emphasis is on first- and second-order linear equations. Topics include existence and uniqueness of solutions, graphical approaches, numerical methods, and applications such as population modeling and mechanical vibrations. Prerequisite(s): MATH 205 and 206. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every year. S. Ross.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="225"/><a name="MATH225"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 225. Number Theory.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The theory of numbers is concerned with the properties of the integers, one of the most basic mathematical sets. Seemingly naive questions of number theory stimulated much of the development of modern mathematics and still provide rich opportunities for investigation. Topics include classical ones such as primality, congruences, quadratic reciprocity, and Diophantine equations, as well as more recent applications to cryptography. Additional topics such as computational methods, elliptic curves, or an introduction to analytic methods may be included. Prerequisite(s): MATH 205. Not open to students who have received credit for MATH s45N. Enrollment limited to 30. M. Montgomery.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="228"/><a name="MATH228"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 228. Mathematics and Music.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores how mathematics has been used to describe, analyze, and create music. It draws on a wide variety of mathematical techniques and treats an equally wide variety of musical topics, including rhythm, tuning systems, change-ringing, serial and aleatoric composition, and contradances. No musical background is required. Prerequisite(s): MATH 205 and 206. Enrollment limited to 30. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C005">Sound (C005)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="255"/><a name="MATH255"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 255. Topics in Mathematical Modeling.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Mathematical modeling is a tool used by natural and social scientists, including physicists, biologists, engineers, economists, and political scientists. Mathematical models use the language of mathematics to describe and analyze complex systems. They extract the essential features of real world phenomena and represent the system in one or more mathematical forms. These abstract structures may include differential equations, dynamical systems, statistical models, and game-theoretic models, among others.  <span class="crsaddmod"/>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every year.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="255A"/><a name="BI/MA255A"/><h4 class="crsname">BI/MA 255A. Mathematical Models in Biology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Mathematical models are increasingly important throughout the life sciences. This course provides an introduction to a variety of models in biology, with concrete examples chosen from biological and medical fields. Students work both theoretically and with computer software to analyze models, compute numerical results, and visualize outcomes. Prerequisite(s): MATH 205. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="255B"/><a name="MATH255B"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 255B. Mathematical Modeling.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course uses mathematical techniques to study the behavior of real-world processes such as weather or population growth. Often this involves learning enough about that process to set up a corresponding system of equations of some kind the solutions of which can inform us about the behavior of process over time. A model can be used to predict future behavior and help us understand the extent to which changes in various elements of the process may affect that future. Finding solutions of the equations by analytic techniques, graphs, numerical methods, computers or some combination, and interpreting the results and their worthiness, are all part of the art of modeling. Prerequisite(s): MATH 205 and 206. Enrollment limited to 30. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="255D"/><a name="MATH255D"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 255D. Mathematical Modeling with Monte Carlo Methods.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces mathematical modeling using Monte Carlo methods. Applications are drawn from the natural and social sciences, engineering, and mathematics. The course covers several Monte Carlo methods and students learn to write sample simulation problems using Matlab. The course also covers important ideas from probability theory needed to understand Monte Carlo methods. Prerequisite(s): MATH 205 and 206. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> H. Boateng.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="255E"/><a name="MA/PH255E"/><h4 class="crsname">MA/PH 255E. Modeling Nature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A model is a simplified description of a system in mathematical and/or conceptual terms. Models help us understand how systems work and behave. The goals of this course are threefold: building models of natural systems, exploring their underlying mathematical structures and similarities, and simulating them with computers. Concepts acquired from simple systems in physics are applied to more complex systems in areas of biology, environment, climate, and social dynamics. Prerequisite(s): MATH 105 or 106 and PHYS 107.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[S]</span>  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> Normally offered every year. R. Saha.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C056">Physics of the Large and Small (C056)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="295"/><a name="MATH295"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 295. Sophomore-Junior Seminar.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">With varying subject matter, this writing-attentive seminar addresses both the oral and written communication of mathematics. The seminar focuses on understanding why rigor is necessary and what constitutes effective communication of mathematical ideas to different audiences. Students practice peer editing and peer reviewing, and learn how to write effective grant and thesis proposals. Prerequisite(s): MATH s21.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Normally offered every year.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="301"/><a name="MATH301"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 301. Real Analysis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to the foundations of mathematical analysis, this course presents a rigorous treatment of fundamental concepts such as limits, continuity, differentiation, and integration. Elements of the topology of the real numbers are also covered. Prerequisite(s): MATH 205, 206, and s21. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="305"/><a name="MATH305"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 305. Applied Partial Differential Equations with Boundary Value Problems.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Partial differential equations (PDEs) arise in several fields of study in the natural and social sciences. This course provides an introduction to the theory and applications of partial differential equations. Students learn solution techniques and qualitative analysis for linear partial differential equations including initial and boundary value problems for second-order linear partial differential equations. Prerequisite(s): MATH 219. Enrollment limited to 25.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> H. Boateng.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="308"/><a name="MATH308"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 308. Complex Analysis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course extends the concepts of calculus to deal with functions whose variables and values are complex numbers. Instead of producing new complications, this leads to a theory that is not only more aesthetically pleasing, but is also more powerful. The course should be valuable to those interested in pure mathematics as well as those who need additional computational tools for physics or engineering. Topics include the geometry of complex numbers, differentiation and integration, representation of functions by integrals and power series, and the calculus of residues. Prerequisite(s): MATH 205 and 206. Enrollment limited to 25. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="309"/><a name="MATH309"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 309. Abstract Algebra I.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to basic algebraic structures common throughout mathematics. These may include the integers and their arithmetic, modular arithmetic, rings, polynomial rings, ideals, quotient rings, fields, and groups. Prerequisite(s): MATH 205 and s21. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. P. Jayawant.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="313"/><a name="MATH313"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 313. Topology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The notion of "closeness" underlies many important mathematical concepts, such as limits and continuity. Topology is the careful study of what this notion means in abstract spaces, leading to a thorough understanding of continuous mappings and the properties of spaces that they preserve. Topics may include metric spaces, topological spaces, continuity, compactness, connectedness, homotopy theory, fixed-point theorems, and applications of these topics in areas such as geographic information systems, robotic, and game theory. Prerequisite(s): MATH 205, 206, and s21. Enrollment limited to 25. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="342"/><a name="EC/MA342"/><h4 class="crsname">EC/MA 342. Optimal Control Theory with Economic Applications.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Optimal control theory unifies numerous economic problems related to the creation and use of physical capital. This course introduces optimal control theory as a tool for dynamic optimization and applies that theory to a variety of classic economic problems involving capital. Among the economic problems examined are optimal use of a renewable resource, optimal use of a nonrenewable resource, and optimal economic growth when growth begets pollution. The course includes formally proving Pontryagin's maximum principle, which  characterizes dynamic optima, in the special case context of common economic problems. Prerequisite(s): MATH 205, 206, and one economics course. Enrollment limited to 20. M. Murray.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="355"/><a name="MATH355"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 355. Topics in Computational Mathematics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Computational mathematics considers how computing can aid the study of mathematics. Computers may be used to perform numerical calculations involved in modeling, provide graphical understanding in analysis, or complete symbolic calculations in algebra. Mathematical study of computer algorithms can lead to more efficient algorithms and actual implementation of algorithms helps students deepen their understanding of mathematics while gaining appreciation for computers' capabilities as well as deficiencies. Normally one or two MATH 355 seminars are offered annually.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="355A"/><a name="MATH355A"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 355A. Numerical Analysis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course studies the best ways to perform calculations that have already been developed in other mathematics courses. For instance, if a computer is to be used to approximate the value of an integral, one must understand both how quickly an algorithm can produce a result and how trustworthy that result is. While students implement algorithms on computers, the focus of the course is the mathematics behind the algorithms. Topics may include interpolation techniques, approximation of functions, solving equations, differentiation and integration, solution of differential equations, iterative solutions of linear systems, and eigenvalues and eigenvectors. Prerequisite(s): MATH 106 and 205. Enrollment limited to 25.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> K. Ott.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="355B"/><a name="MATH355B"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 355B. Graph Algorithms.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">How can we create a network of cables between houses with minimum cost? Under what circumstances can a mail delivery van traverse all the streets in the neighborhood it serves without repeating any street?  Graph theory is the branch of mathematics that provides the framework to answer such questions. Topics may include definitions and properties of graphs and trees, Euler and Hamiltonian circuits, shortest paths, minimal spanning trees, network flows, and graph coloring. Some of the class meetings are devoted to learning to program in Maple. Students then write computer programs to provide solutions to questions such as the ones mentioned before. Prerequisite(s): MATH s21. Enrollment limited to 25. P. Jayawant.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="355D"/><a name="MATH355D"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 355D. Dynamical Systems and Computer Science.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The study of long-term behaviors of feedback processes, dynamical systems is a field that is best understood from both theoretical and computational viewpoints, as each informs the other. Students explore attracting and repelling cycles and witness the complicated dynamics and chaos a simple quadratic function can exhibit. Real and complex functions are considered. Simultaneously, students learn sound computer science fundamentals by writing Visual Basic programs that illustrate the theory of dynamical systems. In particular, students plot both orbit and bifurcation diagrams, Julia sets, and the Mandelbrot set. The course explores both dynamical systems and computer science in depth, thus requiring four meetings per week. Prerequisite(s): MATH s21. Enrollment limited to 25. S. Ross.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="355G"/><a name="MATH355G"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 355G. Computability Theory.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores, in mathematical depth, the concept of algorithmic computability.  What does it mean to say&#8212;and prove&#8212;that a function can/cannot be computed by a mechanical procedure?  Are there different levels of computability and noncomputability, just as there are different sizes of finite and infinite sets?  The study of such questions predates and does not depend on electronic computers, but it influenced their development and yields important information about their capabilities.  Accordingly, the course ranges from foundations laid by Turing and others in the 1930s up through current work and still unresolved matters, like the P-NP problem. Prerequisite(s): MATH s21. Enrollment limited to 30. One-time offering. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="MATH360"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester. This course may not be used to fulfill requirements for the mathematics major or minor in mathematics. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365"/><a name="MATH365"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 365. Special Topics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Content varies from semester to semester. Possible topics include chaotic dynamical systems, number theory, mathematical logic, measure theory, algebraic topology, combinatorics, and graph theory.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="379"/><a name="MATH379"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 379. Abstract Algebra II.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is a continuation of MATH 309, Abstract Algebra I. Advanced topics in group theory, ring theory, and field theory are covered. Applications include geometric constructions, crystallography, and algebraic coding theory. Prerequisite(s): MATH 309. Normally offered every other year. P. Wong.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="MATH457"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Prior to entrance into MATH 457, students must submit a proposal for the work they intend to undertake toward completion of a thesis. Open to all majors upon approval of the proposal. Required of candidates for honors. Students register for MATH 457 in the fall semester.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="MATH458"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Prior to entrance into MATH 458, students must submit a proposal for the work they intend to undertake toward completion of a thesis. Open to all majors upon approval of the proposal. Required of candidates for honors. Students register for MATH 458 in the winter semester.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="495"/><a name="MATH495"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 495. Senior Seminar.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Prior to entrance into MATH 495, students must submit a proposal for the section of senior seminar they wish to undertake. While the subject matter varies, the writing-attentive seminar addresses an advanced topic in mathematics. The development of the topic draws on students' previous course work and helps consolidate their earlier learning. Students are active participants, presenting material to one another in both oral and written form, and conducting individual research on related questions. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="495C"/><a name="MATH495C"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 495C. Numerical Linear Algebra.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is an introduction to numerical linear algebra, which is fundamental to scientific computing. Through guided and self-directed explorations, students examine direct and iterative solutions for linear systems problems including computation of eigenvalues and eigenvectors. The course focuses on both theoretical study of convergence of the numerical methods and practical implementations of these methods. Prerequisite(s): MATH 301. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> H. Boateng.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="495D"/><a name="MATH495D"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 495D. Chaotic Dynamical Systems.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">One of the major scientific accomplishments of the last twenty-five years was the discovery of chaos and the recognition that sensitive dependence on initial conditions is exhibited by so many natural and man-made processes. To really understand chaos, one needs to learn the mathematics behind it. This seminar considers mathematical models of real-world processes and studies how these models behave as they demonstrate chaos and its surprising order. Prerequisite(s): MATH 301. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> S. Ross.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="495H"/><a name="MATH495H"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 495H. Elliptic Curve Cryptography.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An elliptic curve is defined as the set of points of a cubic polynomial in two variables. Interestingly, one can add any two points on the curve to get another point on the curve. In this way, the points form a group. These groups are used in various areas of mathematics, and prominently in cryptography. After an introduction to the basics, each student examines various methods of encryption using elliptic curves, drawing from previous knowledge in abstract algebra, analysis, geometry, and number theory. Computer algebra systems also are used to illustrate the applications. Prerequisite(s): MATH 301 and 309. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> A. Salerno.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="495I"/><a name="MATH495I"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 495I. Fair Division with Combinatorics and Topology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">How can the rent of a house with differently-sized rooms be divided among a group of people so that each person believes the best deal was secured?  Such fair division questions can be answered with a variety of mathematical techniques from combinatiries and topology. After an introduction to the required basics of topology, geometry, and combinatorics, students independently explore these and related questions using the Borsuk-Ulam theorem, the Brouwer fixed point theorem, their discrete versions, and other combinatorics methods. Prerequisite(s): MATH 301. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> P. Jayawant.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="495J"/><a name="MATH495J"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 495J. Advanced Topics in Biomathematics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Biology is one of the most fertile sources of new mathematics. Research may be based on computation and data, or it may rely entirely on theorems and proofs. It may require calculus, linear algebra, graph theory, differential equations, or numerical analysis. Students in this seminar read biology-inspired mathematical research and present their findings to each other. The students in the seminar and their mathematical interests influence the selection of research papers to be investigated. No previous course in biology or mathematical modeling is required. Prerequisite(s): MATH 301. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> M. Greer.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="495L"/><a name="MATH495L"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 495L. The Fundamental Theorem of Algebra.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Over the centuries, there have been numerous proofs of the Fundamental Theorem of Algebra (FTA), which asserts that every polynomial of degree <span class="cite">n</span> must have at most  <span class="cite">n</span> distinct roots over the complex numbers. The great German mathematician Carl F. Gauss (1777-1855) published no fewer than four different proofs of the result. While the name of the theorem foregrounds algebra, none of the known proofs is purely algebraic. Over the centuries, techniques from complex analysis, topology, and field extensions have been employed to give new proofs of the FTA. In this seminar, students explore some of these proofs where the methods are drawn from various subfields in mathematics. Prerequisite(s): MATH 309. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> P. Wong.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="495M"/><a name="MATH495M"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH 495M. Infinite Series.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An infinite series is the sum of the terms of an infinite sequence. In calculus we encounter infinite series of real numbers, for example, the geometric series. This course focuses on infinite series of functions, beginning with an introduction to function series and convergence. Students explore power series, Laurent series, and trigonometric series, culminating with an in-depth examination of Fourier series. Fourier series have numerous applications to areas such as partial differential equations, signal and image processing, acoustics and econometrics, to name only a few. Based on their interests, students investigate one or more of the aforementioned applications of Fourier series using current research papers and texts in mathematics and computer software. Prerequisite(s): MATH 301. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> K. Ott.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="MATHs21"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH s21. Introduction to Abstraction.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An intensive development of the important concepts and methods of abstract mathematics. Students work individually, in groups, and with the instructors to prove theorems and solve problems. Students meet for up to five hours daily to explore such topics as proof techniques, logic, set theory, equivalence relations, functions, and algebraic structures. The course provides exposure to what it means to be a mathematician. Prerequisite(s): one semester of college mathematics. Required of all majors. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. P. Jayawant, M. Montgomery.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s45"/><a name="MATHs45"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH s45. Seminar in Mathematics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The content varies. Normally offered every year.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s45K"/><a name="MATHs45K"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH s45K. Roller Coasters: Theory, Design, and Properties.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Amusement park roller coasters excite us, scare us, and capture our imagination. What records will designers break next? How do they create rides that are exhilarating, yet physically safe? A scientific contemplation of these questions requires math and physics concepts such as vectors, parametric equations, curvature, energy, gravity, and friction. Students consider these ideas, gaining background in basic and more advanced math and physics. During the second half of the course, students conceive and design projects to study specific aspects of roller coasters. Prerequisite(s): MATH 105. Enrollment limited to 25. Instructor permission is required.  <span class="gened">[Q]</span> M. Greer.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s45N"/><a name="MATHs45N"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH s45N. Number Theory.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The theory of numbers is concerned with the properties of the integers, one of the most basic mathematical sets. Seemingly naive questions of number theory stimulated much of the development of modern mathematics and still provide rich opportunities for investigation. Topics studied include classical ones such as primality, congruences, quadratic reciprocity, and Diophantine equations, as well as more recent applications to cryptography. Additional topics such as computational methods, elliptical curves, or an introduction to analytic methods may be included. Prerequisite(s): MATH s21. Not open to students who have received credit for MATH 225. Enrollment limited to 30. A. Salerno.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s45Q"/><a name="MATHs45Q"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH s45Q. p-adic Numbers.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is an introduction to p-adic numbers, which are fascinating but lesser known than rational, real, and complex numbers. The study of p-adic numbers blends together many parts of mathematics, and has numerous applications, including to physics. These numbers are an analogue of the real numbers, and as such many of the concepts from calculus extend naturally. However, differences in the geometry and the calculus of these numbers lead to interesting discoveries and insights; in this geometry, for example, all triangles are isosceles, and every point inside a circle is the center of the circle. Topics may include the study of absolute values on a field, basic properties and geometry of p-adic numbers, sequences and series, functions and their derivatives, and power series. Recommended background: MATH 309 and s21. Prerequisite(s): MATH 205. Enrollment limited to 30. A. Salerno.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s45R"/><a name="MATHs45R"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH s45R. Introduction to Geometric Group Theory.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In the 1980s, M. Gromov introduced a new approach to the study of infinite groups, namely the study of groups as geometric objects. Since then, the field of geometric group theory has flourished and is one of the most active areas of current mathematical research. This course presents the rudiments of geometric group theory. Recommended background: MATH 309. Prerequisite(s): MATH s21. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. P. Wong.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s45T"/><a name="DC/MAs45T"/><h4 class="crsname">DC/MA s45T. Mathematical Image Processing.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Digital image processing is a field essential to many disciplines, including medicine, astronomy, astrophysics, photography, and graphics. It is also an active area of mathematical research with ideas stemming from numerical linear algebra, Fourier analysis, partial differential equations and statistics. This course introduces mathematical methods in digital image processing, including basic image processing tools and techniques with an emphasis on their mathematical foundations. Students implement the theory using MATLAB. Topics may include image compression, image enhancement, edge detection, and image filtering. Students conceive and complete projects&#8212;either theoretical or practical&#8212;on an aspect of digital image processing. Prerequisite(s): MATH 205. Enrollment limited to 30. K. Ott.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="MATHs50"/><h4 class="crsname">MATH s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term. May not be used to fulfill the requirement for the mathematics major or concentration in mathematics. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>

               