<div class="Course"><a name="250"/><a name="PE250"/><h4 class="crsname">PE 250. Ethics and Human Rights in Sports.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Sports play a major role in most cultures. Issues pertaining to sports and culture&#8212;and the ethical choices made surrounding these issues&#8212;can have a significant impact in the lives of people everywhere. This course examines some of the philosophical, political, economic, sociological, religious, and legal issues associated with sports. Topics include corporate ethics and sports, gender issues, racism and sports, ethical decision making, and specific sports-related human rights issues. Designed for first- and second-year students. Not open to students who have received credit for First-Year Seminar 150. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every year. G. Purgavie.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="PE360"/><h4 class="crsname">PE 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s20"/><a name="PEs20"/><h4 class="crsname">PE s20. Methodology of Coaching.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This unit explores various methodologies of successful coaching. Students complete the ACEP (American Coaching Education Program) Coaching Principles Course, which leads to a level of certification widely accepted in secondary schools. Topics include the development of a coaching philosophy; sports psychology; sports pedagogy; and team management. In addition to the classroom component, the course involves a service-learning component, in which each student coaches in an assigned elementary school or another community program related to youth development and mentoring. Enrollment limited to 25. Offered with varying frequency. G. Purgavie.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="PEs50"/><h4 class="crsname">PE s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/></span></div>

               