<div class="Course"><a name="112"/><a name="PHIL112"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 112. Contemporary Moral Disputes.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course focuses on particular moral issues and the ethical arguments provoked by them. Topics discussed in the course may include the death penalty, abortion, and war tactics that result in civilian casualties including the ethics of drones, torture, and terrorism. Not open to students who have received credit for FYS 309. Enrollment limited to 30 per section. D. Cummiskey, T. Tracy, P. Schofield.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="150"/><a name="PHIL150"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 150. Introduction to Philosophy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to philosophy and philosophical reasoning by examining some of the fundamental philosophical problems of human existence. Among these are the problem of doubt and uncertainty as an aspect of human knowledge; the justification and importance of religious belief; and the nature of mind, matter, and freedom. An attempt is made to establish a balance between philosophy as a vigorous and professional discipline and philosophy as a personally useful method for exploring one's own reasoning and beliefs. Readings include both historical and contemporary works. Enrollment limited to 30 per section. W. Seeley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="195"/><a name="PHIL195"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 195. Introduction to Logic.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An investigation of the nature of valid reasoning, coupled with training in the skills of critical thinking. Close attention is paid to the analysis of ordinary arguments.   Enrollment limited to 40 per section. Normally offered every year. M. Okrent, L. Ashwell.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="211"/><a name="PHIL211"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 211. Philosophy of Science.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Science has become our model for what counts as knowledge; the course examines that model and discusses how far its claims are justified in the light of the nature and history of science. Topics for consideration are drawn from the nature of scientific explanation, scientific rationality, progress in science, the nature of scientific theories, and the relations of science to society and to other views of the world. Readings include traditional and contemporary work in the philosophy of science. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=NRSC">Neuroscience</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="213"/><a name="PHIL213"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 213. Biomedical Ethics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The rapid changes in the biological sciences and medical technology have thoroughly transformed the practice of medicine. The added complexity and power of medicine has in turn revolutionized the responsibilities and duties that accompany the medical professions. This course explores the values and norms governing medical practice; the rights and responsibilities of health care providers and patients; the justification for euthanasia; and the problems of access, allocation, and rationing of health care services. Not open to students who have received credit for FYS 362 or PHIL s26. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C013">Law and Society (C013)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=NRSC">Neuroscience</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="214"/><a name="ES/PL214"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/PL 214. Environmental Ethics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of selected issues in environmental ethics, including questions about population growth, resource consumption, pollution, the responsibilities of corporations, environmental justice, animal rights, biodiversity, and moral concern for the natural world. The course explores debates currently taking place among environmental thinkers regarding our moral obligations to other persons, to future generations, to other animals, and to ecosystems and the Earth itself. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. T. Tracy, P. Schofield.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="227"/><a name="PHIL227"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 227. Philosophy of Art.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to central issues in contemporary philosophy of art through the lens of artistic works and practice. Students investigate what constitutes a work of art, artistic representation, the nature of aesthetic qualities, and the relevance of artists' intentions to the evaluation of works of art, with close attention to visual, performance, literary, and experimental art forms. Not open to students who have received credit for AV/PL 226. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30 per section. W. Seeley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C029">Visible Ideas: 2D and 3D Design (C029)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="234"/><a name="PHIL234"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 234. Philosophy of Language.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is an advanced introduction to contemporary issues in the philosophy of language. Students investigate the natures of reference, meaning, and truth while reading the work of 
Frege, Wittgenstein, Russell, Kripke, Lewis, Putnam, and others. They address questions such as: What is it for a sign or a bit of language to be meaningful? What is it for words to represent or identify something? What is it for a statement to be truthful? What is a language, and what is it to know a language? How can you believe that Superman flies while believing that Clark Kent doesn't? Prerequisite(s): one course in philosophy. Recommended background: PHIL 195. Enrollment limited to 30. M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="235"/><a name="PHIL235"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 235. Philosophy of Mind.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An inquiry into the nature of human mentality that pays special attention to the issues raised by experience and the relation between thought and language. Is mind distinct from body? If not, are mental states identical with brain states, or does the mind relate to the brain as programs relate to computer hardware? What is the connection between linguistic meaning and thought? Readings are drawn from historical and contemporary sources. Recommended background: one course in philosophy.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. L. Ashwell, M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=NRSC">Neuroscience</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="236"/><a name="PHIL236"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 236. Theory of Knowledge.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Is knowledge possible, and if so, how? The course investigates how we can know the ordinary things we take ourselves to know. Students are introduced to major philosophical theories concerning when our thoughts about ourselves and the world are rationally justified.   Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. L. Ashwell.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="243"/><a name="PL/RE243"/><h4 class="crsname">PL/RE 243. Religion and Modern Critics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the dialogue between Western religious traditions and modern culture since the Enlightenment. Attention is given both to critical challenges (e.g., from philosophy, science, social theory, and psychology) and to religious responses that together have set the context for contemporary debates about the meaning and value of religion. Readings are drawn from thinkers such Hume, Kant, Schleiermacher, Kierkegaard, Marx, Darwin, Nietzsche, and Freud.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. T. Tracy.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="245"/><a name="PHIL245"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 245. Metaphysics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to some of the central issues in metaphysics. Possible questions considered include: Which kinds of things exist? What is one saying when one says that something "exists"? What does it mean to say that something causes something else? What is one saying when one says that something might possibly be other than it is? What does it mean to say that something is the same identical thing at one time that it is at another?  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. L. Ashwell.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="255"/><a name="PHIL255"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 255. Human Nature and Perfectibility.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course looks at influential theories of human nature and different conceptions of the possibility of human perfection. What is the essence of human nature? Is the capacity to improve upon itself part of its essence? What is the best possible human life and why is it so difficult to achieve? The course considers a wide range of sources from ancient philosophical and religious texts to modern and contemporary scientific and philosophical theories of human nature. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="256"/><a name="PHIL256"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 256. Moral Philosophy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Is there a difference between right and wrong? Is it merely a matter of custom, convention, preference, or opinion, or is there some other basis for this distinction, something that makes it "objective" rather than "subjective"? How can we tell, in particular cases and in general, what is right and what is wrong? Is there some moral principle or method for deciding particular moral problems? Philosophers discussed include Hobbes, Hume, Kant, Mill, and the Dalai Lama. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30 per section. Normally offered every year. D. Cummiskey, S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="257"/><a name="PHIL257"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 257. Moral Luck.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the relationship between luck and morality. It examines the moral and metaphysical problem of free will, determinism, and responsibility, and the related problem of moral luck. It looks at the role friendship plays in the moral life and the ways "relational goods" help to protect us from some of the exigencies of bad luck. It considers Kant's attempt to make morality "safe" from luck and the way Aristotle embraces luck in his moral outlook. It also looks at the nature of evil and the extent to which evil is under our control.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Not open to students who have received credit for FYS 288 or PHIL s22. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30 per section. S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="258"/><a name="PHIL258"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 258. Philosophy of Law.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">What is law? What is the relationship of law to morality? What is the nature of judicial reasoning? Particular legal issues include the nature and status of liberty rights (the right to privacy including contraception, abortion, and homosexuality), the legitimacy of restrictions on speech and expression (flag burning and racist hate speech), and the justification of the death penalty. Readings include traditional and contemporary legal theory, case studies, and court decisions. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C013">Law and Society (C013)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="260"/><a name="PL/RE260"/><h4 class="crsname">PL/RE 260. Philosophy of Religion.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A consideration of major issues that arise in philosophical reflection upon religion. Particular issues are selected from among such topics as the nature of faith, the possibility of justifying religious beliefs, the nature and validity of religious experience, the relation of religion and science, and the problem of evil.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. T. Tracy.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="262"/><a name="PHIL262"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 262. Philosophy and Feminism.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">One central project of feminist philosophy is the use of philosophical methods to think carefully about important and distinctive features of the lives of women, and also about the concepts employed in the feminist political movement and similar social movements, such as those centered around race, class, disability, and sexuality. Topics include: what it is to be a woman; what it is to face discrimination or oppression; science and society, particularly genders in science; sex and sexuality; reproduction; the family; gender in popular culture; the body and appearance, including looking at the fashion and beauty industries. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. L. Ashwell, S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="268"/><a name="PHIL268"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 268. Capitalism and Its Critics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Some consider a capitalist economy an environment ideally conducive to human flourishing, while others consider it a significant threat. Debates over the merits of capitalism have raged among philosophers for generations. This course considers some of capitalism's most able defenders, as well as some of its most incisive critics. The course also examines some hybrid views, which attempt  to harness capitalism's capacity for good, while mitigating its ability to harm. Enrollment limited to 30. P. Schofield.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C013">Law and Society (C013)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="271"/><a name="CM/PL271"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/PL 271. Ancient Greek Philosophy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the basic philosophical ideas underlying Western thought as these are expressed in the writings of the Pre-Socratics, Socrates, Plato, and Aristotle. Greek thought is discussed in its historical and social context, with indications of how important Greek ideas were developed in later centuries. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. M. Okrent, S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="272"/><a name="PHIL272"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 272. Philosophy from Descartes to Kant.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The problems of knowledge, reality, and morality are discussed as they developed from the time of the scientific revolution and the birth of modern philosophy until their culmination in Kant. The course considers thinkers from among the classic rationalists (Descartes, Spinoza, Leibniz) and empiricists (Locke, Berkeley, Hume) as well as Kant.   Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. M. Okrent, L. Ashwell, P. Schofield.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C066">Early Modern World (C066)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="273"/><a name="PHIL273"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 273. Philosophy in the Nineteenth Century.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course follows the development of modern thought from Kant, through the rise and breakup of Hegelianism, to the culmination of nineteenth-century thought in Nietzsche. The impact of science, the relation of the individual and society, and the role of reflection in experience are examined in readings drawn from among Kant, Hegel, Schopenhauer, Feuerbach, Marx, Mill, Nietzsche, and Kierkegaard. Recommended background: two courses in philosophy or Philosophy 272.  Open to first-year students. M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=EUS">European Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="295"/><a name="PHIL295"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 295. Logic: Possibility, Probability, and Proofs.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Philosophers use various formal tools for philosophical inquiry. In this course students consider modal logic, the logic of possibility and necessity, formal epistemology, and also some surprising metalogical results. Prerequisite(s): PHIL 195. Not open to students who have received credit for PHIL 395A. Enrollment limited to 30. L. Ashwell.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="304"/><a name="PL/RE304"/><h4 class="crsname">PL/RE 304. The Problem of Evil.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The presence of profound suffering and appalling injustice in the world raises some of the deepest questions that religions seek to address. Can the evils we see around us be reconciled with the classical affirmation that the world is created by a just and all-powerful God? This seminar considers the problem of evil as it arises in the theological and philosophical traditions of the West. Readings include Genesis and Job, Holocaust literature and Jewish theological responses, and contemporary writings in philosophy of religion and theology. Prerequisite(s): one course in philosophy or religious studies.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> T. Tracy.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="310"/><a name="PHIL310"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 310. Buddhist Philosophy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores Buddhist philosophy with a special emphasis on moral and political philosophy. Philosophical topics include the Four Noble Truths, the doctrine of impermanence and codependent arising, the doctrine of no-self, and the concept of emptiness. The relationships among Buddhist philosophy, insight meditation, and moral virtue, especially the practical social, political, and ethical implications, are a primary focus of the course. Prerequisite(s): two courses in philosophy. Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every other year. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C002">Buddhism (C002)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C087">South Asian Studies (C087)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="321"/><a name="PHIL321"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 321. Seminar: Topics in the Contemporary Philosophy of Mind and Language.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An examination of recent discussions of topics concerning language, intentionality, and what it is to be a person. Topics vary from year to year.  <br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="321D"/><a name="PHIL321D"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 321D. The Rise of Philosophical Analysis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the history of twentieth-century philosophy by examining the methods and characteristic doctrines of two   successive philosophical movements. Students first focus on the early twentieth-century attempt, pioneered by Russell and the early Wittgenstein, to apply the newly developed techniques of formal logic to the analysis of the cognitive significance of our ordinary ways of talking. The course then considers the way in which a later generation of "ordinary language" philosophers, including Ryle, Austin, and the later Wittgenstein, reacted  against this attempt. Readings are taken from the works of Russell, G. E. Moore, Wittgenstein, Carnap, Quine, Ayer, Ryle, and Austin. Prerequisite(s): one course in philosophy. Recommended background: PHIL 195 or two courses in philosophy. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="321H"/><a name="PHIL321H"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 321H. Computational Modeling: Autonomous Robots and Embodied Cognition.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores current research models in embodied cognition and artificial intelligence that use simulations, robotics, and genetic algorithms to explore flexible and adaptive behaviors constitutive of our conception of intelligence. These approaches provide alternative models for intelligent behavior that challenge traditional representational and computational theories of mind. The course includes a lab in which students use hands robotics exercises to explore the ideas they encounter in the class. Topics include the nature of intelligence, the computational theory of mind, representation, embodied cognition, behavior-based robotics, biorobotics modeling, dynamic systems, neural networks, genetic algorithms, and philosophical questions surrounding the use of computer simulations and robotics as research tools in psychology and cognitive science. No prior programming experience is necessary. Recommended background: PHIL 195, 235, 237, 321G; PSYC 101, 230; or NS/PY 330. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 18. W. Seeley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="321J"/><a name="PHIL321J"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 321J. Topics in the Contemporary Philosophy of Mind and Language: Self-Knowledge.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">We seem to know our own minds &#8212; our beliefs, desires, intentions, feelings, and sensations &#8212; in a distinctive and particularly secure way. But although introspective self-knowledge is so familiar, it is difficult to account for. This course examines a range of philosophical problems associated with self-knowledge: What (if any) are the differences between self-knowledge and other knowledge, such as knowledge of other people's minds? Can plausible accounts of the process of introspection be reconciled with plausible accounts of the objects of self-knowledge, i.e., mental states and their contents? Do we even have knowledge of our own minds? Prerequisite(s): one 200- or 300-level course in philosophy. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> One-time offering. L. Ashwell.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="322"/><a name="PHIL322"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 322. Seminar: Topics in Contemporary European Philosophy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An examination of recent developments in Continental philosophy. <br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="323"/><a name="PHIL323"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 323. Seminar: Topics in Metaphysics and Epistemology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc"> This course focuses on advanced issues in the theory of knowledge and in the theory of ultimate reality.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="323A"/><a name="PHIL323A"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 323A. Dispositions.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Paradigmatic dispositions are fragility, solubility, elasticity, and conductivity, but discussions of dispositions occur in a wider range of theories than these examples might suggest. Dispositions, also called "powers" or "tendencies" are considered in, for example, analyses of free will, color properties, mental states, natural laws, and causation. Some argue that dispositions are the only type of property there is, yet others question whether there really are such properties. In discussing these debates, students cover several core topics in metaphysics and epistemology, including possible worlds and counterfactuals, realism and anti-realism about properties, reduction, and explanation. Prerequisite(s): PHIL 195 and 211, 232, 234, 235, 236, 245, 272, or 274.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> L. Ashwell.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="324"/><a name="PHIL324"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 324. Seminar: Topics in Ethics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on important issues in ethics and political theory. Prerequisites(s): Philosophy 256 or 257.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="324C"/><a name="PHIL324C"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 324C. Liberty, Equality, and Community.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Liberty and equality are the central values of contemporary political philosophy. These values, however, seem inevitably to conflict. Unlimited freedom leads to inequalities and remedies for inequalities restrict liberty. This seminar focuses on competing accounts of the proper balance between liberty and equality.  In particular, students focus on John Rawls' theory of justice and competing theories of justice, including utilitarian liberalism, Nozick's libertarian theory, communitarian theories, feminist theories, and multicultural approaches. Prerequisite(s): PHIL 255, 256, or 257. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C013">Law and Society (C013)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="324E"/><a name="PHIL324E"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 324E. Virtue Ethics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Virtue ethics emerged as an important kind of moral theory during the last half of the twentieth century. There are many virtue theories, but they share a focus on the morality of character rather than the morality of individual actions. Many seek an answer to the question, "How shall I live?" rather than, "What should I do?" This course explores both the historical roots of virtue theory found in Aristotle and, according to some scholars, Kant. It also examines several contemporary theories of virtue as well as critics of this approach to moral theory. Prerequisite(s): FYS 248 or PHIL 256. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="325"/><a name="PHIL325"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 325. Seminar: Topics in Metaethics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">These courses consider a broad range of issues, both historical and contemporary, in metaethics and moral epistemology. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 15. S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="325B"/><a name="PHIL325B"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 325B. Moral Rules and/or Particulars.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Until recently many moral philosophers have assumed that moral justification proceeds by showing that, for example, an action falls under some more general moral principle. However, the existence and epistemic value of moral generalities have increasingly come to be questioned by a group of contemporary moral philosophers, including Aristotelians, feminists, and some British moral realists. These particularists have advanced the striking metaphysical claim that there are no codifiable moral generalities, as well as the epistemological claim that moral justification need not be parasitic on a supposed metaphysical relationship between justified and justifying properties. This course investigates these claims while also investigating the role that rules may or should play in morality. Prerequisite(s): PHIL 170 or 256. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="325C"/><a name="PHIL325C"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 325C. Moral Realism.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines contemporary theories on the meaning of moral language, the possibility of moral knowledge, the existence of moral facts, the nature of moral arguments, and the relationship between morality and rationality. Philosophers discussed include Moore, Ayer, Stevenson, Hare, Foot, and Mackie. Some background in moral or political theory is recommended.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="350"/><a name="PHIL350"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 350. Seminar on Major Thinkers.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course examines in depth the writings of a major philosopher. Thinkers who may be discussed include Plato, Aristotle, Plotinus, Descartes, Spinoza, Leibniz, Hume, Marx, Wittgenstein, and Quine.  Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="351"/><a name="PHIL351"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 351. Kant.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is an intensive study of Kant's <span class="cite">Critique of Pure Reason</span>. Interpretations by contemporary critics are considered. Prerequisite(s): PHIL 272.  <span class="crsaddmod">Course reinstated beginning Winter 2015.</span>  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C066">Early Modern World (C066)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="PHIL360"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365"/><a name="PHIL365"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 365. Special Topics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A course or seminar offered from time to time and reserved for a special topic selected by the department. <br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="PHIL457"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students register for PHIL 457 in the fall semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both PHIL 457 and 458.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="PHIL458"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students register for PHIL 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both PHIL 457 and 458.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s22"/><a name="PHILs22"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL s22. Moral Luck.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the relationship between luck and morality. It examines the moral and metaphysical problem of free will, determinism, and responsibility, and the related problem of moral luck. It looks at the role friendship plays in the moral life and the ways "relational goods" help to protect us from some of the exigencies of bad luck. It considers Kant's attempt to make morality "safe" from luck and the way Aristotle embraces luck in his moral outlook. It also looks at the nature of evil and the extent to which evil is under our control. Not open to students who have received credit for FYS 288 or PHIL 257. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s25"/><a name="PHILs25"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL s25. Asian and Islamic Ethical Systems.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course provides a comparative study of Asian conceptions of ethics, including Confucian, Buddhist, and Islamic belief systems. Students carry out their own research, focusing on the beliefs, practices, and social structure of a tradition or community of their choice. The course ends with seminars in which students share the results of their research. Prerequisite(s): one course in philosophy. Enrollment limited to 15. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C002">Buddhism (C002)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s27"/><a name="PHILs27"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL s27. Concepts of Self.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In Western philosophy, the idea of a self is central. The once dominant view held that selves were atomistic, isolated, literally individuals. Now many theorists regard selves as constituted and maintained through relationships. With this idea as a baseline, this course examines what selves or agents are, the ways in which selves are constituted and sustained, and the role of emotion in the constitution of a self. The course examines the idea of autonomy, especially in light of feminist critiques. And finally, the course explores the possibility of agency in a deterministic, scientific, though not necessarily scientistic worldview. Not open to students who have received credit for PHIL 219. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s32"/><a name="PHILs32"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL s32. Teaching Philosophy: Course Design and Classroom Instruction.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The line between practicing philosophy and teaching it has always been a blurry one, enough so that being a philosopher is often thought to involve being a teacher. In this course, students assume the role of philosophy instructor. The course covers works by a number of contemporary authors writing on course design and innovative teaching methodology, and students design a week-long introductory philosophy mini-course targeted at high school students.   Prerequisite(s): 3 philosophy courses. 
 Enrollment limited to 9. Instructor permission is required. P. Schofield, S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="PHILs50"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>

               