<div class="Course"><a name="112"/><a name="PHIL112"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 112. Contemporary Moral Disputes.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course focuses on particular moral issues and the ethical arguments provoked by them. Topics discussed in the course may include abortion and euthanasia, war and nuclear arms, world hunger, and the use of natural resources. Not open to students who have received credit for Philosophy/Religious Studies 212. Not open to students who have received credit for PL/RE 212. Enrollment limited to 30 per section. Normally offered every year. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="195"/><a name="PHIL195"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 195. Introduction to Logic.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An investigation of the nature of valid reasoning, coupled with training in the skills of critical thinking. Close attention is paid to the analysis of ordinary arguments.   Enrollment limited to 40 per section. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="211"/><a name="PHIL211"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 211. Philosophy of Science.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Science has become our model for what counts as knowledge; the course examines that model and discusses how far its claims are justified in the light of the nature and history of science. Topics for consideration are drawn from the nature of scientific explanation, scientific rationality, progress in science, the nature of scientific theories, and the relations of science to society and to other views of the world. Readings include traditional, contemporary, and feminist work in the philosophy of science.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="213"/><a name="PHIL213"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 213. Biomedical Ethics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The rapid changes in the biological sciences and medical technology have thoroughly transformed the practice of medicine. The added complexity and power of medicine has in turn revolutionized the responsibilities and duties that accompany the medical professions. This course explores the values and norms governing medical practice; the rights and responsibilities of health care providers and patients; the justification for euthanasia; and the problems of access, allocation, and rationing of health care services. Not open to students who have received credit for First-Year Seminars 362 or Philosophy s26. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="214"/><a name="ES/PL214"/><h4 class="crsname">ES/PL 214. Ethics and Environmental Issues.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of selected issues in environmental ethics, including questions about population growth, resource consumption, pollution, the responsibilities of corporations, environmental justice, animal rights, biodiversity, and moral concern for the natural world. The course explores debates currently taking place among environmental thinkers regarding our moral obligations to other persons, to future generations, to other animals, and to ecosystems and the Earth itself.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. T. Tracy.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C070">Water and Society (C070)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C062">Why Academics Matter (C062)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="218"/><a name="PHIL218"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 218. The Constitution of Selves.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In Western philosophy, the idea of a self is central. The once dominant view held that selves were atomistic, isolated, literally individuals. Now many theorists regard selves as constituted and maintained through relationships. With this idea as a baseline, this course examines what selves or agents are, the ways in which selves are constituted and sustained, and the role of emotion in the constitution of a self. The course examines the idea of autonomy, especially in light of feminist critiques. And finally, the course explores the possibility of agency in a deterministic, scientific, though not necessarily scientistic worldview. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="220"/><a name="PHIL220"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 220. The Rise of Philosophical Analysis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the history of twentieth-century philosophy by examining the methods and characteristic doctrines of two   successive philosophical movements. Students first focus on the early twentieth-century attempt, pioneered by Russell and the early Wittgenstein, to apply the newly developed techniques of formal logic to the analysis of the cognitive significance of our ordinary ways of talking. The course then considers the way in which a later generation of "ordinary language" philosophers, including Ryle, Austin, and the later Wittgenstein, reacted  against this attempt. Readings are taken from the works of Russell, G. E. Moore, Wittgenstein, Ayer, Ryle, and Austin. Prerequisite(s): one course in philosophy. Recommended background: Philosophy 195 or two courses in philosophy. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="227"/><a name="PHIL227"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 227. Philosophy of Art.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to central issues in contemporary philosophy of art through the lens of artistic works and practice. Students investigate what constitutes a work of art, artistic representation, the nature of aesthetic qualities, and the relevance of artists' intentions to the evaluation of works of art, with close attention to visual, performance, literary, and experimental art forms. Not open to students who have received credit for Art and Visual Culture/Philosophy 226. Not open to students who have received credit for AR/PL 226 or AV/PL 226. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30 per section. Normally offered every other year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="232"/><a name="PHIL232"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 232. Philosophy of Psychology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc"> The fundamental question philosophers of psychology ask is: Can there be a science of the mind? The major obstacle to an affirmative answer is the nature of consciousness. Thus a significant part of the course focuses on the philosophical problem of consciousness. Emotions, however, also pose problems for the science of the mind, and are also implicated in the nature of consciousness. A second focus of the course is the nature of emotion and its relationship to consciousness. Prerequisite(s): one course in philosophy. Not open to students who have received credit for Philosophy s21. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="234"/><a name="PHIL234"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 234. Philosophy of Language.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is an advanced introduction to contemporary issues in the philosophy of language. Students investigate the natures of reference, meaning, and truth while reading the work of Frege, Wittgenstein, Russell, Kripke, Lewis, Putnam, and others. They address questions such as: What is it for a sign or a bit of language to be meaningful? What is it for words to represent or identify something? What is it for a statement to be truthful? What is a language, and what is it to know a language? How can you believe that Superman flies while believing that Clark Kent doesn't? Prerequisite(s): one course in philosophy. Recommended background: Philosophy 195.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="235"/><a name="PHIL235"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 235. Philosophy of Mind.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An inquiry into the nature of human mentality that pays special attention to the issues raised by experience and the relation between thought and language. Is mind distinct from body? If not, are mental states identical with brain states, or does the mind relate to the brain as programs relate to computer hardware? What is the connection between linguistic meaning and thought? Readings are drawn from historical and contemporary sources. Recommended background: one course in philosophy. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every other year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="236"/><a name="PHIL236"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 236. Theory of Knowledge.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Is knowledge possible, and if so, how? The course investigates how we can know the ordinary things we take ourselves to know. Students are introduced to major philosophical theories concerning when our thoughts about ourselves and the world are rationally justified.   Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="245"/><a name="PHIL245"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 245. Metaphysics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to some of the central issues in metaphysics. Possible questions considered include: Which kinds of things exist? What is one saying when one says that something "exists"? What does it mean to say that something causes something else? What is one saying when one says that something might possibly be other than it is? What does it mean to say that something is the same identical thing at one time that it is at another?  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="256"/><a name="PHIL256"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 256. Moral Philosophy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Is there a difference between right and wrong? Is it merely a matter of custom, convention, preference, or opinion, or is there some other basis for this distinction, something that makes it "objective" rather than "subjective"? How can we tell, in particular cases and in general, what is right and what is wrong? Is there some moral principle or method for deciding particular moral problems? Philosophers discussed include Aristotle, Hobbes, Hume, Kant, Mill, and the Dalai Lama. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30 per section. Normally offered every year. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="257"/><a name="PHIL257"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 257. Moral Luck.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the relationship between luck and morality. It examines the moral and metaphysical problem of free will, determinism, and responsibility, and the related problem of moral luck. It looks at the role friendship plays in the moral life and the ways "relational goods" help to protect us from some of the exigencies of bad luck. It considers Kant's attempt to make morality "safe" from luck and the way Aristotle embraces luck in his moral outlook. It also looks at the nature of evil and the extent to which evil is under our control. Not open to students who have received credit for First-Year Seminars 288 or Philosophy 170. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30 per section. Normally offered every other year. S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="258"/><a name="PHIL258"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 258. Philosophy of Law.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">What is law? What is the relationship of law to morality? What is the nature of judicial reasoning? Particular legal issues include the nature and status of liberty rights (the right to privacy including contraception, abortion, and homosexuality), the legitimacy of restrictions on speech and expression (flag burning and racist hate speech), and the justification of the death penalty. Readings include traditional, contemporary, and feminist legal theory; case studies; and court decisions. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C013">Law and Society (C013)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="260"/><a name="PL/RE260"/><h4 class="crsname">PL/RE 260. Philosophy of Religion.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A consideration of major issues that arise in philosophical reflection upon religion. Particular issues are selected from among such topics as the nature of faith, the possibility of justifying religious beliefs, the nature and validity of religious experience, the relation of religion and science, and the problem of evil.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. T. Tracy.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="262"/><a name="PHIL262"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 262. Philosophy and Feminism.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Feminist philosophy is an approach to philosophy that takes the experiences, viewpoints, and views of women as primary. One experience of women that is important in a feminist philosophy is the experience of oppression. This course studies the concept and phenomenology of oppression: What is it? How is oppression maintained and perpetuated? What role do men and women play in the oppression of women? How are the different aspects of oppression (oppression on the basis of race, gender, class, sexual orientation, gender identity or expression, or ability) intertwined in the experiences of individuals and groups?  The course also focuses on various arenas in which women experience oppression, examining the ways in which gender-based oppression interacts with other forms of oppression, including racism, classism, ageism, abilism, and anti-gay oppression. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="271"/><a name="CM/PL271"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/PL 271. Greek Philosophy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the basic philosophical ideas underlying Western thought as these are expressed in the writings of the Pre-Socratics,  Plato and Aristotle. Greek thought is discussed in its historical and social context, with indications of how important Greek ideas were developed in later centuries. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Not open to students who have received credit for Philosophy 271. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="272"/><a name="PHIL272"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 272. Philosophy from Descartes to Kant.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The problems of knowledge, reality, and morality are discussed as they developed from the time of the scientific revolution and the birth of modern philosophy until their culmination in Kant. The course considers thinkers from among the classic rationalists (Descartes, Spinoza, Leibniz) and empiricists (Locke, Berkeley, Hume) as well as Kant.   Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C066">Early Modern World (C066)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="273"/><a name="PHIL273"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 273. Philosophy in the Nineteenth Century.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course follows the development of modern thought from Kant, through the rise and breakup of Hegelianism, to the culmination of nineteenth-century thought in Nietzsche. The impact of science, the relation of the individual and society, and the role of reflection in experience are examined in readings drawn from among Kant, Hegel, Schopenhauer, Feuerbach, Marx, Mill, Nietzsche, and Kierkegaard. Recommended background: two courses in philosophy or Philosophy 272.  Open to first-year students. Normally offered every other year. M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="274"/><a name="PHIL274"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 274. Phenomenology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A survey of several of the dominant themes in twentieth-century phenomenology. The course is designed to familiarize students with this area through the study of some of the works of Husserl and Heidegger, among others. Prerequisite(s): one course in philosophy.  Normally offered every other year. M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="290"/><a name="DN/PL290"/><h4 class="crsname">DN/PL 290. Aesthetics and Dance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course approaches issues of aesthetic theory in terms of dance and human performance. Using some of the pivotal texts that have advanced aesthetic understanding through time, students draw dance into the ongoing dialogue of the arts and their cultural significance, investigating the experience of art, the making of meaning, aesthetic perception, and the curse of beauty. Not open to students who have received credit for Dance 290. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 12.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Offered with varying frequency. C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="304"/><a name="PL/RE304"/><h4 class="crsname">PL/RE 304. The Problem of Evil.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The presence of profound suffering and appalling injustice in the world raises some of the deepest questions that religions seek to address. Can the evils we see around us be reconciled with the classical affirmation that the world is created by a just and all-powerful God? This seminar considers the problem of evil as it arises in the theological and philosophical traditions of the West. Readings include Genesis and Job, Holocaust literature and Jewish theological responses, and contemporary writings in philosophy of religion and theology. Prerequisite(s): one course in philosophy or religious studies. Not open to students who have received credit for Religious Studies 304. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. T. Tracy.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="315"/><a name="INDS315"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 315. African American Philosophers.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on how African American philosophers confront and address philosophical problems. Students consider the relationship between the black experience and traditional themes in Western philosophy. Attention is also given to the motivations and context sustaining African American philosophers. Recommended background: African American Studies 100 or 140A or African American Studies/American Cultural Studies 119. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and philosophy. Not open to students who have received credit for Interdisciplinary Studies 165. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="316"/><a name="PL/RE316"/><h4 class="crsname">PL/RE 316. Nietzsche and Religious Imagination.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar develops a comprehensive interpretation of Nietzsche's religious thought and its influences. The course centers on Nietzsche's critique of Christian morality in the mature writings. Part one involves a close reading of <span class="cite">On the Genealogy of Morality</span> and <span class="cite">The Antichrist</span>. Part two examines the themes of critique and tradition, religion and imagination, and the limits of morality. Prerequisite: one course in philosophy or religious studies. Recommended background: Religious Studies 243. Not open to students who have received credit for Philosophy/Religious Studies 315. Not open to students who have received credit for PL/RE 315. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. J. Swan Tuite.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="321"/><a name="PHIL321"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 321. Seminar: Topics in the Contemporary Philosophy of Mind and Language.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An examination of recent discussions of topics concerning language, intentionality, and what it is to be a person. Topics vary from year to year.  <br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="321B"/><a name="PHIL321B"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 321B. Meaning Holism.</h4><span class="CourseDesc"> Meaning holism is the doctrine that "only whole languages or whole theories or whole belief systems really have meanings, so that the meaning of smaller units are merely derivative." Meaning holism characterizes a variety of twentieth-century views regarding mind and language in both the analytic and Continental traditions. This seminar considers meaning holism in W. V. O. Quine and his descendants, Donald Davidson and Daniel Dennett, among others, as well as recent criticism of this position by Jerry Fodor. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="321C"/><a name="PHIL321C"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 321C. Colors and Sounds.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Traditionally, philosophical thought about perception and consciousness has focused primarily on vision&#8212;in particular, on color and color experience. Philosophers interested in the nature and content of experience have much to learn through attention to the distinctive features of other sensory modalities and the things we perceive through them. In this seminar, students examine what colors are, what sorts of things are colored, and the relationship between colors and our experiences of them. They then investigate the nature of sounds and of auditory experience, and address the questions associated with developing a philosophical theory of auditory perception. Prerequisite(s): Philosophy 211, 232, 234, 235, 236, 245, 272, or 274. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C036">Color: Sight and Perception (C036)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C005">Sound (C005)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="322"/><a name="PHIL322"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 322. Seminar: Topics in Contemporary European Philosophy.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An examination of recent developments in Continental philosophy.  Normally offered every other year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="324"/><a name="PHIL324"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 324. Seminar: Topics in Ethics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on important issues in ethics and political theory. Prerequisites(s): Philosophy 256 or 257.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="324A"/><a name="PHIL324A"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 324A. Seminar:  Kantian Ethics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar uses Kant's moral theory as a
vehicle to explore some of the central questions and
assumptions of Western moral theory. Kantian ethics is typically contrasted with the moral theory of David Hume and its heirs, the utilitarians. Central to this contrast between Kantians and Humeans is an emphasis on the dualisms
of reason and passion, duty and sentiment, principle and
sympathy, autonomy and heteronomy, right acts and good
consequences. In each case, Kant is identified with the
first and Hume with the second of the pairs. On the other
hand, recent interpretations of Kant's ethics by Marcia
Baron, Barbara Herman, Thomas Hill, Christine Korsgaard,
and Onora O'Neill present a more unified, and perhaps more
compelling, picture of Kantian ethics. This seminar focuses
on these new interpretations of Kantian moral theory. Prerequisite(s): Philosophy 256 or 257.



 Offered with varying frequency. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="324B"/><a name="PHIL324B"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 324B. Consequentialism and its Critics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Consequentialism is the view that the morally right act is whatever act produces the most good. The appeal of such a view is obvious; it provides a clear way of judging between moral claims, and it generally requires acts that benefit society. Critics complain that consequentialists can manipulate and even kill individuals to achieve their ends, and may also destroy themselves in the process of promoting the good. This course looks at this contemporary debate and the truth about what we ought morally to do. Prerequisite(s): Philosophy 256 or 257. Enrollment limited to 12. Offered with varying frequency. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="324C"/><a name="PHIL324C"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 324C. Liberty and Equality.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Liberty and equality are the central values of contemporary political philosophy. These values, however, seem inevitably to conflict. Unlimited freedom leads to inequalites and remedies for inequalities restrict liberty. This seminar focuses on competing accounts of the proper balance between liberty and equality.  In particular, students focus on John Rawls' theory of justice and competing therories of justice, including utilitarian liberalism, Nozick's libertarian theory, communitarian theories, feminist theories, and multicultural approaches. Prerequisite(s): Philosophy 256 or 257. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C013">Law and Society (C013)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="324E"/><a name="PHIL324E"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 324E. Virtue Ethics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Virtue ethics emerged as an important kind of moral theory during the last half of the twentieth century. There are many virtue theories, but they share a focus on the morality of character rather than the morality of individual actions. Many seek an answer to the question, "How shall I live?" rather than, "What should I do?" This course explores both the historical roots of virtue theory found in Aristotle and, according to some scholars, Kant. It also examines several contemporary theories of virtue as well as critics of this approach to moral theory. Prerequisite(s): First-Year Seminar 248 or Philosophy 256. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Offered with varying frequency. S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="325"/><a name="PHIL325"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 325. Seminar: Topics in Metaethics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines contemporary theories on the meaning of moral language, the possibility of moral knowledge, the existence of moral facts, the nature of moral arguments, and the relationship between morality and rationality. Philosophers discussed include Moore, Ayer, Stevenson, Hare, Foot, and Mackie. Some background in moral or political theory is recommended. Enrollment limited to 15. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="350"/><a name="PHIL350"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 350. Seminar on Major Thinkers.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course examines in depth the writings of a major philosopher. Thinkers who may be discussed include Plato, Aristotle, Plotinus, Descartes, Spinoza, Leibniz, Hume, Marx, Wittgenstein, and Quine.  Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="351"/><a name="PHIL351"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 351. Kant.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course is an intensive study of Kant's <span class="cite">Critique of Pure Reason</span>. Interpretations by contemporary critics are considered. Prerequisite(s): Philosophy 272.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Offered with varying frequency. M. Okrent.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C066">Early Modern World (C066)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="PHIL360"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365"/><a name="PHIL365"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 365. Special Topics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A course or seminar offered from time to time and reserved for a special topic selected by the department. <br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365A"/><a name="PHIL365A"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 365A. Human Nature.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines human nature from philosophical, evolutionary, and cultural perspectives. Students focus on ideals of rationality, the role of the emotions, the nature of free will, the role of culture and biology, and conceptions of human happiness. Recommended background: two philosophy courses. Prerequisite(s): one of the following: Philosophy 150, 256, 271, or 272. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395"/><a name="PHIL395"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 395. Seminar: Topics in Logic.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students address topics from among: basic metatheory of first-order logic, including soundness and completeness; computability theory and mathematical logic, including Turing machines, the halting problem, and G&#246;del's incompleteness results; and modal logics and possible worlds semantics. Prerequisite(s): Philosophy 195. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="PHIL457"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students register for Philosophy 457 in the fall semester and for Philosophy 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both Philosophy 457 and 458.   <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457, 458"/><a name="PHIL457, 458"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 457, 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students register for Philosophy 457 in the fall semester and for Philosophy 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both Philosophy 457 and 458.   <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="PHIL458"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students register for Philosophy 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both Philosophy 457 and 458.   <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s17"/><a name="PHILs17"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL s17. The Ethics of Care.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Several decades ago, Carol Gilligan introduced the idea that women might speak about morality in a different voice from men. Her important work has inspired and contributed to the development of the ethics of care, an approach to ethics that takes women's moral commitments and orientations seriously. This unit presents a careful study of the ethics of care and a critical examination of it. Students read both the historically significant works from which the ethics of care began as well as recent developments of the theory and criticism of it from within feminist circles.  <span class="gened">[W1]</span> Offered with varying frequency. S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s21"/><a name="PHILs21"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL s21. Philosophy of Psychology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc"> The fundamental question philosophers of psychology ask is: Can there be a science of the mind? The major obstacle to an affirmative answer is the nature of consciousness. Thus a significant part of the unit focuses on the philosophical problem of consciousness. Emotions, however, also pose problems for the science of the mind, and are also implicated in the nature of consciousness. A second focus of the unit is the nature of emotion and its relationship to consciousness. Prerequisite(s): one course in philosophy. Not open to students who have received credit for Philosophy 232. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every other year. S. Stark.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s25"/><a name="PHILs25"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL s25. Asian and Islamic Ethical Systems.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This unit provides a comparative study of Islamic and several Asian conceptions of ethics, including Confucian, Buddhist, and Hindu belief systems. Students carry out their own research, focusing on the beliefs, practices, and social structure of a particular tradition or community of their choice. The unit ends with seminars in which students share the results of their research. Prerequisite(s): one course in philosophy. Enrollment limited to 15. Offered with varying frequency. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s26"/><a name="PHILs26"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL s26. Biomedical Ethics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">During the past forty years, the rapid changes in the biological sciences and medical technology have thoroughly transformed the practice of medicine. The added complexity and power of medicine has in turn revolutionized the responsibilities and duties that accompany the medical professions. This unit explores the values and norms governing medical practice; the rights and responsibilities of health care providers and patients; the justification for euthanasia; and the problems of access, allocation, and rationing of health care services.  Not open to students who have received credit for First-Year Seminars 362. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 12. Offered with varying frequency. D. Cummiskey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C031">Philosophy and Psychology (C031)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="PHILs50"/><h4 class="crsname">PHIL s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=381&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>

               