<div class="Course"><a name="101"/><a name="THEA101"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 101. Theater and Film: An Introductory Survey.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to drama on stage and in motion pictures. Beginning with a discussion of action, plot, and character, the course moves on to consider the elements of theatrical performance&#8212;including acting, directing, and design&#8212;as well as important plays from the Greeks to the present. These may include works by Sophocles, Shakespeare, Ibsen, Chekhov, Brecht, and Beckett. The course then shifts focus to film, examining the elements of mise-en-sc&#232;ne, cinematography, editing, and sound, and concluding with a study of major films from the silent era to the twenty-first century. These may include works by Chaplin, Wells, Bergman, Hitchcock, Scorsese, and David Lynch. Normally offered every year. M. Andrucki.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C019">Film and Media Studies (C019)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C075">Filmmaking in Cultural Context (C075)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C074">Shakespearean Acting (C074)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="104"/><a name="DN/TH104"/><h4 class="crsname">DN/TH 104. What is Performance?.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this course students think critically about theater and dance performance from the point of view of makers, performers, audiences, and society. Students see and discuss live performance throughout the semester and explore historical and current ideas in performance from inside and out. Not open to students who have received credit for FYS 437. Enrollment limited to 40. C. Hinkle.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="130"/><a name="THEA130"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 130. Introduction to Design.</h4><span class="CourseDesc"> The creation of theater is a synthesis of text, performance, and visual imagery. This course explores how the visual aspect of theatrical design affects the way an audience perceives, feels, and responds to text and action. Students learn to use line, mass, color, and texture to communicate metaphoric and thematic ideas as they relate to the overall theatrical experience. They examine how forms of art, architecture, and music use these tools to influence and transform the audience, and build on this foundation to create a design vocabulary for theater. Students discuss how clothing, adornment, and body language influence the way individuals perceive others and present themselves.  They learn the fundamentals of collaborative creation, and design scenery and costumes for a classic work of dramatic literature.  Required of all majors.  No previous art or theater training is required. Enrollment limited to 14. Normally offered every year. B. McDowell.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C029">Visible Ideas: 2D and 3D Design (C029)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="132"/><a name="THEA132"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 132. Theater Technology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course provides a look "behind the curtain" to reveal the secrets of theater magic. Students learn the geography of various types of theaters as well as mechanical and electrical systems. They are introduced to the materials and methods for fabricating scenery and rigging, practice the safe use of woodworking tools, experiment with painted scenic finishes, and learn the basics of stage lighting and sound. Many of the skills introduced in this class are transferable to other artistic practices or domestic needs. This is a hands-on course; all students participate in the preparation and presentation of theater department productions.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 14. M. Reidy.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C029">Visible Ideas: 2D and 3D Design (C029)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="200"/><a name="THEA200"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 200. The Classical Stage.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">We still measure theatrical excellence by the achievements of ancient Greece and Rome, Elizabethan England, and seventeenth-century France. This course studies selected plays and works of critical theory from those remarkable times and places. Authors may include Aeschylus, Sophocles, Euripides, Aristophanes, Plato, Aristotle, Plautus, Terence, Horace, Marlowe, Shakespeare, Jonson, Webster, Corneille, Racine, Moli&#232;re, and the neoclassical theorists of France and Italy. The viewing of filmed versions of several of the plays on the syllabus reveals the continuing vigor of these classical works in performance. Open to first-year students. M. Andrucki.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C066">Early Modern World (C066)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="205"/><a name="THEA205"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 205. Shakespeare on Film.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of the film versions of several plays by William Shakespeare. These may include<span class="cite"> Hamlet</span>, <span class="cite">King Lear</span>, <span class="cite">Macbeth</span>, <span class="cite">Richard III</span>, <span class="cite">Henry V</span>, <span class="cite">Romeo and Juliet</span>, <span class="cite">Much Ado about Nothing</span>, <span class="cite">Titus Andronicus</span>, and <span class="cite">A Midsummer Night's Dream</span>. Film directors may include Reinhardt, Olivier, Kurosawa, Kozintsev, Branagh, and Taymor. Readings in film analysis and criticism supplement the close study of the texts of the plays and careful viewing of the films. Open to first-year students. M. Andrucki.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C075">Filmmaking in Cultural Context (C075)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="220"/><a name="THEA220"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 220. The Modern Stage: Ibsen to O'Neill.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The premiere in 1879 of Henrik Ibsen's incendiary masterpiece, <span class="em">A Doll House</span>, sparked an explosion of creativity in Western theater and drama over the next eight decades. This course studies several of the most important plays staged during that turbulent period. In addition to Ibsen, authors may include Strindberg, Chekhov, Shaw, Pirandello, Brecht, Williams, Hansberry, and O'Neill. Students also read critics and theorists who have discussed the nature and purpose of the stage during this revolutionary period. Viewings of filmed scenes from several of the plays on the syllabus help to reveal their power in performance. Open to first-year students. M. Andrucki.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C024">Modern Europe (C024)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=EUS">European Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="221"/><a name="AV/TH221"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/TH 221. Performance Art.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Performance art is live art performed by artists. In this course, students investigate the history and theories of performance art through readings, screenings, discussions and the creation of original works. They experiment with a variety of performance elements including movement, design, media, text, voice and sound. The class collaborates to create site/historic-specific performance events and individuals make a self-directed original work.  <span class="crsaddmod">Course reinstated beginning Fall 2016.</span> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 20. One-time offering. G. Berg.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C023">Improvisation and Experimentation in the Arts (C023)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="222"/><a name="THEA222"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 222. The Modern Stage: Beckett to the Present.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An overview of drama and theater from the landmark premiere of Beckett's <span class="cite">Waiting for Godot</span> in 1953 until the present. Authors may include Genet, Pinter, Ionesco, Albee, Shepard, Mamet, Churchill,  August Wilson, Suzan-Lori Parks, and other contemporary British, American, and continental dramatists.  Students also read critics and theorists who have written on the nature and purpose of the stage during this period. Viewing filmed scenes from several of the plays under study helps to reveal their power in performance. M. Andrucki.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=EUS">European Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="223"/><a name="THEA223"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 223. Theories of Drama: Theater and Film.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">What is the purpose of drama? To teach morality? To bring about social change? To provide wonder and delight? And how should drama accomplish this purpose? Through the power of language? Or the force of visual images? By telling compelling stories? By portraying complex characters? This course explores these questions through readings from classical, neoclassical, romantic, modern, and postmodern authors including Plato, Aristotle, Horace, Castelvetro, Johnson, Coleridge, Nietzsche, Brecht, Artaud, Eisenstein, Bazin, and Mulvey. Prerequisite(s): at least one course in history or the humanities.  <span class="crsaddmod">Course renumbered beginning Fall 2016.</span> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. M. Andrucki.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="230"/><a name="CI/TH230"/><h4 class="crsname">CI/TH 230. Drama and Theater of China.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Nothing is impossible in Chinese theater. On stage, we see a wronged soul lamenting his tragic death, a young lady being brought back to life by true love years after passing away, and a series of misunderstandings and coincidences twisting a funeral into a comedy.  Chinese people celebrate happiness, joy, crisis, dilemma, desperation, and pain through theater. In this course, students experience breathtaking performance practices, apprehend inspiring theatrical aesthetics, and examine Chinese theatrical performances from ancient shamanistic rituals to contemporary intercultural collaborations. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C033">Asian Art and Literature (C033)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C052">Asian Narrative Traditions (C052)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C047">Chinese Society and Culture (C047)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C067">The Translated World (C067)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="231"/><a name="THEA231"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 231. Scene Design.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course presents in-depth study of the creative and practical tools used by set designers to visually enrich and shape the theatrical experience. Students study a history of theatrical architecture and design, focusing on how they have shaped the uses of stage space and the vocabulary of modern scene design. The course builds on aesthetic fundamentals developed in THEA 130, and examines in greater depth the relationship between set designers and theatrical texts. Practically, students learn fundamentals of theatrical drafting, perspective and scale drawing, and model making. This course is recommended for students with an interest in the visual and emotional impact of effective scene design on drama and performance. Prerequisite(s): THEA 130, or an individual portfolio review. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 14. Instructor permission is required. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C029">Visible Ideas: 2D and 3D Design (C029)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="232"/><a name="THEA232"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 232. Lighting Design.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course provides an introduction to the unique aesthetic and technical decisions a lighting designer must make. Students examine the modern lighting aesthetic by studying popular culture and learning to translate these images to the stage. Students also are required to serve on a lighting crew for one of the department's productions and design part of the spring dance concert. Prerequisite(s) or corequisite(s): one of the following: THEA 101, 130, or 132. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 14. Instructor permission is required. M. Reidy.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C075">Filmmaking in Cultural Context (C075)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C029">Visible Ideas: 2D and 3D Design (C029)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="233"/><a name="THEA233"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 233. Costume Design.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In theater, as in life, clothes often "make the man." This course focuses on the myriad aspects of personality, position, and state of mind created and enhanced for stage characters by the art of costume design. Emphasis is placed on analyzing play texts and bringing characters to life. The course builds on aesthetic fundamentals developed in THEA 130, and offers further instruction in costume research, figure drawing, and sketching and painting skills used to present costume design information. This course is recommended for students with an interest in visual and emotional impact of effective design on drama and performance.  Prerequisite(s): THEA 130 or an individual portfolio review. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 14. B. McDowell.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C029">Visible Ideas: 2D and 3D Design (C029)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="235"/><a name="THEA235"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 235. Dress and Adornment in Western Culture.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Dress does not mean just fashion. The history of dress and human adornment includes political, sexual, economic, and cultural factors, often entwined in subtle or ephemeral ways with the aesthetics of what we consider fashion. This course, which is conducted in a survey format, begins with early Greek culture and continues into our own era, examining not just physical appearance, but these other factors that have driven the myriad changes in the history of dress throughout Western culture. Enrollment limited to 20. B. McDowell.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C083">Material Culture (C083)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="236"/><a name="THEA236"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 236. Pattern Drafting and Draping.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to the skills of pattern drafting, draping, and fitting garments, as well as some advanced costume construction skills and increased familiarity with the properties of different textiles. The course is structured as a series of lectures, demonstrations, and the completion of several hands-on projects by students. Recommended background: basic sewing skills. Enrollment limited to 12. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C006">Applying Mathematical Methods (C006)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C029">Visible Ideas: 2D and 3D Design (C029)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="240"/><a name="THEA240"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 240. Playwriting.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">After reviewing the fundamentals of dramatic structure and characterization, students write one full-length or two one-act plays. Recommended background: two courses in theater or dramatic literature. Not open to students who have received credit for THEA s41. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 15. C. Hinkle.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="242"/><a name="THEA242"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 242. Screenwriting.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course presents the fundamentals of screenwriting: concept, plot, structure, character development, conflict, dialogue, visual storytelling and format. Lectures, writing exercises, and analyses of films such as <span class="cite">The Social Network</span>, <span class="cite">Chinatown</span>, and <span class="cite">Rushmore</span> provide the student with the tools to create a short screenplay. Prerequisite(s): THEA 240. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 12. Instructor permission is required. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C019">Film and Media Studies (C019)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C075">Filmmaking in Cultural Context (C075)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="261"/><a name="THEA261"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 261. Beginning Acting.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces the student to the physiological processes involved in creative acting. The student learns the Stanislavski approach to the analysis of realistic and naturalistic drama. Exercises leading to relaxation, concentration, and imagination are included in an improvisational context. Studies in motivation, sense perception, and emotion-memory recall lead the student to beginning work on scene performance. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 16. Normally offered every semester. C. Hinkle, S. Wood.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C074">Shakespearean Acting (C074)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="262"/><a name="MU/TH262"/><h4 class="crsname">MU/TH 262. Performing Music Theater.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Learning to perform musical theater means learning to put the arts of singing, acting, and dancing&#8212;along with instrument-playing&#8212;at the service of dramatic characterization and interaction.  In this course scenes and numbers from shows in a variety of styles will be studied and learned; some of these will be performed in a cabaret evening at the end of the semester.  Open to students with some experience singing or dancing or acting or playing an instrument employed in musical theater.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2016.</span> Enrollment limited to 32. Normally offered every other year. J. Parakilas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="263"/><a name="THEA263"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 263. Voice and Speech.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students examine the nature and working of the human voice. Students explore ways to develop the voice's potential for expressive communication with exercises and the analysis of breathing, vocal relaxation, pitch, resonance, articulation, audibility, dialect, and text performance. Recommended background: one course in acting, performance, or public speaking.  Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 20. Normally offered every year. K. Vecsey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C085">Language and Literacy (C085)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C074">Shakespearean Acting (C074)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C005">Sound (C005)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270U"/><a name="DN/TH270U"/><h4 class="crsname">DN/TH 270U. Studio Dance: Alexander Technique.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Introduction to the principles and practices of the Alexander Technique, a practice that is critical for actors, dancers, and musicians for freeing the body for maximum efficiency by identifying unwanted movement patterns and constrictions. Alexander Technique helps teach performers relaxed and efficient ways to work that enhance performance and avoid injury. Class work includes simple anatomy, developmental movement, monologue work, analysis of movement, analysis of tension, journaling, breathing, and relaxation techniques. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270W"/><a name="DN/TH270W"/><h4 class="crsname">DN/TH 270W. Studio: Pilates.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to the exercises and principles of classical pilates. This physical training course uses the Pilates method and complementary conditioning techniques to develop core strength, alignment, and flexibility. This course is designed for physical performers, but useful for bodies of all kinds. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="290"/><a name="DN/TH290"/><h4 class="crsname">DN/TH 290. Performance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Working under faculty direction, students perform major roles in departmental productions as actors, designers, or technicians. Two semesters of DN/TH 290 constitute one course credit. No more than one course credit may be earned through DN/TH 290. Department chair permission is required. Staff, C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="340"/><a name="THEA340"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 340. Theories of Drama: Theater and Film.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">What is the purpose of drama? To teach morality? To bring about social change? To provide wonder and delight? And how should drama accomplish this purpose? Through the power of language? Or the force of visual images? By telling compelling stories? By portraying complex characters? This course explores these questions through readings from classical, neoclassical, romantic, modern, and postmodern authors including Plato, Aristotle, Horace, Castelvetro, Johnson, Coleridge, Nietzsche, Brecht, Artaud, Eisenstein, Bazin, and Mulvey. Prerequisite(s): at least one course in history or the humanities.  <span class="crsaddmod">Course renumbered as THEA 223 beginning Fall 2016.</span> Enrollment limited to 15. M. Andrucki.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="THEA360"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="362"/><a name="THEA362"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 362. Advanced Acting.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students extend their technique to explore two unique performance challenges&#8212;the classical dramas of the world's stages and the peculiar nature of comic performance. Prerequisite(s): THEA 261. Enrollment limited to 16. Instructor permission is required. S. Wood.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C074">Shakespearean Acting (C074)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="364"/><a name="THEA364"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 364. Advanced Voice and Speech.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of vocal and physical techniques for the exploration of theatrical texts. Specialized topics for the vocal professional include: characterization as it relates to voice and speech; cold readings; assessing and preparing for the vocal demands of a role; working with the vocal coach. Recommended for students intending to focus on acting or performance art in the senior thesis. Enrollment limited to 12. Instructor permission is required. K. Vecsey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C074">Shakespearean Acting (C074)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365"/><a name="THEA365"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 365. Special Topics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Offered occasionally in selected subjects. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="370"/><a name="THEA370"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 370. Directing.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to the art of directing, with an emphasis on creative and aesthetic problems and their solutions. Included is an examination of the director's relationship to the text, the design staff, and the actor. The approach is both theoretical and practical, involving readings, rehearsal observation, and the directing of scenes and short plays. Prerequisite(s) or corequisite(s): THEA 261. Open to first-year students. Instructor permission is required. Normally offered every year. S. Wood.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="THEA457"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">By departmental invitation only. Students undertake a substantial academic or artistic project. Students register for THEA 457 in the fall semester and for THEA 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both THEA 457 and 458.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="THEA458"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">By departmental invitation only. Students undertake a substantial academic or artistic project. Students register for THEA 457 in the fall semester and for THEA 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both THEA 457 and 458.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s26"/><a name="THEAs26"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA s26. Theater Production Workshop.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Working under faculty supervision or with visiting professional artists, student actors, directors, designers, and technicians undertake the tasks necessary to produce a play. Readings and discussions explore various ways of understanding and producing a text. May be taken more than once. Instructor permission is required. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s27"/><a name="THEAs27"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA s27. Scenic Painting.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Scene painting relies on visual illusion to create realism. Scenic painters must master creating paintings on a large scale that are seen at great distances: Michelangelo used many scene-painting skills to give life to the Sistine Chapel. In this course students learn specific techniques to turn paint and canvas visually into wood, marble, ornate stone carving, virtually anything that exists in three dimensions. In this course students master a broad array of tools and techniques that allow scenic painters to accomplish realistic visual effects. Projects including marbling, wood graining, trompe l'oeil, and painting on a large scale are designed to be cumulative, building skills that can be incorporated into individually chosen final projects. Enrollment limited to 10. B. McDowell.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C029">Visible Ideas: 2D and 3D Design (C029)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s33"/><a name="THEAs33"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA s33. Central European Theater and Film.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A study of Hungarian, Polish, and Czech theater and film, focusing on the impact on these arts of the social and political changes of the last sixty years, from the Polish and Hungarian uprisings of 1956 to the rebuilding of culture in the region following the collapse of the Soviet Bloc in 1989. While in Budapest, students view films at the Hungarian National Film Archive and attend performances of central European theater at the International Contemporary Drama Festival and the Hungarian National Theater. Visits to theater and film centers in Prague are also included. Prerequisite(s): some background in one of the following: theater, film, or modern European history. Enrollment limited to 18. Instructor permission is required. M. Andrucki, K. Vecsey.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C019">Film and Media Studies (C019)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C024">Modern Europe (C024)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=EUS">European Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s40"/><a name="RH/THs40"/><h4 class="crsname">RH/TH s40. Digital Video Production.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A hands-on, immersion course at Maine Media Workshops in Rockport, Maine, in the art of storytelling through digital video production, including both narrative fiction and documentary genres. Students learn cinematic language, storytelling, storyboarding, drafting a shooting script, location scouting, casting talent, rehearsing, blocking, and directing actors and crew. They also consider the roles of filmmakers, from producers and directors to camera and sound specialists and editors. Students are introduced to Final Cut Pro and the postproduction process. During the course students are expected to research, write, shoot, and edit a number of finished works. There is an extra fee for this course. Enrollment limited to 8. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C019">Film and Media Studies (C019)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C075">Filmmaking in Cultural Context (C075)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="THEAs50"/><h4 class="crsname">THEA s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="104"/><a name="DN/TH104"/><h4 class="crsname">DN/TH 104. What is Performance?.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this course students think critically about theater and dance performance from the point of view of makers, performers, audiences, and society. Students see and discuss live performance throughout the semester and explore historical and current ideas in performance from inside and out. Not open to students who have received credit for FYS 437. Enrollment limited to 40. C. Hinkle.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="151"/><a name="DANC151"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 151. Introduction to Dance Composition.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the physical language of dance. Students develop skills in inventing and structuring movement through improvisation and by creating solo and group studies. Significant reading, writing, and viewing assignments inform class discussions.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 15. C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C023">Improvisation and Experimentation in the Arts (C023)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C029">Visible Ideas: 2D and 3D Design (C029)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="240"/><a name="DANC240"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 240. Technique: A Kinesthetic Approach.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This modern dance technique course develops an understanding of the use of the physical body in dance. Topics include a basic study of anatomy; the mechanics of movement; and the use of time, space, and energy for efficient and effective movement. Recommended background: previous dance training. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[S]</span> R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="250"/><a name="DANC250"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 250. Early Modern Dance History.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">At the turn of the twentieth century, modern dance emerged as an exciting new art form. From Isadora Duncan to the collaborations of Cage and Cunningham, modern dance has been deeply rooted in innovative exploration and a convergence of diverse cultural expressions. This course focuses on the early dance pioneers, the ideas and conditions that informed their work, and their subsequent influences on the art world. Open to first-year students.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> C. Dilley, R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="251"/><a name="DANC251"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 251. Dance Composition.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An exploration of the craft and the art of making dance performance from human gesture. Readings, critical analysis, and informal showings support the complex process of creating a finished movement-based piece for public performance by the end of the semester. Prerequisite(s): DANC 151 or 253. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 9. Normally offered every year. C. Dilley, R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C023">Improvisation and Experimentation in the Arts (C023)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C029">Visible Ideas: 2D and 3D Design (C029)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="252"/><a name="AA/DN252"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/DN 252. Contemporary Issues in Dance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on current dance works and some of the issues that inform contemporary dance practices. Discussions include the ways in which choreographers, performers, and societies confront matters of political climate, cultural diversity, entertainment, globalization, and the politicized human body in dance. Open to first-year students.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="253"/><a name="DANC253"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 253. Dance Repertory Performance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students experience a variety of approaches to making and performing dance through intensive choreographic residencies with professional guest choreographers. The course culminates in a concert of the accumulated pieces at the end of the semester. Recommended background: previous dance experience. This course may be repeated for credit. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 12. Instructor permission is required. C. Dilley, R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="256"/><a name="INDS256"/><h4 class="crsname">INDS 256. Rites of Spring.</h4><span class="CourseDesc"><span class="cite">Le Sacre du printemps</span>&#8212;<span class="cite">The Rite of Spring&#8212;</span> began as a ballet, with music by Igor Stravinsky, choreography by Vaslav Nijinsky, and sets and costumes by Nicholas Roerich. Premiered in 1913 to riots in Paris, <span class="cite">The Rite of Spring</span> has lived on to become one of the most important pieces of music in the Western canon and the zenith of stature and daring for choreographers. This course examines where it came from and how it has evolved over time through dance works, music, and cultural context. Cross-listed in dance, music, and Russian.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C080">Music and Culture (C080)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="265"/><a name="DN/ED265"/><h4 class="crsname">DN/ED 265. Teaching through the Arts.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course considers arts education theory and policy, methods and models of arts education, and theories of creativity. Class sessions include large- and small-group work, participatory experiences, lectures, group discussions, and student-led activities and presentations. Through a thirty-hour field placement, students explore teaching in and through the arts. Recommended background: EDUC 231. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 18. (Community-Engaged Learning.) B. Sale.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C030">Children, Adolescents, School (C030)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270"/><a name="DANC270"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 270. Studio.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This series of studio courses provides instruction in a variety of dance styles and performing practices. DANC 270 may be repeated without limit. One-half credit is earned for each course completed. All 270 studio courses fulfill a physical education requirement. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Staff, C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270A"/><a name="DANC270A"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 270A. Studio: Modern I.</h4><span class="CourseDesc"> In this entry level modern technique course, students address problems of performance, practice, style, and form in order to build strong technique and enhanced artistry and understanding. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every semester. Staff, C. Dilley, R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C023">Improvisation and Experimentation in the Arts (C023)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270B"/><a name="DANC270B"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 270B. Studio: Ballet I.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this ballet technique course, students develop strong technique and enhance artistry through work on the traditional practice, style, vocabulary, and form of classical ballet.  Recommended background: experience in dance. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every semester. Staff, C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270C"/><a name="DANC270C"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 270C. Studio: Modern Partnering.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Contemporary partnering skills, including contact improvisation skills, weight sharing, spatial and physical relationships, and personal responsibility, are combined with modern dance technique.  Recommended background: sufficient experience in dance. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C023">Improvisation and Experimentation in the Arts (C023)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270D"/><a name="DANC270D"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 270D. Studio: Repertory Styles.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This advanced modern technique course explores a variety of approaches to modern dance training and practice as experienced with different guest teachers throughout the semester. Recommended background: sufficient experience in dance. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. C. Dilley, R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270E"/><a name="DANC270E"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 270E. Studio: Jazz I.</h4><span class="CourseDesc"> In this mixed-level technique course, students address jazz dance performance, practice, style, and form in order to build strong technique as well as to enhance artistry and understanding.  Recommended background: experience in dance. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270F"/><a name="DANC270F"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 270F. Studio: Advanced Jazz Repertory.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This jazz technique course explores a variety of approaches to creating dance repertory in a jazz style. It is for advanced dancers and leads to performance at the end of the semester. The instructor approves enrollment based on the level of experience of the student. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270G"/><a name="DANC270G"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 270G. Studio: Dance Ensemble, Intermediate.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This intermediate-level course focuses on modern technique, clarity of intention, and general performance skills, in order to maintain a strong technique and develop one's personal contribution to ensemble dancing. Recommended background: intermediate experience in dance and some modern training. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every year. C. Dilley, R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C023">Improvisation and Experimentation in the Arts (C023)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270H"/><a name="DANC270H"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 270H. Studio: Ballet II.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this ballet technique course, students strengthen their technique and enhance their artistry through the practice of classical ballet. This level is appropriate for intermediate or advanced ballet dancers who are already at ease with the ballet vocabulary. Recommended background: a solid experience in ballet technique. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every semester. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270I"/><a name="DANC270I"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 270I. Studio: Improvisation.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students explore improvisational dance skills essential to any style of dance through the use of body weight, momentum, and physical contact. Some familiarity with any form of dance is helpful. Open to first-year students. R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C023">Improvisation and Experimentation in the Arts (C023)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270J"/><a name="DANC270J"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 270J. Studio: World Dance Forms.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">All cultures dance but the approach to dance varies greatly from place to place. Students explore a culturally specific dance form, learning the basic techniques, movement, and a dance or dance practices from that form. The form taught in any given semester varies according to the expertise of the instructor. Open to first-year students. Staff, C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270K"/><a name="DANC270K"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 270K. Studio: Hip Hop.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this mixed-level technique course, students address hip-hop dance performance, practice, style, and form in order to build strong technique as well as to enhance artistry and understanding. Recommended background: some experience in dance. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Staff, C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C023">Improvisation and Experimentation in the Arts (C023)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270M"/><a name="DANC270M"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 270M. Studio: Dance Ensemble, Advanced.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This advanced-level course focuses on modern technique, clarity of intention, and general performance skills, in order to maintain a strong technique and develop one's personal contribution to ensemble dancing. Recommended background: advanced experience in dance and some modern training. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Normally offered every year. C. Dilley, R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270U"/><a name="DN/TH270U"/><h4 class="crsname">DN/TH 270U. Studio Dance: Alexander Technique.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Introduction to the principles and practices of the Alexander Technique, a practice that is critical for actors, dancers, and musicians for freeing the body for maximum efficiency by identifying unwanted movement patterns and constrictions. Alexander Technique helps teach performers relaxed and efficient ways to work that enhance performance and avoid injury. Class work includes simple anatomy, developmental movement, monologue work, analysis of movement, analysis of tension, journaling, breathing, and relaxation techniques. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270W"/><a name="DN/TH270W"/><h4 class="crsname">DN/TH 270W. Studio: Pilates.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An introduction to the exercises and principles of classical pilates. This physical training course uses the Pilates method and complementary conditioning techniques to develop core strength, alignment, and flexibility. This course is designed for physical performers, but useful for bodies of all kinds. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="290"/><a name="DN/TH290"/><h4 class="crsname">DN/TH 290. Performance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Working under faculty direction, students perform major roles in departmental productions as actors, designers, or technicians. Two semesters of DN/TH 290 constitute one course credit. No more than one course credit may be earned through DN/TH 290. Department chair permission is required. Staff, C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C028">Theater Arts (C028)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="290G"/><a name="DN/MU290G"/><h4 class="crsname">DN/MU 290G. West African Music and Dance Ensemble.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Directed by master drummer Jordan Benissan, a native of Togo, West Africa, this ensemble course offers students a chance to study and perform dance and music from several West African cultures. Students gain hands-on experience with various instruments, including drums, rattles, and bells, and learn about multiple traditions of West African dance and song. The group performs at least once per semester. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 25. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C022">Considering Africa (C022)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="300"/><a name="DANC300"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 300. Bates Dance Festival.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course provides Bates dance students with the opportunity to participate in the Bates Dance Festival Professional Training Program. Full participation in the festival requires four daily courses including a technique course, a composition/creative process course or repertory course, an improvisation course, and an elective from among the festival's offerings in complementary studies. Festival courses are taught by leading scholars, artists, and practitioners in their fields. Students attend concerts, informal showings, discussions, and video presentations in addition to their courses. This course may be repeated for credit. Enrollment limited to 10. Instructor permission is required. C. Dilley, R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C023">Improvisation and Experimentation in the Arts (C023)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="340"/><a name="DANC340"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 340. Technique: The Body in Motion.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Continued study and practice of modern dance technique, focusing on the physicality of movement and the structure of the human body. Prerequisite(s): DANC 240. R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="351"/><a name="DANC351"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 351. Advanced Composition Seminar.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A further investigation of the compositional tools used in creating dance and the continued development of a better understanding of the intention behind the movement.  The course emphasizes the personal exploration of creative process, craft, artistic intention, and integrity in dance making. This course may be repeated for credit. Prerequisite(s): DANC 251. Staff, C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="DANC360"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every semester. C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="DANC457"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A substantial dance-related project, usually in the form of choreography. Students register for DANC 457 in the fall. A choreographic thesis is available only to students who have completed the two additional courses in creative process, including DANC 351. <span class="crsaddmod"/>  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. C. Dilley, R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="DANC458"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A substantial dance-related project, usually in the form of choreography. Students register for DANC 458 in the winter semester. A choreographic thesis is available only to students who have completed the two additional courses in creative process, including DANC 351. <span class="crsaddmod"/>  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. C. Dilley, R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s29"/><a name="DN/EDs29"/><h4 class="crsname">DN/ED s29. Tour, Teach, Perform.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course uses the diverse collective skills of the students in the class as base material for the creation of a theater/dance piece that tours to elementary schools. The first two weeks are spent working intensively with a guest artist to create the performance piece. The remaining weeks are spent touring that piece, along with age-appropriate movement workshops, to elementary schools throughout the region. This course open to performers and would-be performers of all kinds. This course may be repeated for credit. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 20. (Community-Engaged Learning.) Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C030">Children, Adolescents, School (C030)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s32"/><a name="DANCs32"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC s32. Building a Dance Practice.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students take a daily intermediate modern dance technique class and develop an individual project in an area of dance research such as choreography, improvisation, pedagogy, criticism/theory, or art therapy. Recommended background: at least one college-level dance course or intermediate level of proficiency in any dance form. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. R. Boggia.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C012">The Collaborative Project (C012)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C023">Improvisation and Experimentation in the Arts (C023)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="DANCs50"/><h4 class="crsname">DANC s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. C. Dilley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C011">Dance (C011)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=1199&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>

               