<div class="Course"><a name="100"/><a name="WGST100"/><h4 class="crsname">WGST 100. Introduction to Women and Gender Studies.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">An interdisciplinary study of women and gender in cross-cultural and historical perspective. Emphasis is given to the diversities of race, class, ethnicity, age, (dis)ability, sexuality, nationality, and religion.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="121G"/><a name="EN/WS121G"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/WS 121G. Asian American Women Writers.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines from a sociohistorical perspective fictional, autobiographical, and critical writings by Asian American women including Meena Alexander, Sui Sin Far, Gish Jen, Maxine Hong Kingston,  Tahira Naqvi, Cathy Song, Jhumpa Lahiri, and Hisaye Yamamoto. Students explore their concerns with personal and cultural identity, as both Asian and American, as females, as minorities, and often as postcolonial subjects. The course highlights the varied immigration and social histories of women from different Asian countries, often homogenized as "Oriental" in mainstream American cultural representations. Enrollment limited to 25 per section. (Race, Ethnicity, or Diasporic Literature.) (Post-1800.) L. Dhingra.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C052">Asian Narrative Traditions (C052)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C059">Colonialism (C059)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C014">Globalization (C014)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C037">Identity, Race, and Ethnicity (C037)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C087">South Asian Studies (C087)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C050">Women and Gender in Asia (C050)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C060">Women and Writing (C060)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="130"/><a name="INDC130"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 130. Food in Ancient Greece and Rome.</h4><span class="CourseDesc"> Participants in this course study food in ancient Greece and Rome: the history of the food supply for agrarian and urban populations; malnutrition, its probable impact on ancient economies, and its uneven impact on populations; famine; the symbolism of the heroic banquet&#8212;a division of the sacrificial animal among ranked members of society, and between men and gods; cuisine and delicacies of the rich; forbidden food; the respective roles of men and women in food production, and their unequal access to food supply; dietary transgression; and sacred food. Cross-listed in classical and medieval studies, history, and women and gender studies. Not open to students who have received credit for CMS s28. Enrollment limited to 50. (European.) (Premodern.) D. O'Higgins.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C083">Material Culture (C083)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=CMS">Classical and Medieval Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="155"/><a name="PT/WS155"/><h4 class="crsname">PT/WS 155. Gender, Power, and Political Systems.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course scrutinizes several sites where power is produced &#8212; constitutions, international politics, political theory, voting, social movements, and globalization&#8212; in order to assess the impact of gender on the status, behavior, and authority of differnet political actors. Recognizing how race, class, sexuality, and nation matter, students consider why women are under-represented in nearly all governments and how women make more of a difference in national and global politics than the images of "men in suits" imply. Students examine questions concepts, and theories that acknowledge women's political agency and help evaluate their influences across a range&#8212;ancient to emerging&#8212; of political systems. Not open to students who have received credit for PLTC 155. Enrollment limited to 40. (Identities and Interests.) (Philosophical, Literary, and Legal Studies.) L. Hill.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="201"/><a name="AA/WS201"/><h4 class="crsname">AA/WS 201. Race, Ethnicity, and Feminist Thought.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">While all courses in the women and gender studies program examine gender in relation to other critical categories of social identity and experience, this course focuses on race, ethnicity, and national power at their intersections with gender. Using perspectives from the social sciences, the humanities, and critical-race, womanist, feminist, and queer theories, students examine feminist efforts at self-definition and self-sufficiency, as well as feminist contributions to knowledge, social and political activism, and theorizing.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. L. Hill.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C037">Identity, Race, and Ethnicity (C037)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="202"/><a name="WGST202"/><h4 class="crsname">WGST 202. Queer and Trans Sports Studies.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course brings queer studies and trans studies perspectives to sport, looking at practice, representation, discourse, and relations among them. Topics include the reach into the lives of all athletes of gender binarism and gender segregation; the regulation of transgender, gender nonconforming, and intersex athletes, including the delineation of those categories, in the context of other discourses around human variation in sport; the roles of raced masculinities, femininities, heteronormativities, and homonormativities in the valuation of athleticism, athletes, and sports; and issues from pleasure to pink-washing surrounding the participation of queer-identified people in recreational, competitive, and professional sport. Recommended background: one course on the study of gender, sexuality, queer studies, trans studies, and/or sports studies.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> E. Rand.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="203"/><a name="RE/WS203"/><h4 class="crsname">RE/WS 203. Women, Gender, and Islam.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The course introduces normative Islamic traditions and Islamic discourses about women and gender from inception of the religion in the seventh century <span class="smcaps">C.E.</span> to the present day. It surveys Muslim women's experiences across a broad span of historical periods and cultural arenas, from the Middle East, Asia, and Africa to Europe and North America. Encouraging a critical postcolonial reflexive perspective and emphasizing Muslim women's voices and historical agency, the course draws on a range of scholarly disciplines and methods including historical, anthropological, literary, and art historical studies to explore understandings beyond common stereotypes of "the oppressed Muslim woman." Recommended background: WGST 100. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="204"/><a name="CM/WS204"/><h4 class="crsname">CM/WS 204. Gender and the Body in Ancient Greece.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">How did people in ancient Greece think about the categories of male and female? How did these categories intersect with others, such as social status, age, and ethnicity? This course considers issues of gender in archaic and classical Greece and looks at how Greek people thought about the body, sexuality, and "transgressive" behavior and individuals. Students analyze literary texts (in translation) as well as medical, religious, and legal evidence&#8212;inscriptional and textual&#8212;and modern scholarship. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 35. D. O'Higgins.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C054">The Ancient World (C054)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="207"/><a name="RE/WS207"/><h4 class="crsname">RE/WS 207. Eve, Adam, and the Serpent.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the historical formation of Genesis 1&#8211;3 against the background of its literary, cultural, and historical context and its subsequent interpretation and use in Jewish, Christian, and Islamic traditions. Special attention is given to the ways in which the biblical texts have been interpreted and used to imagine, promote, and justify social orders &#8212; both hierarchical and egalitarian &#8212; as well as how the construction of gender relations links to the ways in which other social institutions are articulated and justified. Topics include the creation of the cosmos, characterizations of the Creator, the origins and perfection of humanity, the origins of evil, and the human fall from perfection. Enrollment limited to 40. C. Baker.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="220"/><a name="PT/WS220"/><h4 class="crsname">PT/WS 220. Gender, War, and Peace.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course uses gender as an analytical tool to examine the history of war and peace. How do war and militarization construct masculinities and femininities? What types of roles have women played in the making of war and in the making of peace? How has gender socialization influenced people's analysis of and participation in war and in peace activism? What are the gender politics of the politics of war and of peacemaking? How is gender deployed in current war zones and in current movements for peace? Recommended background: WGST 100.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. (Governance and Conflict.) (Political Economy.) M. Plastas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="238"/><a name="INDC238"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 238. Sexuality Movements.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to social movement theory and interest group politics in the United States via the case study of gay, lesbian, bisexual, transgender, and queer (LGBTQ) politics from the immediate post-World War II period to the present, and examines the relationship of sexuality to the racial and gender dynamics of American identity-based social movements. The course traces the development of research methodologies to study collective action from early rational choice models to resource mobilization theory to new social movement models and political opportunity and process models. How the LGBTQ movements drew upon, expanded, and challenged foundations established by both African American civil rights and feminism is also explored. A range of source materials includes political science, sociology, and history monographs and articles, primary source documents, literature, and film. Cross-listed in politics, sociology, and women and gender studies.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 30. (Identities and Interests.) (Institutional Politics.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> S. Engel.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C013">Law and Society (C013)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="245"/><a name="PT/WS245"/><h4 class="crsname">PT/WS 245. Democratizing States and Gender Politics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">How do gender politics shape transitions to democracy? Does political change create opportunities for increasing women's representation in politics, leadership, and access to decision-making? Under what circumstances do women oppose authoritarian regimes? How does gender affect prospects for democracy? This course uses a comparative approach to investigate cases of regime change in Latin America, Eastern and Central Europe, the Middle East, and sub-Saharan Africa in order to understand whether and how political change creates possibilities for democratizing gender relations and politics. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. (Identities and Interests.) L. Hill.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="248"/><a name="EN/WS248"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/WS 248. Queer Studies.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course considers the production and regulation of gender and sexuality in relation to norms of identity, social organization, and embodiment, and the interconnections of queer sexualities and queer genders with each other and with race, economic status, citizenship, and other axes of difference. While the course engages the body of scholarship understood in the 1990s and beyond to form a field called "Queer Theory," it also focuses on activist and scholarly work generated before, outside, and against its boundaries, especially in Queer of Color critique and Trans Studies, with central attention to lives and thinking of people embodying or associates with marginalized genders and sexualities. Recommended background: one course on the study of gender, sexuality, queer studies, and/or trans studies.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2017.</span> Enrollment limited to 30. (Community-Engaged Learning.) (Critical thinking.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> Normally offered every year. S. Engel, E. Osucha, E. Rand.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="250"/><a name="INDC250"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 250. Interdisciplinary Studies: Methods and Modes of Inquiry.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Interdisciplinarity involves more than a meeting of disciplines. Practitioners stretch methodological norms and reach across disciplinary boundaries. Through examination of a single topic, this course introduces students to interdisciplinary methods of analysis. Students examine what practitioners actually do and work to become practitioners themselves. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, and women and gender studies. Prerequisite(s): AAS 100, ACS 100, or WGST 100, and one other course in African American studies, American cultural studies, or women and gender studies.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 40. Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="254"/><a name="PT/WS254"/><h4 class="crsname">PT/WS 254. Gender Matters: U.S. Women and Politics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">What difference has women's visible entry into U.S. politics, over the last forty years made in the everyday lives of most women? Just as notions of ideal womanhood and manhood have molded politics since America's founding, politics shapes women's and men's lives as citizens, workers, and parents. What bodies matter when leaders are selected, policy agendas are set, and resource allocation decisions are made? How do women's participation and influence&#8212;as decisive voters, social movement activists, persuasive legislators, and presidential candidates&#8212;affect the conduct of politics or thinking about what matters to the nation? This course recognizes U.S. women&#8212;variously positioned in racial, class, sexual, and cultural communities&#8212;as political subjects and reviews concepts, frameworks, and theories used to make sense of both changes and continuity in women's status, participation, and influence on public life and decision making. Not open to students who have received credit for PT/WS 255. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. (Identities and Interests.) (Institutional Politics.) L. Hill.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="255"/><a name="INDC255"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 255. Modern Japanese Women Writers.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">How have modern Japanese women writers portrayed the complexities of their lives and the worlds in which they lived? How do they negotiate the gendered institutions of the society in which they live? How has their work shaped what is known as "Japanese literature" within and outside of Japan? Students consider issues such as family, friendship, power, gender roles, selfhood, the female body, and aging in reading a range of novels, short stories, and poems. Supplemental readings provide background in Japanese literary history and gender theory. Selected authors include Higuchi Ichiy&#333;, Hayashi Fumiko, Enchi Fumiko, Ohba Minako, Kurahashi Yumiko, Tawara Machi, and Kawakami Mieko. Readings and discussion are in English. No prior experience studying Japanese culture necessary. Cross-listed in Asian studies, Japanese, and women and gender studies. Open to first-year students.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> J. Sturiano.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C053">Asian Modernity (C053)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C052">Asian Narrative Traditions (C052)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C019">Film and Media Studies (C019)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C046">Japanese Society and Culture (C046)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C067">The Translated World (C067)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C050">Women and Gender in Asia (C050)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C060">Women and Writing (C060)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ASIA">Asian Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="256"/><a name="MU/WS256"/><h4 class="crsname">MU/WS 256. Opera and Gender.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Considering topics from mad and dying heroines to cross-dressing characters to real-life divas, this course serves as an introduction to opera history and representations of gender on the operatic stage from the seventeenth century to the present. Engaging with the music, texts, and visuals of select operatic works, students explore a range of topics including gender subversion, castrati, pants roles, and cross-dressing; the hero, antihero, and the femme fatale; women in positions of power; madness, exoticism, and disease; intersections of gender, race, and class; diva culture; female opera composers, librettists, and directors; and women in the opera industry today.  <span class="crsaddmod">Course crosslisted beginning Winter 2017.</span> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. One-time offering. C. Thomas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C080">Music and Culture (C080)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="262"/><a name="PL/WS262"/><h4 class="crsname">PL/WS 262. Philosophy and Feminism.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">One central project of feminist philosophy is the use of philosophical methods to think carefully about important and distinctive features of the lives of women, and also about the concepts employed in the feminist political movement and similar social movements, such as those centered around race, class, disability, and sexuality. Topics include: what it is to be a woman; what it is to face discrimination or oppression; science and society, particularly genders in science; sex and sexuality; reproduction; the family; gender in popular culture; and the body and appearance, including the fashion and beauty industries. Not open to students who have received credit for PHIL 262. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. Normally offered every year. S. Stark, L. Ashwell.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C042">Philosophy (C042)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="267"/><a name="INDC267"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 267. Blood, Genes, and American Culture.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Places recent popular and scientific discussions of human heredity and genetics in broader social, political, and historical context, focusing on shifting definitions of personhood. Topics include the ownership and exchange of human bodies and body parts, the development of assisted reproductive technologies, and the emergence of new forms of biological citizenship. Recommended background: course work in biology and/or women and gender studies. Cross-listed in American cultural studies, history, and women and gender studies.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 40. (Modern. ) (United States.) R. Herzig.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C083">Material Culture (C083)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="270"/><a name="SO/WS270"/><h4 class="crsname">SO/WS 270. Sociology of Gender.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on the social construction of gender through a consideration of a series of interrelated social institutions and practices central to gender stratification. Emphasis is placed on the intersections between gender inequality and inequalities of race/ethnicity, class, sexual orientation, and nation. Recommended background: one previous course in the sociology or women and gender studies. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. (Community-Engaged Learning.) E. Kane.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="275"/><a name="AN/WS275"/><h4 class="crsname">AN/WS 275. Gender and Culture.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Comparative analysis of the social construction of gender in a wide range of contemporary societies, focusing on the contrast among African, Asian, and North Atlantic notions of gender identity and gender relations. Students work toward a deeper understanding of gender diversity, confronting their own cultural assumptions. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. (Community-Engaged Learning.) Normally offered every year. E. Eames.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C026">Culture and Meaning (C026)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="282"/><a name="PT/WS282"/><h4 class="crsname">PT/WS 282. Constitutional Law II: Rights and Identities.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces students to constitutional interpretation and development in civil rights and race equality jurisprudence, gender equality jurisprudence, sexual orientation law, and matters related to privacy and autonomy (particularly sexual autonomy involving contraception and abortion access). Expanding, contracting, or otherwise altering the meaning of a right involves a range of actors in a variety of venues, not only courts. Therefore, students consider rights from a "law and society" perspective, which focuses on analyzing judicial rulings as well as evaluating the social conceptualization, representation, and grassroots mobilization around these rights. Prerequisite(s): PLTC 115. Recommended background: PLTC 216. Enrollment limited to 30. (Identities and Interests.) (Philosophical, Literary, and Legal Studies.) S. Engel.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C037">Identity, Race, and Ethnicity (C037)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C013">Law and Society (C013)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="287"/><a name="AV/WS287"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/WS 287. Gender and Visual Culture.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course concerns gender in the making and viewing of visual culture, with emphasis on the later twentieth and early twenty-first centuries, and the roles of visual culture in the construction of  gendered identities. Topics include the use of the visual in artistic, political, and historical representations of gendered people; queer and transgenderings; the visualization of gender in relation to race, ethnicity, nationality, class, age, sex, and sexuality; and matters of censorship, circulation, and resources that affect the cultural production of people oppressed and/or marginalized by sex and/or gender. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30 per section. (Race, Sexuality, Gender.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> E. Rand.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="295"/><a name="AV/WS295"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/WS 295. The Decorated Body.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course analyzes the arts associated with the body, using the body as subject and as lens for theoretical discussions in relation to non-Western and Western cultures. Cross-cultural and cross-disciplinary, with particular attention to the body as gendered and raced, the course addresses the ways that the body has been adorned and manipulated as an artistic medium through practices including painting, scarification, surgical manipulation, tattooing, piercing, branding, and hair adornment. Enrollment limited to 25. (Non-Western Canon.) (Race, Sexuality, Gender.) Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C036">Color: Sight and Perception (C036)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C083">Material Culture (C083)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="299"/><a name="AV/WS299"/><h4 class="crsname">AV/WS 299. Gender in African Art.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the complex role of gender in African art and visual culture. Focused topics include gender divisions in artistic production, women in royal traditions, gender restrictions in viewing sacred arts, arts and visual culture celebrating women&#8217;s power, performative cross-dressing, gender identities in cultural performance, the personification of spirit spouses, and cis- and transgender expressions in contemporary art.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 30. (Non-Western Canon.) (Race, Sexuality, Gender.) Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C022">Considering Africa (C022)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="301A"/><a name="INDC301A"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 301A. Sex and the Modern City: European Cultures at the Fin-de-Si&#232;cle .</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Economic and political change during the 1800s revolutionized the daily lives of Europeans more profoundly than any previous century. By the last third of the century, the modern city became the stage for exploring and enacting new roles, new gender identities in particular. This course examines the cultural reverberations of these cataclysmic changes by focusing on sex, gender, and new urban spaces the decades around the turn of the twentieth century. Students consider the writings of Zola and Freud, investigate middle-class flirtations with the occult, and read about sensational crimes like those of Jack the Ripper. Cross-listed in European studies, history, women and gender studies. Not open to students who have received credit for INDS 390A. Enrollment limited to 15. (European.) (Modern. )  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> C. Shaw.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C057">The City in History: Urbanism and Constructed Spaces (C057)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=EUS">European Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="301Q"/><a name="HI/WS301Q"/><h4 class="crsname">HI/WS 301Q. A Woman's Place: Gender and Geography in the United States, 1800&#8211;Present.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Using a case study approach, this course looks at diverse American women from the early 1800s to the present and how they shaped, traversed, and contested the spaces they inhabited or were assigned, whether public or private, rural or urban, temporary or lifelong. Not open to students who have received credit for HI/WS 390Q. Enrollment limited to 15. (Modern. ) (United States.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> M. Creighton.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="301Z"/><a name="INDC301Z"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 301Z. Race and U.S. Women's Movements.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course focuses on how racial formations develop in women's movements and how gender ideologies take shape through racialization. Some of the movements examined include the woman's suffrage movement, the anti-lynching movement, the civil rights movement, moral reform movements, the welfare rights movement, the women's liberation movement, and the peace movement. Students analyze how the intertwined categories of race and gender shape various women's responses to debates about issues including citizenship, U.S. foreign policy, reproductive rights, and immigration. Students consider current theoretical and methodological debates and examine the topic through the perspectives of women in various ethnic and racial groups. Cross-listed in history, politics, and women and gender studies. Prerequisite(s): one course in women and gender studies. Enrollment limited to 15. (Identities and Interests.) (Institutional Politics.) (Modern. ) (United States.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> M. Plastas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="310"/><a name="RE/WS310"/><h4 class="crsname">RE/WS 310. Gender and Judaism.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this course, students explore aspects of Jewish culture and images of Jews and Judaism through the lenses of gender and sexuality. They examine ideologies, images, and practices from Jewish traditions with an eye to the ways in which gender and sexuality are constructed, maintained, contested, and/or transformed through them. Feminist Jews and Judaism serve as sources for insight and critique as well as constructive resources for religious reflection, ritual, and visions of Judaism's future. Enrollment limited to 15. C. Baker.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="311"/><a name="RE/WS311"/><h4 class="crsname">RE/WS 311. Buddhism and Gender.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the role of gender in Buddhist communities from the inception of the religious tradition to the modern day. How has gender identity influenced the development of this tradition? Where do we see gender in Buddhist literature, doctrine, and art? How do modern ideas of what "Buddhism" is affect change in the North American context, and how is this different from the Buddhist past? The course draws on a variety of sources, including literary, cinematic, and visual materials, to answer these questions. Special attention is given to how gender is presented in doctrinal texts, and the (dis)connection between these documents and the lived experiences of Buddhist people, as presented in interviews and autobiographies by Buddhist practitioners from a variety of moments and communities. Enrollment limited to 15. A. Melnick.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C002">Buddhism (C002)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C001">Religious Studies (C001)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="323"/><a name="SP/WS323"/><h4 class="crsname">SP/WS 323. Gendered Experiences in the Am&#233;ricas Borderlands.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students become acquainted with testimonies, film, comics, and fiction and nonfiction narratives that engage border tensions and issues of immigration in English and Spanish. Concepts such as sense of place, mobility, and permanence; histories of place; place of enunciation; transnational migration; and transnational historical networks are utilized as critical lenses to analyze gendered experiences of migration. All discussions and written assignments are in Spanish. Recommended background: SPAN 230. Prerequisite(s): one 200-level Spanish course above SPAN 211. Not open to first-years or sophomores. Not open to students who have received credit for SPAN 223. C. Aburto Guzm&#225;n.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C072">Latin American Studies (C072)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C032">Post/Colonial Issues in French and Spanish (C032)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C089">Spanish in Tarragona (C089)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="325"/><a name="INDC325"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 325. Black Feminist Literary Theory and Practice.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar examines literary theories that address the representation and construction of race, gender, and sexuality, particularly, but not exclusively, theories formulated and articulated by Afra-diasporic women such as Spillers, Ogunyemi, Henderson, Carby, Christian, Cobham, Valerie Smith, McDowell, Busia, Lubiano, and Davies. Students not only analyze theoretical essays but also use the theories as lenses through which to explore literary productions of women writers of Africa and the African diaspora in Europe and in the Americas, including Philip, Dangarembga, Morrison, Herron, Gayl Jones, Head, Cond&#233;, Brodber, Brand, Merle Collins, and Harriet Wilson. Cross-listed in African American studies, English, and women and gender studies. Strongly recommended: at least one literature course. Enrollment limited to 15. (Critical thinking.) S. Houchins.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C060">Women and Writing (C060)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="326"/><a name="PT/WS326"/><h4 class="crsname">PT/WS 326. The Politics of Authenticity.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Is there such a thing as an authentic self? If so, can politics help us realize it? In this writing-attentive course, students discuss what the politics of authenticity is or might be, how it has been conceptualized in American politics and Western political theory, and why it has become an object of widespread suspicion and continuing appeal. Students examine how authenticity has been posited and contested in three different domains: in the history of Western political thought; in feminist, queer, and transgender writings; and in discussions of race. Authors include Rousseau, Freud, Butler, Malcolm X, Yoshino, and Coates.  <span class="crsaddmod"/> Enrollment limited to 15. (Identities and Interests.) (Philosophical, Literary, and Legal Studies.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> One-time offering. N. Hagel.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C037">Identity, Race, and Ethnicity (C037)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="335"/><a name="WGST335"/><h4 class="crsname">WGST 335. Tobacco: Gender Matters.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In the opening episode of the popular television show <span class="cite">Mad Men</span>, entitled "Smoke Gets in Your Eyes," cigarettes feature as the primary signifier of mid-twentieth-century social norms and cultural divides. As <span class="cite">Mad Men</span> suggests, tobacco matters to our ability to understand the formation of cultural values and divides. In this reading- and research-intensive seminar, students use gender to examine the global history of tobacco production, consumption, and control. Through historical and comparative study they consider the role of tobacco in shaping ideas about gender, race, ethnicity, sexuality, and class. Topics include the political economy of tobacco, tobacco control movements, tobacco and human rights, and health equity. Prerequisite(s): WGST 100. Not open to students who have received credit for PT/WS s14. Enrollment limited to 15. (Community-Engaged Learning.) M. Plastas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="342"/><a name="INDC342"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 342. Performance, Narrative, and the Body.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines the politics of the body through the  inter/transdisciplinary frames of the narrative and performance, including the specific ways performance and narrative theories of the body and cultural practices operate in everyday life and social formations. Students examine how the "body" is performed and how narrative is constructed in a variety of different contexts such as race, gender, disease, sexuality, and culture. The course places narrative and performance at the center (rather than the margins) of inquiry, asking how far and how deeply performativity reaches into our lives and how performances construct our identities, differences, and our bodies: who we are and who we can become. Cross-listed in African American studies, anthropology, and women and gender studies. Prerequisite(s): WGST 100. Recommended background: course work in African American studies, American cultural studies, anthropology, politics, sociology, or women and gender studies. Enrollment limited to 15. M. Beasley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C037">Identity, Race, and Ethnicity (C037)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C085">Language and Literacy (C085)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="343"/><a name="PY/WS343"/><h4 class="crsname">PY/WS 343. Women, Culture, and Health.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course examines a variety of perspectives on women's health issues, including reproductive health, body image, sexuality, substance use and abuse, mental health, cancer, AIDS, heart disease, poverty, work, violence, access to health care, and aging. Each topic is examined in sociocultural context, and the complex relationship between individual health and cultural demands or standards is explored. Prerequisite(s): AS/PY 260; NS/PY 160 or 200; or PSYC 211, 215, 235, 242, or 303. (Diversity.) Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="344"/><a name="SP/WS344"/><h4 class="crsname">SP/WS 344. Gendering Social Awareness in Contemporary Spain.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">In this course, students use gender as the main category of analysis, paying particular attention to its interconnectedness with power. Carefully examining texts written by women in contemporary Spain, students explore the deliberate use of gender as a lens through which to understand different forms of domination&#8212;economic, political, and social. Prerequisite(s): one 200-level Spanish  course above SPAN 211. Recommended background: SPAN 230. Not open to first-years or sophomores. Instructor permission is required. F. L&#243;pez.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C024">Modern Europe (C024)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C089">Spanish in Tarragona (C089)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C060">Women and Writing (C060)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C018">Writing Spain (C018)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="347"/><a name="PT/WS347"/><h4 class="crsname">PT/WS 347. Gender and the State.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Two key questions provide the focus for this course: How does gender define citizenship, politics, and the state? What roles do states play in shaping notions of manhood and womanhood? Theoretical framings of gender and politics form the basis for reviewing processes through which gender constructions shape governace and policy as well as how state projects, such as economic development or war, influence gender relations. Using case studies from various national contexts, the course investigates how women (re)define their political roles, seek access to state power, and thus pursue visibility and authority within the state. Recommended background: one course in politics or women and gender studies. Enrollment limited to 15. (Governance and Conflict.) (Identities and Interests.) L. Hill.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="352"/><a name="INDC352"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC 352. Preserving the Vibration: Digitizing the Legacy of Vertamae Smart-Grosvenor.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course introduces public and digital humanities through the life and work of noted journalist, food anthropologist, and public broadcaster Vertamae Grosvenor. Public humanities is concerned with expanding academic discourse beyond academia and facilitating conversations on topics of humanistic inquiry with the community at large. Digital studies provide a plethora of unconventional ways to engage community in public dialogues for the greater good. Drawing from books, operas, NPR audio segments, interviews, cookbooks, and other artifacts of Grosvenor, students create and curate a digital archive. Themes include Gullah culture, African American migration, foodways, memoir, public memory, and monuments. Leading theories and methods of black feminism, material culture, race, food studies, new media and digital humanities are foregrounded. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, digital and computational studies, and women and gender studies. Prerequisite(s): AA/AC 119; AA/HI 243; AAS 100; ACS 100; AC/AV 340; AC/EN 395B; AV/WS 287; INDS 250 or 267; REL 255 or 270; or WGST 100.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2017.</span> Enrollment limited to 15. Normally offered every other year. M. Beasley.<br/></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="353"/><a name="AC/WS353"/><h4 class="crsname">AC/WS 353. Critical Theory/Critical Acts.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Critical theory unravels streams of repressive discourses and hierarchies in our contemporary world, and artists have fostered ruptures and fissures in everyday life. This seminar ponders the concept of "cultural worker" and laments the domain of theory by exploring the intersections between critical theory, art, and cultural politics. Students engage in the ruptures, the fragments of knowledge, and making sense of the residue of "social change" while not forgetting the problematization of the aesthetic. They consider U.S.-based interdisciplinary artists such as Thiong'o, Fusco, Ana Mediata, Tania Bruguera, David Hammon, Jay-Z, Pope.L, and Lady Gaga with critical theorists such as Fanon, Butler, Foucault, Phalen, Mu&#241;oz, Moten, Adorno, Barthes, Olkowski, and Benjamin. This seminar is based on close readings of theoretical texts and connecting those texts with contemporary cultural politics. Prerequisite(s): one of the following: AA/AC 119, ACS 100, AC/AV 340, AC/EN 395B, AV/WS 287, INDS 250 or 267, or WGST 100. Enrollment limited to 15. M. Beasley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C083">Material Culture (C083)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="355"/><a name="WGST355"/><h4 class="crsname">WGST 355. Gender and Technology.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Using gender as its central category of analysis, this advanced reading seminar examines historical and contemporary relationships among masculinities, femininities, and technologies. The course devotes special attention to those technologies used to define, alter, and enhance sexual identity, including dietary aids, cosmetics, psychopharmaceuticals, and hormone therapies. Throughout, the seminar seeks to illuminate structured relations of inequality, investigating the ways in which everyday material objects come to generate, enforce, and transform patterns of social stratification. Prerequisite(s): WGST 100 and two other courses listed in women and gender studies. R. Herzig.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C027">The Human Body (C027)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C083">Material Culture (C083)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ENVR">Environmental Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="356"/><a name="WGST356"/><h4 class="crsname">WGST 356. Marriage in America.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This reading-intensive seminar delves into the surprising history of ideas and practices of marriage in the United States and U.S. territories from the colonial era to the present.  Paying special attention to the idealization of intimate romantic love in contemporary popular culture, readings and discussions explore the interplay of citizenship, religion, consumption, labor, reproduction, sexuality, and racialized gender in an institution long at the center of American life. Prerequisite(s): WGST 100. Enrollment limited to 20. R. Herzig.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="360"/><a name="WGST360"/><h4 class="crsname">WGST 360. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study per semester.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="365"/><a name="WGST365"/><h4 class="crsname">WGST 365. Special Topics.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A course or seminar offered from time to time and reserved for a special topic selected by the Committee on Women and Gender Studies.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="377"/><a name="FR/WS377"/><h4 class="crsname">FR/WS 377. <span class="em">Colon/Colonis&#233;: R&#233;cits de l'Exp&#233;rience Nord-Africaine</span>.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course studies the colonial, postcolonial, and immigrant experience of North Africans as portrayed in Francophone literature. Readings include narratives and journals from the beginning of the colonial period in Algeria (1830), as well as the contemporary novels and discourse of feminists such as Assia Djebar, Malika Mokeddem, and Le&#239;la Sebbar. Gender is often highlighted as a category of analysis. Prerequisite(s): FRE 240, 250, or 251. Not open to students who have received credit for FRE 377. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C059">Colonialism (C059)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C022">Considering Africa (C022)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C034">French and Francophone Studies (C034)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C037">Identity, Race, and Ethnicity (C037)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C090">Middle East in Global Context (C090)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C032">Post/Colonial Issues in French and Spanish (C032)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C041">Racisms (C041)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="384"/><a name="ED/WS384"/><h4 class="crsname">ED/WS 384. Education in a Globalized World.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">We live in an era characterized by global flows of ideas and information, commodities, and people. In this course students examine the impacts of globalization and globalism upon educational policy and practices. Students explore how these transformative forces influence educative processes in different geographical, national, and cultural contexts. Topics address a set of concerns with enduring resonance to the field of educational studies,  including social inequity and change; relations of power; and constructions of race, gender, and social class. A thirty-hour field experience is required. <span class="crsaddmod"/> Not open to students who have received credit for ED/WS 280. Enrollment limited to 28. (Community-Engaged Learning.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> P. Buck.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C030">Children, Adolescents, School (C030)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C022">Considering Africa (C022)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C014">Globalization (C014)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395I"/><a name="SO/WS395I"/><h4 class="crsname">SO/WS 395I. Race, Class, Gender, and Family.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar focuses on current debates in the research and policy literatures on social inequality and family. Potential topics include family policy, poverty, domestic violence, the division of labor in households, reproduction, partnerships, parenting, children's experiences within families, and the integration of work and family. All of these topics are addressed with attention to the role of intersecting social inequalities in structuring family experiences, including race, class, gender, sexuality, and nation. Prerequisite(s): SOC 204 and 205. Enrollment limited to 15.  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> E. Kane.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C008">Class, Inequity, Poverty, and Justice (C008)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395P"/><a name="EN/WS395P"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/WS 395P. Worldly Women as Artists: Transnational Women Writers.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the question of what (or who) qualifies a woman to be regarded as an artist. Students also create an "artist portfolio" in the medium of their choice (visual arts, music, performance, photography, writing, etc.). In her novel, <span class="cite">To the Lighthouse (1927)</span>, Virginia Woolf resisted the prevailing sentiment that "women can't paint, women can't write." How do twentieth- and twenty-first-century women writers represent female artists? How have transnational female painters and writers described their own creative journeys either visually or in writing? How are the female artists&#8217; personae, themes, and challenges different from male perspectives on art? This seminar examines the fiction, paintings, poetry, and memoirs by Woolf, Dickinson, Kate Chopin, Christina Rossetti, Georgia O&#8217;Keeffe, Mary Cassatt, Frida Kahlo, Mary Oliver, Cathy Song, Gogi Saroj Pal,  Siona Benjamin, Shani Mootoo, and others. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Critical thinking.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> L. Dhingra.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C055">Beauty and Desire (C055)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C036">Color: Sight and Perception (C036)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C037">Identity, Race, and Ethnicity (C037)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C085">Language and Literacy (C085)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C040">Popular Culture (C040)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C061">Producing Culture: Arts and Audience (C061)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="395Z"/><a name="EN/WS395Z"/><h4 class="crsname">EN/WS 395Z. Arab American Feminisms.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course develops students' ability to look at the intersection of gender, ethnicity, politics, and sexuality. Students read theoretical and literary material as a catalyst for discussions of fiction, focusing on the way Arab American feminists articulate their unique theoretical concerns. Students read such scholars as Mohja Kahf, Rabab Abdulhadi, Nadine Naber, and Randa Jarrar. Students consider the critical triumphs and limitations of creative and theoretical work in discussing these subjects. Recommended background: previous course work in American cultural studies or women and gender studies. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. (Race, Ethnicity, or Diasporic Literature.)  <span class="gened">[W2]</span> T. Pickens.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C086">English (C086)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C060">Women and Writing (C060)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="400"/><a name="WGST400"/><h4 class="crsname">WGST 400. Junior-Senior Seminar.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This seminar is an advanced inquiry into feminist theories and methods. Drawing on work in several disciplinary fields, students ask how using gender as a category of analysis illuminates and/or changes the questions of other disciplines. Students also investigate the development of core theories and methods within women and gender studies. Required of all majors. Normally, one 400-level seminar is offered each year. Open to juniors and seniors only.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="400C"/><a name="WGST400C"/><h4 class="crsname">WGST 400C. Understanding Disease.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Intensive reading seminar examining the nature, causes, and consequences of human disease and illness. Students consider the birth of the germ theory and biomedical model of disease; the professionalization of medical care; and the role of class, nation, gender, and race in disease research and treatment. Prerequisite(s): five core courses in women and gender studies. Open to juniors and seniors only. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. R. Herzig.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="400D"/><a name="WGST400D"/><h4 class="crsname">WGST 400D. Global Feminisms.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">A seminar exploring feminist movements in an international context. Topics include divisions of labor and the "global assembly line," immigration and transnationalism, postcolonialism, and cultural imperialism. Students analyze local and international feminist activism and examine multiple definitions of gender, race, ethnicity, and nationhood. Prerequisite(s): five core courses in women and gender studies. Open to juniors and seniors only. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. R. Herzig, L. Hill.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="457"/><a name="WGST457"/><h4 class="crsname">WGST 457. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The research and writing of an extended essay or report, or the completion of a creative project, under the supervision of a faculty member. Majors normally register for WGST 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both WGST 457 in the fall semester.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="458"/><a name="WGST458"/><h4 class="crsname">WGST 458. Senior Thesis.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">The research and writing of an extended essay or report, or the completion of a creative project, under the supervision of a faculty member. Majors normally register for WGST 458 in the winter semester. Majors writing an honors thesis register for both WGST 457 in the fall semester and 458 in the winter semester.  <span class="gened">[W3]</span> Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s12"/><a name="PT/WSs12"/><h4 class="crsname">PT/WS s12. Gender, War, and Peace.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course uses gender as an analytical tool to examine the history of war and peace. How do war and militarization construct masculinities and femininities? What types of roles have women played in the making of war and in the making of peace? How has gender socialization influenced people's analysis of and participation in war and in peace activism? What are the gender politics of the politics of war and of peacemaking? How is gender deployed in current war zones and in current movements for peace? Recommended background: WGST 100. Not open to students who have received credit for PT/WS 220. Enrollment limited to 30. (Governance and Conflict.) (Political Economy.) M. Plastas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C064">Conflict and Threat: War and Disease (C064)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s14"/><a name="PT/WSs14"/><h4 class="crsname">PT/WS s14. Gender and Tobacco.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the sociohistorical complexities of tobacco and the political economies of tobacco production, consumption, and regulation. The course focuses on how gender, race, and class influence tobacco industry policies, tobacco control procedures, the health and economic impact of tobacco on communities, and the strategies of grassroots and transnational activists in tobacco regulation movements. Recommended background: course work in women and gender studies. Not open to students who have received credit for WGST 335. Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. M. Plastas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C065">Public Health (C065)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s18"/><a name="INDCs18"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC s18. Wilde Times: Scandal, Celebrity, and the Law.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Oscar Wilde, an icon today, was popular in his own time as well. His relationship with Alfred Douglas was an open secret despite the fact that homosexuality was at the time a criminal offence. Indeed, Wilde&#8217;s sexuality was tolerated until he sued Douglas&#8217;s irascible father for libel. This course begins with the 1895 trials, seeking to understand cultures of sexuality in a period notorious for sexual repression, and contextualizing issues they raise of scandal and the law, celebrity, gender, and sexuality. Designed to encourage independent research, the course guides students through the research process, drawing to the fore histories often hidden from view. Cross-listed in European studies, history, and women and gender studies.  <span class="crsaddmod">New course beginning Winter 2017.</span> Open to first-year students. Enrollment limited to 30. C. Shaw.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C013">Law and Society (C013)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=EUS">European Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s19"/><a name="INDCs19"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC s19. Food, Culture, and Performance.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This interdisciplinary seminar examines the idea of cultural engagement through food. Students explore the meanings of food and eating across cultures, with particular attention to how people define themselves socially, symbolically, and politically through food consumption practices. Students in this community-based course collaborate with Nezinscot Farm exploring themes of gathering, homesteading, and biodynamic farming.  The course develops research and writing skills, introduces visual and performance theories of culture, and fosters an understanding of the importance of food and its relationship to identity construction, histories, and cultural literacy. The course culminates in a  performative meal.  Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, anthropology, and women and gender studies.
 Enrollment limited to 20. (Community-Engaged Learning.) M. Beasley.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C091">Knowledge, Action, and the Public Good (C091)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C083">Material Culture (C083)</a></li></ul></div><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=AAS">African American Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=ACS">American Cultural Studies</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s22"/><a name="SP/WSs22"/><h4 class="crsname">SP/WS s22. Militants, Queers, and Thugs: Latino and African American Masculinities and Social Movements.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students engage questions about Latino and African American masculinities in the contemporary moment. How do the politics of ethnicity, gender, sexuality, and race complicate social perceptions of Latino and African American men? How do African American and Latino men take hold of narrative to construct and negotiate their gender identities?  How do social-movement narratives contest stereotypical notions of Latino and black masculinity? Students analyze Puerto Rican, Dominican, and African American fiction and testimonial narrative about masculinity during the 1960s and 1970s in New York City. Students employ intersectionality, queer theory, and racial theories to consider the relationship and tensions between militancy and queerness in the formation of Latino, Afro-Latino, and African American masculinities. Conducted in English. Enrollment limited to 15. Instructor permission is required. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C089">Spanish in Tarragona (C089)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s27"/><a name="PT/WSs27"/><h4 class="crsname">PT/WS s27. Feminisms of the 1970s and 1980s.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">This course explores the rise of multiple feminist theories and forms of activism during the 1970s and 1980s. Students critically examine the genealogy of the conceptualization of "second-wave feminism," and explore the role of gay, Chicano, and black liberation, civil rights, and labor struggles on the development of feminist thinking and action. The course pays particular attention to how feminists of this period addressed questions of U.S. foreign policy in Vietnam, Central America, and South Africa; the nuclear arms race; and U.S. domestic race relations. Students read from primary source material and study the literature produced by Marxist feminisms, black feminisms, lesbian feminisms, liberal feminisms, and radical feminisms. Recommended background: WGST 100. Enrollment limited to 25. (Identities and Interests.) (Institutional Politics.) M. Plastas.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C009">Queer Studies (C009)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s32"/><a name="PT/WSs32"/><h4 class="crsname">PT/WS s32. Global Flows: Work, Sex, and Care.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Globalization refers to processes underlying profound changes in contemporary life from the corporate boardroom to the family bedroom.  What do women and sex have to do with the global political economy?  How does gender&#8212;the social organization of sexual difference&#8212;shape the future "world without borders"?   In what ways might global restructuring depend on women and gender relations?  This course examines how sexual divisions of labor, power, and decision making shape flows of money, jobs, goods, and people across borders.  Students use interdisplinary perspectives from political economy, women and gender studies, and film studies to consider gender as an aspect of global processes of change and transformation in international flows, connections, production and consumption. Enrollment limited to 20. (Identities and Interests.) L. Hill.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C014">Globalization (C014)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C084">Learning and Teaching (C084)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s37"/><a name="INDCs37"/><h4 class="crsname">INDC s37. Afrofuturism and the Black Speculative Imagination: A Study of Octavia Butler.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Of the 1969 moonwalk, George Clinton said that once man defied gravity, all bets were off. The music mogul later went on to defy gravity by "funk-ifying" the world. Yet Clinton's ideas are not without precedent in African American culture. In this course, students examine the aesthetic that came to be known as Afrofuturism as an outlet for African American literary and artistic expression. Students focus on the work of Octavia Butler and her volcanic influence, fame, and talent. Since her work dovetails with Clinton's anti-gravity stance and forms a locus for black speculative fiction in particular and speculative fiction in general, they study a selection of her novels, short fiction, and own words as well as secondary critical and theoretical material. Cross-listed in African American studies, American cultural studies, English, and women and gender studies. Prerequisite(s): one course in African American studies, American cultural studies, or English. Recommended background: course work in the natural sciences. Not open to students who have received credit for AA/EN 259. Enrollment limited to 30. T. Pickens.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".gecDetails">Concentrations</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox gecDetails">
			<p>This course is referenced by the following General Education Concentrations</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C038">Diasporas (C038)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C037">Identity, Race, and Ethnicity (C037)</a></li><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=GEC#C060">Women and Writing (C060)</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
<div class="Course"><a name="s50"/><a name="WGSTs50"/><h4 class="crsname">WGST s50. Independent Study.</h4><span class="CourseDesc">Students, in consultation with a faculty advisor, individually design and plan a course of study or research not offered in the curriculum. Course work includes a reflective component, evaluation, and completion of an agreed-upon product. Sponsorship by a faculty member in the program/department, a course prospectus, and permission of the chair are required. Students may register for no more than one independent study during a Short Term.  Normally offered every year. Staff.<br/><a href="#" class="gecIntProgramToggle" data-togglebox=".idpDetails">Interdisciplinary Programs</a><div class="catCourseInfoBox idpDetails">
			<p>This course counts toward the following Interdisciplinary Program(s)</p>
			<ul><li><a href="/catalog/?s=current&amp;a=renderDept&amp;d=WGST">Women and Gender Studies</a></li></ul></div></span></div>
